<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
<b>Other</b> is a special type of resource.  Unlike all other resources, it doesn't correspond to a 
specific identifiable real-world concept.  Instead, it's a placeholder for any resource-like concept 
that isn't already defined in the HL7 specification.
</p>

<p>
The Other resource is intended for use in two circumstances:
</p>
<ol>
  <li>When an implementer needs a resource concept that is likely to be defined by HL7 in the future but
   they have not yet done so (due to bandwidth issues, lack of sufficient requirements, lower 
   prioritization, etc.)</li>
  <li>When the resource concept falls "outside the 99%" - i.e. less than 1% of the systems that use FHIR 
  are likely to ever make use of the resource.  To keep the specification manageable, it cannot incorporate
  every esoteric requirement that might be needed in some implementation somewhere.  This set of resources
  likely won't ever be officially defined in HL7.</li>
</ol>

<p>
There's also a third circumstance: An implementer wishes to convey information that could/should be conveyed
using a standard resource, however they want to represent the information in a custom format that isn't
aligned with the official resource's elements.  While this resource would be the preferred way of meeting that
use-case because it will at least be wire-format compatible, such a use would not be conformant because
making use of the Other resource would prevent the healthcare-related information from being safely processed,
queried and analyzed by other conformant systems.
</p>

<p>
Implementers don't really need to be concerned with one of the two categories their desired resource fits
within.  If they need a resource and it doesn't yet exist, they should use Other.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Other defines only a minimal set of data elements - those necessary to identify what kind of resource it
represents and those necessary to support resource <a href="extras.html#compartments">compartmenting</a>.  All other data elements
are represented using the <a href="extensibility.html">extension</a> mechanism.
</p>
</div>

</div>
