<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
A flag is typically presented as a label in a prominent location in a patient chart to notify the clinician of potential issues, 
though it may also appear in other contexts.  E.g. instructions to a radiology technician. The information in the flag will 
usually be derived from the record, and therefore, for a thorough and careful clinician, will be redundant.  However, given the volume 
of information frequently found in patients' records and the potentially serious consequences of losing sight of some facts, this 
redundancy is deemed appropriate.  As well, some flags may reflect information not captured by any other resource in the record.  
(E.g. "Patient has large dog at home")
</p>
<p>
In line with its purpose, a flag is concise, highlighting a small set of high-priority issues among the much larger set of 
data in the chart. Readers who want more detail should consult the chart.  Caution should be exercised in creating Flag instances.
If entries are created for information that could be gleaned in a sufficiently timely fashion by reviewing the patient record, 
the flag list will itself become overwhelming and will cease to serve its intended purpose.
</p>
<p>
Flags are expected to persist in a record for some period of time and are, at most, targeted to particular types of practitioners
or to practitioners in particular system.  
</p>
<p>Examples of issues that might appear in flags:</p>
<ul>
<li>Risks to the patient (functional risk of falls, spousal restraining order, latex allergy)</li>
<li>Patient's needs for special accommodations (hard of hearing, need for easy-open caps)</li>
<li>Risks to providers (dog in house, patient may bite, infection control precautions)</li>
<li>Administrative concerns (incomplete information, pre-payment required due to credit risk)</li>
</ul> 
<p>
Examples of issues that should not appear in flags:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Potential allergy or drug interaction to planned therapy (use <a href="contraindication.html">Contraindication</a>)</li>
<li>Known adverse reaction to a substance (use <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a>)</li>
</ul>    
<p>
Note that we include "latex allergy" in the "in scope" list, and "allergy" in the "not in scope" list. The Flag resource is not 
designed to replace the normal order checking process, and one should not expect to see all allergies in Flags. However, if there 
is an activity that might occur prior to careful evaluation of the record (e.g., donning of latex gloves) and that activity might 
pose a risk to the patient, that is the sort of eventuality the Flag is intended to support.
</p>
<p>
Specific guidelines about what type of information is appropriate to expose using Flag, as well as what categories of individuals 
should see particular flags, will vary by interoperability community.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Flags may highlight a highly condensed view of information found in the <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a>, 
<a href="condition.html">Condition</a>, <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> and possibly 
other resources.  A <a href="extension-flag-detail.html">common extension</a> allows the linkage of a Flag to the supporting detail resource.
The purpose of these other resources is to provide detailed clinical information.  The purpose of a Flag is to alert practitioners to 
information that is important to influence their interaction with a Patient prior to detailed review of the record.
</p>
<p>
Flags are not used to convey information to a specific individual or organization (e.g. an abnormal lab result reported to the ordering 
clinician, reporting of an adverse reaction to a regulatory authority).  These are handled using the 
<a href="communicationrequest.html">CommunicationRequest</a> and the <a href="communication.html">Communication</a> resources.
</p>
<p>
Flags are not raised as a result of a reported or proposed action (e.g. drug-drug interactions, duplicate therapy warnings).  
These would be handled using <a href="contraindication.html">Contraindication</a>.
</p>
</div>

</div>
