<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<a name="notes"></a>
<h2>
Notes
</h2>
<ul>
  <li>
  There is no address on the PractitionerRole as the location that is defined here contains the address.<br/>
  This prevents having to duplicate the address values across multiple resources.
  </li>
</ul>
<a name="identifier"></a>
<h3>
Identifier Expectations
</h3>
<p>
The question whether qualification.identifiers should be repeated in .identifier or not depends on the usage.<br/>
Some systems will provide e.g. license numbers in Practitioner.identifier, others will provide them in Practitioner.qualification.identifier, and others might provide them in both. 
The difference is that a license number in Practitioner.identifier doesn't convey anything about the status of the license, while qualification should (though it might not be up-to-date).
</p>
<a name="mult-locations"></a>
<h2>
Multiple Locations in a PractitionerRole
</h2>
<p>
  As briefly noted in the boundaries and relationships section the PractitionerRole resource can be used
  to represent multiple locations in the one resource instance, however this should be done with care.
  When representing multiple locations in an instance, and/or multiple specialties, all details apply
  to all locations. Using that approach you cannot differentiate a different contact number, different
  availabilities, or different services at each location.<br/>
  Hence maintaining these records needs to ensure that when changing a value, such as availability, 
  it applies to all locations. If different values are required for the different locations, then a new 
  instance will need to be created, and then split as appropriate. Existing resources referencing the
  original PractitionerRole instance will need to be updated to refer to the appropriate record.<br/>
  For this reason we expect that it will be common to profile the location element down to a single location,
  simplifying overall usage, and the availabilities are clear that they apply to this location, and any
  referenced healthcare services.
</p>
</div>
