<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
PractitionerRole covers the recording of the location and types of services that Practitioners are able to provide
for an organization.
</p>
<p>
The role, specialty, Location telecom and HealthcareService properties can be repeated if required in other instances
of the PractitionerRole. Some systems record a collection of service values for a single location, others record the 
single service and the list of locations it is available. Both are acceptable options for representing this data.<br/>
Where availability, telecom, or other details are not the same across all healthcareservices, or locations 
a seperate PractitionerRole instance should be created.
</p>
<p>
For use cases where an organization has activities where a practitioner is not defined/pre-allocated for a specific role 
(e.g. an un-named surgeon at XYZ Hospital), a PractitionerRole resource can be used with an empty Practitioner property, 
and the other relevant role properties populated - i.e. code, organization.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
	Qualifications (from the Practitioner resource) do not imply a Role, but might be considered when an Organization 
  allocates practitioners to roles within their organization, and could provide useful information (such as expiry information)
  which could need to be tracked in some situations to ensure they continue to be eligible for a specific role.
</p>
<p>
  The <a href="careteam.html">CareTeam</a> resource is also often used to provide details of a role that a practitioner is
  allocated to perform, but is usually scoped to a much finer granularity of care, and often within the specific context
  of a <a href="patient.html">Patient</a>, or functional role (e.g. Crisis planning team). In contrast the PractitionerRole
  is used in a more general sense to cover all the places that the practitioner is allocated to work (and specific details
  relevant to that role - such as a specific contact number, or electronic services endpoint).
</p>
<p>
When referencing a practitioner from clinical (or other) content where the organization and role are important to the context 
of the reference to the practitioner, then a reference to the PractitionerRole should be used.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Practitioner performs different roles within the same or even different organizations. Depending on jurisdiction and custom, 
it may be necessary to maintain a specific Practitioner Resource for each such role or have a single Practitioner with multiple roles.
The role can be limited to a specific period, after which authorization for this role ends. Note that the represented organization
need not necessarily be the (direct) employer of a Practitioner.
</p>
</div>

</div>
