<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<h2>Notes</h2>
<p>
<ul>
<li>Multiple Organizations or Practitioners may provide services at a Location. These references are not kept in Location, but can be found
in the models for <a href="organization.html">Organization</a> and <a href="practitioner.html">Practitioner</a> instead.</li>
<li>Locations may range from whole buildings to cabinets; it is possible to relate smaller Locations to their containing bigger Location 
using the Location.partOf element.</li>
<li>Location.position is expressed using the same syntax, datum and reference system as used in Google Earth's KML files,
see <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/kml">Google/OGS's KML</a>.</li>
</ul>
</p>

<h3>Location Mode</h3>
<p>The Location.mode element can be used to indicate whether a Location resource represents a specific (potentially identifiable) Location ('instance'), 
or a class of Locations ('kind'). Especially Resources capturing orders, resource scheduling, plans and definitions may refer to Locations in 'kind' mode. 
For these domains, it is often not necessary to refer to a specific Location, but rather to a class of Locations. An example of this is found in planning, 
where we need to allocate an "isolation room" for a patient, or need to dispatch "an ambulance" at a certain time. In these cases it is not important 
exactly which isolation room or ambulance is allocated, and it is sufficient to just indicate a 'kind' of Location.</p>
<p>Note that 'kind' should not be used to represent Locations where an actual instance of a Location was involved, but identifying information is missing.
E.g. when a patient arrived 'by ambulance', but it is not known by which ambulance, this should be represented using a Location in 'instance' mode with a
missing identifier, not a Location of 'kind' ambulance.</p>
<p>
Some of Location's data elements are only relevant when mode is 'instance' and should not be used when mode is 'kind':
<ul>
<li>Location.identifier</li>
<li>Location.telecom</li>
<li>Location.address</li>
<li>Location.position</li>
<li>Location.status</li>
<li>Location.managingOrganization</li>
</ul>
</p>
</div>
