<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"></a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p style="border:2px; border-style:solid; border-color:#999999; padding: 1em; border-radius: 4px 4px 4px 4px;"><b><i>For an overview of this resource and others in the Medication Definition domain, also see the <a href="medication-definition-module.html">module page</a></i></b></p>
		<p>
			A material used in the preparation of a medicinal/pharmaceutical product, within the context of a particular use or role. 
		</p>
		<p>
			An ingredient is part of a product, either alone or in combination with other ingredients. 
			It is essentially a substance with the addition of the specific role it is playing in the product, or in preparation of the product
			which may include whether it is an active or inactive 
			substance and what the strength is (the quantity of substance compared to the whole product).
			The ingredient is represented in the context of a given product, because its role and strength are a function of what it is used in/for. 
			It is expected that the same substance used in a different role, or with a different strength, would be a different Ingredient resource instance.
			Resource instances may however be shared by very similar products (e.g. different pack sizes of the same "product").
		</p>
		<p>
			Some other resources, such as <a href="medication.html">Medication</a> and <a href="substance.html">Substance</a> 
			allow specifying a basic ingredient representation. When more detail is needed such as for manufacturing or regulatory use, 
			use the Ingredient resource.
		</p>
		<p>
			Ingredient is represented as a resource, instead of, for example, a backbone or a datatype within other resources, 
			due to some practical considerations for certain use cases.
			In some situations, an ingredient could have been represented "in line" within another resource 
			(e.g. embedded within MedicinalProductDefiniton or ManufacturedItemDefinition).			
			However there are cases where it is necessary to refer to an ingredient from another resource - for example when the 
			ingredient associated with a product also has an authorization, or when a multi-part tablet needs to state which ingredient 
			is contained in which component of that tablet (as well as linking the ingredient to the whole tablet and/or the whole product).
			These cases can only be served by representing the ingredient as an externally referenceable entity, that can be linked from other resources, 
			hence the rationale for Ingredient being a resource in its own right.
			If such cases are not in scope of a given project, and it is preferred to avoid ingredient being a separate resource, 
			then there is the option for that project to represent an ingredient using a contained Ingredient resource. 
			Even simpler situations, where only a coded or free text ingredient is necessary, can use attributes such as MedicinalProductDefinition.ingredient. 
		</p>
		
	</div>
</div>
