<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<a name="use"></a>
<h3>Base Resource</h3>

<p>
A compartment implicitly always includes the resource that is a 'root' of the   compartment
e.g. the resource <code>Patient/123</code> is the root resource of the Patient Compartment
for <code>Patient/123</code>. 
Thus an operation that retrieves everything within the compartment will include the base 
resource; a scope that grants access to everything within the compartment will grant access 
to the resource; etc. 
</p>

<a name="use"></a>
<h3>Using Compartments</h3>

<p>
As an example of compartment usage, to retrieve a list of a patient's conditions, use the URL:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Patient/[id]/Condition
</pre>
<p>
Additional search parameters can be defined, such as this hypothetical search for 
acute conditions:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Patient/[id]/Condition?code:in=http://hspc.org/ValueSet/acute-concerns
</pre>
<p>
Note that as searches, these are syntactic variations on these two search
URLs respectively:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Condition?patient=[id]
  GET [base]/Condition?patient=[id]&amp;code:in=http://hspc.org/ValueSet/acute-concerns
</pre>
<p>
The outcome of a compartment search is the same as the equivalent normal search. 
For example, both these searches return the same outcome if there is no patient 333:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Patient/333/Condition
  GET [base]/Condition?patient=333
</pre>
<p>
Whether the patient doesn't exist, or the user has no access to the patient,
both these searches return an empty bundle with no matches. Some systems 
will include an operation outcome warning that there is no matching patient.
</p>
<p>
However, there is a key difference in functionality between compartment based searches 
and direct searches with parameters. Consider this search:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Patient/[id]/Communication
</pre>
<p>
Because the definition of the <a href="compartmentdefinition-patient.html">patient compartment</a> for 
<a href="communication.html">Communication </a> says that a Communication resource is in the 
patient compartment if the subject, sender, or recipient is the patient, the compartment
search is actually the same as the union of these 3 searches:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Communication?subject=[id]
  GET [base]/Communication?sender=[id]
  GET [base]/Communication?recipient=[id]
</pre>
<p>
There is no way to do this as a single search, except by using the <a href="search_filter.html">_filter</a>:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Communication?_filter=subject re [id] or sender re [id] or recipient re [id]
</pre>
<p>
Further details of searching by compartment are <a href="http.html#vsearch">described under the search operation</a>.
As a search related operation, the assignment of resources to compartments is only based on 
the current version of any of the resources involved. Note that <a href="references.html#contained">contained</a>
patient resources cannot create a patient compartment of their own. 
</p>

<p>
Note that while this specification describes how to use the compartment syntax to find resources 
that are logically associated with the compartment, the compartment is not part of the
identity of the resource. E.g. the response to the following is not defined by this specification:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Patient/[patient-id]/Condition/[resource-id]
</pre>
<p>
The response for write operations (PUT/DELETE/PATCH) are also not defined by this
specification. Nor is the response to a POST defined:
</p>
<pre>
  POST [base]/Patient/[patient-id]/Condition
</pre>
<p>
There is no expectation for servers to support either read or write 
to such URLs.
</p>

<a name="logical"></a>
<h3>Logical Meaning of Compartments</h3>
<p>
Compartments may be used explicitly, like this, but can also be used implicitly. For instance,
if a FHIR server is providing a patient view of a record, the authorized user associated
with use of the FHIR RESTful API may be limited to accessing records from the
compartment instance(s) logically associated with their identity. Irrespective of whether
compartments are being used explicitly or implicitly, servers will need to make arrangements
to make some resources with no direct link to a patient available to the client (medications, 
substances, binaries, etc.).
</p>
<p>
Note that resources may cross between compartments, or interlink them. Examples of 
this would be where a <a href="diagnosticreport.html">Diagnostic Report</a> identifies  
a subject, but an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> it references identifies
a different subject, or where a <a href="list.html">List</a> resource references
items that identify different subjects. Such cross-linking may arise for 
many valid reasons, including:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Cases where subject records are inter-linked - Transplants, Perinatal care, family therapy etc.</li>
 <li>Workflow management where action lists link multiple patients and/or practitioners</li>
</ul>
<p>
Given the wide variety of use cases and contexts in which FHIR is used, compartments 
do not define how cross-linking is handled. Systems may reject resources, remove them 
from both compartments, or place them in both, or act in some other fashion.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="graphdefinition.html">graph definition</a> resource provides a method
by which rules about cross-linking may be made and enforced.
</p>
<p>
It is at the discretion of the server whether to include resources in a compartment when
the reference to the resource that establishes the compartment is in an extension.
</p>

<p>
Some resources are not in any compartment, e.g. <a href="medication.html">Medication</a>, 
<a href="substance.html">Substance</a>, <a href="location.html">Location</a>. These resources are not linked directly to a patient 
or authored record, and are sometimes called 'master files'. Servers will need to make 
arrangements to make these resources available to the clients that are limited to 
particular compartments. For example, a Medication resource describes a medication itself 
and does not link to a patient; however, a resource such as MedicationAdministration 
connects the Medication (details of what was administered) to the patient (for whom was 
it administered), and so is required to interpret the administration.
</p>

<h2>Defining New Compartments</h2>
<p>
Compartments are defined and added to the list above when implementer 
communities identify them as common access points for data. As described 
below, compartments have both syntactical and logical consequences, and
both these aspects of their functionality are evaluated when deciding
whether to define compartments. 
</p>

</div>
