<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Each resource may belong to one or more logical compartments. A compartment is a logical 
grouping of resources which share a common property. Compartments have two principal roles:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Function as an access mechanism for finding a set of related resources quickly</li>
 <li>Provide a definitional basis for applying access control to resources quickly</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Note:</b></p>
<p>
At present, compartment definitions can <i>only</i> be defined by HL7 International.  This is because
their existence creates significant impact on the behavior of servers.
</p>
</div> 

<div> 
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2> 
<p>
Compartment definitions describe how particular compartment instances are named and identified,
and how systems know which resources are in the compartment. The following compartments are 
defined by this specification:
</p>
<%compartmentlist%>
<p>
The full definitions of these compartments are published as <code>CompartmentDefinition</code>
resources. Servers typically do not support the full definition of a compartment, and are not 
required to. Systems may publish <code>CompartmentDefinition</code> resources so that
other systems may make use of compartments properly.
</p>
<ul>
 <li>CompartmentDefinitions are used by <a href="capabilitystatement.html">CapabilityStatement</a> instances for specifying how resources are accessed</li>
</ul>
<ul>
 <li><a href="graphdefinition.html">GraphDefinition</a> also provides a mechanism for grouping resources, though it does not provide an additional search mechanism.
 Inclusion of resources in a <a href="graphdefinition.html">GraphDefinition</a> supports more complex criteria for inclusion than that allowed by CompartmentDefinition.</li>
</ul>

</div> 



</div>
