<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The GraphDefinition resource provides a formal computable definition of a graph of resources - that is, a coherent set of resources that form 
a graph by following references. The Graph Definition resource defines a set and makes rules about the set.
The GraphDefinition resource can be used to:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Summarize a set of profiles on resources</li>
 <li>Define a graph of resources to return in a query</li>
 <li>Define a graph of resources to include in a document</li>
 <li>Document rules about the relationship between a set of resources e.g. must all resources concern the same patient?</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
There is a close relationship between <a href="structuredefinition.html">Profiles</a> and 
<code>GraphDefinitions</code>:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A <a href="structuredefinition.html">StructureDefinition</a> defines a profile, and profiles can make rules about the relationships between resources. A carefully defined set of profiles implies part of what is in a GraphDefinition</li>
 <li>A GraphDefinition defines rules about the relationships between resources, and in so doing, implies some constraints that would need to be represented in their profiles</li>
 <li>Like <a href="compartmentdefinition.html">CompartmentDefinition</a>, GraphDefinition allows defining a grouping of resources and may be used for security access permissions.
 However, GraphDefinitions do not define additional query capabilities and is much more limited in how membership in the collection is defined
 (all resources that are part of a Compartment must expose a search parameter of the same name).</li>
</ul>
<p>
Profiles and Graph Definitions can be used together, or separately. When used together, they should
be consistent. Note, though, that a graph definition may contain a subset or a superset of the relationships
explicitly described in the profiles it refers to.
</p>
<p>
It is possible that in some circumstances, a graph definition makes incompatible rules with 
the Profiles it refers to - in this case, no graph if resources will meet the constraints expressed. 
Applications should - but are not required - detect when such incompatibilities arise.
</p>
</div>

</div>
