<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h3>Using GraphDefinitions</h3>
<p>
The GraphDefinition resource can be used to:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Summarize a set of profiles on resources</li>
 <li>Define a graph of resources to return in a query</li>
 <li>Define a graph of resources to include in a document</li>
 <li>Document rules about the relationship between a set of resources e.g. must all resources concern the same patient?</li>
</ul>

<a name="summary"> </a>
<h4>Summarize a set of profiles on resources</h4>
<p>
FHIR resources are relatively granular. In many/most cases, many resources 
are needed to handle any particular task. A typical example of this is a complex
diagnostic report: it will start with a DiagnosticReport, which will link
to a set of panels (Observation resources), each of which link to a set of 
Observation resources for atomic data items.
</p>
<p>
One way to represent this is to profile each of the resources, creating 
100s of profiles, and then leave it to the user to infer the overall pattern
of the report from the detailed profiles for each observation in the report. 
But it's not easy to see the forest for the trees. A GraphDefinition can 
summarise the overall picture and present a summary to the user. 
</p>
<p>
Here's <a href="http://fhir.hl7.org.au/fhir/rcpa/pprofiles.html">an example</a> of 
the kind of summary this represents. (Todo: make this an actual graph definition,
and clone into the main spec)
</p>

<a name="fetch"> </a>
<h4>Fetching a graph of resources</h4>
<p>
As another example of using many resources, to describe a medication
dispense, an application needs, in addition to the MedicationDispense resource
that describes the actual dispense, and application will typically retrieve 
resources for the patient, provider, organizations, and the prescription for
the dispense. 
</p>
<p>
A client can retrieve a single resource:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/MedicationDispense/example
</pre>
<p>
Then, when it reads the returned resource, if can fetch the referenced resources: 
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/Patient/example
  GET [base]/Practitioner/example
  GET [base]/MedicationRequest/example
  ... etc
</pre>
<p>
This is a very inefficient way to retrieve all the required resources. An alternative 
approach is to do a search, and _include the required resources:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/MedicationDispense?_id=example
    &amp;_include=MedicationDispense.authorizingPrescription
    &amp;_include=MedicationDispense.subject
</pre>
<p>
But scaling up this approach to fetch a full package with its dependencies
becomes increasingly difficult as the package gets deeper. A graph definition
can be used instead of inform the server what to return as part of the search:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [base]/MedicationDispense?_id=example&amp;_graph=med-package
</pre>
<p>
This is a reference to the local graph package 'med-package', with the 
intent that the server returns the graph as outlined by the definition.
In this case, the graph definition would look approximately like this:
</p>
<pre>
MedicationDispense
  .subject
  .context
  .performer.actor
  .authorizingPrescription
     .requester.agent 
  .substitution.responsibleParty
</pre>

<a name="document"> </a>
<h4>Building a document</h4>
<p>
A very similar issue applies when building a document using the <a href="composition-operations.html#document">$document 
operation</a>. A document must include all the resources linked directly from the composition, but 
whether to include additional linked resources is at the discretion of the document author. How does
the user inform the $document operation which linked resources to include? One option is a boolean flag
for including <b>all</b> linked data, but this may be extensive - up to an entire patient record - and 
may include resources that are not desired.
</p>
<p>
An operation can use a graph definition as a parameter to the $document operation:
</p>
<pre>
GET [base]/Composition/example/$document?graph=example
</pre>
<p>
This tells the server to include the graph of resources defined 
in the <a href="graphdefinition-example.html">example GraphDefinition</a> - in this case,
any resources referred to from lists, when the section content is a list.
</p>

<a name="rules"> </a>
<h4>Document Relationship rules</h4>
<p>
One important question about the use of resources is cross-resource consistency. 
For example, if an Observation refers to both a Patient and Encounter, does the 
Encounter have to refer to the same patient? 
</p>
<p>
In general, the answer to this is that it usually should - the record needs to be 
consistent. However there are edge cases where the references may differ. For 
example, with regard to patient references, they may differ for:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Health Records concerning mother and baby</li>
 <li>Organ Transplants</li>
 <li>Counselling, particularly family counselling</li>
</ul>
<p>
Other reasons for the references to differ - mixing records about the same patient
from different servers, or specific records about patients mixed with records
about groups of patients (particularly common in veterinarian care).
</p>
<p>
The <code>GraphDefinition</code> resource allows for compartment consistency rules
to be made regarding the links between resources. For each link in the graph, the
graph definition can make a rule about the compartment consistency. The rule 
can specify one of the following consistencies:
</p>
<table class="codes">
<tr><td><b>Code</b></td><td><b>Meaning</b></td></tr>
<tr><td>identical</td><td>The compartment must be identical (the same literal reference)</td></tr>
<tr><td>matching</td><td>The compartment must be the same - the record must be about the same patient, but the reference may be different</td></tr>
<tr><td>different</td><td>The compartment must be different</td></tr>
<tr><td>custom</td><td>The compartment rule is defined in the accompanying FHIRPath expression</td></tr>
</table>
<p>
Todo: how would this be validated? - where is the graph referred to?
</p>

</div>
