<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <div>
                <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
                <p>DeviceAlert represents a single alert condition detected and signaled by a device to create clinician&apos;s awareness of a patient safety risk that needs to be addressed.</p>
                <p>The device is often a communicating, physical, patient-connected health/medical device operating in an acute care setting (e.g., patient monitor, ventilator, infusion pump, etc.). However, Software as a Medical Device (SaMD), non-patient connected devices, and other Health Software &#x201C;apps,&#x201D; as well as lower acuity care settings (e.g., a fall detector app running on a patient&apos;s mobile device at home) are in scope as well.</p>
                <p>Alerts can relate to physiological (e.g., Patient Lucy has a low SpO2), technical (e.g., Infusion Pump #2 has a fluid line occlusion), or other conditions. Alerts can also  have different priorities based on the hazard&apos;s severity and urgency of clinicians&apos; action, ranging from High (e.g., a life-threatening condition requiring immediate response) to Advisory (e.g., information to create contextual awareness without requiring timely response).</p>
                <p> DeviceAlert is intended for capturing device alert information for documentation and display purposes (e.g., to enable analytics towards alarm noise reduction opportunities). DeviceAlert is not intended for controlling alarms (e.g., remote pausing the audio of an alarm signal). Additionally, any actions that follow from the alert are not part of the resource.</p>
                <p>The specifics of an alert are preferably described using medical device nomenclature from the <em>Alerts and events</em> partition of the ISO/IEEE 11073-10101 standard for Medical Device Communication Nomenclature. DeviceAlert is also aligned with the ISO/IEC 60601-1-8 medical device alarm systems standard. Internationally, medical device regulatory agencies require conformance to ISO/IEC 60601-1-8. Moreover, DeviceAlert is aligned with other standards and specifications such as the Gemini (IHE/HL7) SDPi-Alerting (SDPi-A) Profile, the IHE Alert Communication Management (ACM) profile, and other ISO/IEEE 11073 standards from the Service-Oriented Point-of-Care Medical Device Communication (SDC) standards family.</p>
                <p>DeviceAlert models both the concept of alert condition detection as well as its related signaling. Both concepts are combined in one resource due to their high, complex state dynamics and strong interrelationship. For instance, the &#x201C;Presence&#x201D; state of an alert signal (e.g., monitor beeps or not) depends on the &#x201C;Presence&#x201D; state of the triggering condition, the &#x201C;Activation&#x201D; state of the triggering condition (e.g., detectable or not), and the &#x201C;Activation&#x201D; state of the signal itself. More information on this can be found in the <a href="#background-and-context">Background and Context</a> section below.</p>
                <p>Some of the resources listed in the <a href="#bnr">Boundaries and Relationships</a> section, below, may be used complementarily. For example, in a home care setting, a patient fall condition detected by a phone app (DeviceAlert) may trigger a remote alert signal in the caregiving family member app (DeviceAlert), while, days later, the treating physician may receive a &#x201C;patient fell 2&#8211;5 times in the last 3 months&#x201D; message on her clinician app (<a href="./communication.html">Communication</a>) or see such message flagged in the EMR (<a href="./flag.html">Flag</a>).
                </p>

                <a name="usage"/>
                <h3>Usage Scenarios</h3>

                <p>The following scenarios provide examples of what this resource is utilized for:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>A vital signs monitor detects a low heart rate condition and signals an alarm that gets communicated to a FHIR-enabled system for information documentation purposes.</li>
                        <li>A patient-worn watch monitoring heart information identifies a hypertensive condition and issues an alarm to notify the user.</li>
                        <li>Alert conditions from devices associated with a patient are consumed by a nursing &#x201C;dashboard&#x201D; application and integrated into a display that synthesizes all the information for review by clinical staff.</li>
                        <li>A smart alerting system consumes medical device alerts and other information from an ensemble of devices around a patient point-of-care, analyzes the information in real-time and signals patient alert conditions that are not recognized by any single device, or filters out lower-priority/duplicative alert conditions detected by individual devices.</li>
                        <li>A medication management workflow application subscribes to all the alert information from infusion pumps for a specific patient, to determine pump operational changes that may impact clinical workflow.</li>
                        <li>A quality analytics application periodically reviews device alert information and identifies opportunities for process improvement.</li>
                </ul>

                <a name="bnr"/>
                <h3>Boundaries and Relationships</h3>

                <h4>Resource Relationships</h4>

                <p>This resource directly references:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                                <a href="device.html">Device</a> or <a href="devicemetric.html">DeviceMetric</a> to identify the device or part thereof that originated the detection of the alert condition (e.g., the heart rate device metric that detected a tachycardia alert). These resources may contain additional data elements to describe the alert activation states (e.g., if detection of all or a subset of alerts is on, paused or off).</li>
                        <li>
                                <a href="patient.html">Patient</a> to identify the patient the physiological alert is about, or <a href="device.html">Device</a> to identify the device the technical alert is about. Additional potential subjects of an alert could be <a href="location.html">Location</a>,                                <a href="medication.html">Medication</a>,                                <a href="biologicallyderivedproduct.html">BiologicallyDerivedProduct</a>,                                <a href="specimen.html">Specimen</a>, or <a href="nutritionproduct.html">NutritionProduct</a>.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                                <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> to identify any evidentiary data needed to interpret the alert condition or that is the reason why the alert condition is present.</li>
                        <li>
                                <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> and <a href="encounter.html">Encounter</a> to identify relevant context of the alert condition.</li>
                </ul>

                <h4>Resource Boundaries</h4>

                <h5>Flag</h5>
                <p>The primary distinction between <a href="flag.html">Flag</a> and DeviceAlert lies in their origin and intent: Flag highlights selected information from the patient record for general awareness, while DeviceAlert originates from a device, based on device-generated data (often outside the patient record), and is designed for regulated, automated alerting that may trigger immediate clinical response through visual, audible or haptic signals. DeviceAlert also tracks alert condition and signal states, though for low-priority alerts, a Flag may be a suitable supplementary means of annunciating through the patient record.</p>

                <h5>DetectedIssue</h5>
                <p>
                        <a href="detectedissue.html">DetectedIssue</a> identifies clinical concerns linked to proposed or ongoing actions, while DeviceAlert is typically triggered by physiological or physical events, not clinical decisions. These resources differ not only in origin, but also in how they are processed and directed: Detected issue is part of clinical reasoning workflows, while DeviceAlert is often part of automated device monitoring systems.</p>

                <h5>Communication</h5>
                <p>In <a href="communication.html">Communication</a>, there is a specific intended sender and receiver, and the information is delivered only once. Device-generated alerts are not necessarily (or even usually) targeted at a specific intended receiver, and they are often continuous and ongoing.</p>

                <h5>Observation</h5>
                <p>
                        <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> is intended for capturing measurements and subjective point-in-time assessments, and may be used to complement DeviceAlert, identifying any evidentiary data needed to interpret the alert condition (that is, the reason why the alert condition is present).</p>

                <h5>Subscription</h5>
                <p>
                        <a href="subscription.html">Subscription</a> differs from from DeviceAlert in origin and behavior: Subscription reflects a client&apos;s request for filtered notifications from a FHIR server, while DeviceAlert represents unsolicited events triggered by devices based on physiological or physical conditions. Due to the vast number and variability of device alerts, consumer-controlled filtering (subscription) is typically impractical. Moreover, DeviceAlert supports documentation and logging use cases, while subscriptions have a run-time nature.</p>

                <h5>AuditEvent</h5>
                <p>
                        <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> is primarily for administrative and operational tracking, while DeviceAlert serves clinical purposes, often prompting action. DeviceAlert captures multiple dynamic states across an alert&apos;s lifecycle, which would be inefficient and duplicative to model using separate AuditEvents, especially since AuditEvents are usually immutable and DeviceAlert often requires updates.</p>

                <a name = "background-and-context"></a>
                <h3>Background and Context</h3>
                <p>DeviceAlert models two alert aspects: the condition detected by a device, and the signal, representing how the alert is announced (and by which attention is drawn to the existence of the alert condition). Signal behavior is determined by device design and configuration and may persist beyond the condition itself due to features like latching (extending brief alerts for visibility).</p>
                <img src="devicealert-state-machine.svg" alt="The DeviceAlert state machine showing transitions between idle, inactivated, latched, alarming, acknowledge, and signal-inactivated states; and the interplay between alert conditions and signals." style="max-width: 100%; height: auto;"/>
                <p>The center row of the diagram shows the flow between the states of an alert record, considering both the alert condition detected by the device (upper row) and the signals emitted by the device (lower row). The upper and lower rows show the values of key elements of DeviceAlert and the associated <a href="devicemetric.html">DeviceMetric</a> in correspondence to the alert record states.</p>
        </div>
</div>
