<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
    <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" />
    <title>Untitled Document</title>
</head>
<body>
    <div>
        <a name="scope" id="scope"></a>
        <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
        <p>A DeviceAlert represents an exceptional condition or occurrence determined to 
        exist by a device.</p>
        <p>The term "alert" covers both alarms and non-alarm informational data.</p>
        <p>Alerts may be physiological (about the state of a patient) or technical 
        (about the state of the device, for example indicating that a particular 
        observation cannot be made due to a malfunction)</p>
        <p>An alert often requires notification and possibly urgent or timely action by a 
        clinician or biomedical technician</p>
        <p>It has a severity attribute which may be notification-only, a concerning 
        medium-priority condition requiring awareness, or a possibly life-threatening 
        requiring immediate action</p>
        <p>The state described in a DeviceAlert instance requires electronic handling 
        different from the usual periodic (repetitive, scheduled) observations that may 
        be sent by a device to an electronic medical record system for charting. Since 
        these are scheduled according to charting preferences, 
        there is a need for a different message type that is sent as fast as technically 
        feasible, by a specialized, low-latency subsystem of the device.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the DeviceAlert resource is:</p>
        
        <ul>
            <li>to bring the occurrence and lifecycle of an alert condition and associated 
            signals into the FHIR ecosystem, available to other systems and functions.</li>
            <li>The track the existence of one or more kinds of signals emitted by a 
            device as a result of the condition, such as audible, visual, or haptic</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This requires tracking of the condition's state, time of its persistence if it 
           is no longer active, state of local and remote signals relating to the condition 
           and whether they have been responded to.</p>
        <p>It should be noted that the handling and use of such information is subject to 
        safety, regulatory, manufacturing, testing and technical standards. Any integrators 
        of a system making use of device alerts and signals is responsible for rigorous 
        risk analysis and testing to assure safety, efficacy, and security of the intended 
        use of the system in its system environment.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>Kinds</h3>
        <p>Examples of alert conditions represented by a DeviceAlert:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>abnormal heart rhythm</li>
            <li>physiological measurement that is high or low relative to a threshold 
            preselected as significant for the patient</li>
            <li>malfunction of life-supporting or therapy-supporting equipment, such as 
            occluded infusion line</li>
            <li>technical condition interfering with monitoring function such as 
            a detached or loose ECG leads</li>
        </ul>
    </div>
    <div>
        <a name="bnr" id="bnr"></a>
        <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
        <p>These are the DeviceAlert related resources:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="device.html">Device:</a> The physical, virtual, or software device 
            that this DeviceAlert is for. Note that the Device.property element is used to 
            record static characteristics or properties of the Device. 
            A DeviceAlert is originated by a device represented by a Device resource, which 
            may be a component of another Device: 
            a specific subsystem, channel, or metric. An additional alert signal may be 
            emitted by a device, system, or equipment (such as an annunciator) other than 
            the device that determined the signal.</li>
        </ul>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="devicedefinition.html">DeviceDefinition:</a> Describes a "kind" 
            of device - not a specific instance of the device. Note alternatively to Device 
            the DeviceDefinition.property element may be used to record static characteristics 
            or properties of the DeviceDefinition.</li>
        </ul>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="observation.html">Observation:</a> Used to record the particular 
            value underlying or supporting the DeviceAlert at a point in time.</li>
        </ul>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="devicemetric.html">DeviceMetric:</a> In some cases, a DeviceAlert 
            is supported by information about a particular metric subsystem in a DeviceMetric 
            resource, such as the configured alarm limits set for a measurement.</li>
        </ul>
    </div>
</body>
</html>
