<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource is used to pass information into and back from an <a href="operations.html">operation</a>
(whether invoked directly from REST or within a messaging environment).  It is not persisted or allowed
to be referenced by other resources except as described below.
</p>
<p>
Because Parameters does not reflect a persistent healthcare-related entity but rather just a collection
of data passed into or out of an operation, there is generally no need to have a RESTful endpoint at
which such instances can be created, updated, queried, etc.  However, there are a few limited cases
where this can make sense:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Parameters instances can be stored to record inbound and/or outbound information in support of
    an <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> instance
  </li>
  <li>
    Parameters instances might be persisted either on their own or as part of a Bundle to support
    documentation of examples for an <a href="implementationguide.html">ImplementationGuide</a>
    and/or test data for a TestScript
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
Technically, Parameters is a specialization of Resource and as such could potentially appear anywhere
that 'Resource' is permitted and could be referenced anywhere an element has an unconstrained type of
Reference.  For example, it could appear in FHIR documents, as contained resources, referenced by
extensions, in elements like Observation.focus, etc.  However, <b>such use is prohibited</b> unless the
element containing the Resource or Reference type explicitly indicates that Parameters is permitted.
If there is a requirement to exchange arbitrary collections of data elements, this need should typically
be met using <a href="basic.html">Basic</a>.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This special resource has no other use than for operation parameters, and there is no RESTful end-point associated with it.
For further information, see the <a href="operations.html">operations</a> page.
</p>
<p>
<a href="operationdefinition.html">OperationDefinition</a> defines constraints on the Parameters resource instances that are used to convey the inputs and outputs of the operation.
</p>
</div>

</div>
