<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<p>
Note: for technical compatibility reasons, the <i>Parameters</i> resource inherits from 
<a href="resource.html">Resource</a>, but since the parameter exchange format has no
end-point and/or persistence, it never has an id, a versionId, or a lastUpdated. 
The other features of Resource (tags, profiles, security labels, language etc.) may
have use when operations are executed.
</p>

<a name="ids"> </a>
<h3>Names and Identifiers</h3>
<p>
The following rules apply to name and identifier uniqueness within a Parameters resource:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr>
  <td>Parameter Names</td>
  <td>Parameter names can be repeated at any level. The meaning of duplicate parameter names - and whether it is valid to 
    repeat any given parameter name - depends on the context. Typically, <a href="operationdefinition.html">operation definitions</a>
	define what parameters can be used, and whether they can repeat. The order of parameters with different names is not considered significant</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>Resources</td>
  <td>Resources in <code>parameter.resource</code> do not need to be unique, though the interpretation of 
    non-unique resources, or different versions of the same resource, may be ambiguous in cases where
	the parameter names do not clearly differentiate the purpose of the parameter. For 
	additional commentary, see the notes about <a href="bundle.html#bundle-unique">about resource uniqueness in Bundles</a>,
	though be aware that those rules do not apply to the <code>Parameters</code> resource unless the <a href="[%extensions-location%]StructureDefinition-parameters-fullUrl.html">fullUrl extension</a> is present on parameters with resources.</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>Internal References</td>
  <td>When internal references are resolved in a resource in a <code>parameter.resource</code>, the 
    resolution stops at <code>parameter.resource</code>. This allows resources to appear more than
	once in a Parameters resource, and also means that resources cannot reference content in another 
	resource using an internal reference (except for <a href="references.html#contained">references inside contained resources</a>)</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>References</td>
  <td>When resolving references in resources, the applicable <a href="operationdefinition.html">Operation Definition</a> may 
	  specify how references may be resolved between parameters. If a reference cannot be resolved between the parameters, the application should fall back to its 
		<a href="references.html">general resource resolution methods</a></td>
 </tr>
 
 
 

</table>

</div>
