<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="overrides"> </a>
<h3>Overriding Versions</h3>
<p>
The ExpansionProfile resources allows a client to specify a particular version to use for a given code system,
and that this version is used <b>irrespective</b> of any version stated in any value set. This has obvious 
safety issues, in that it may result in a value set expansion giving a different list of codes that is both 
wrong and unsafe, and implementers should only use this capability reluctantly. This feature is primarily defined
to allow implementers to deal with situations where specifications have fallen into decay as time passes, and 
the specified versions of code systems can no longer be used at all.
</p>
<p>
In principle, well designed specifications should not be authored in a fashion that allows them
to decay in this fashion, but the technical infrastructure, eco-system, and community are not yet
in a position to make this a reality. For this reason, clients are allowed to override versions. 
Clients setting the <code>ExpansionProfile.fixedVersion.mode</code> to override need to ensure that this 
action is not unsafe in their context.
</p>

<a name="overrides"> </a>
<h3>Excluding Codes</h3>
<p>
Some fields in the ExpansionProfile can result in the return of an expansion that contains 
a reduced set of information in the expansion. if any of these fields may alter the expansion,
terminology servers SHALL mark their use in the <code>ValueSet.expansion.parameters</code>
with the matching parameter name:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr><td><code>ExpansionProfile.fixedVersion</code></td><td>fixedVersion (in addition to the normal 'version' parameter)</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>ExpansionProfile.activeOnly</code></td><td>activeOnly</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>ExpansionProfile.excludeNotForUI</code></td><td>excludeNotForUI</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>ExpansionProfile.excludePostCoordinated</code></td><td>excludePostCoordinated</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>ExpansionProfile.limitedExpansion</code></td><td>limitedExpansion (in addition to the the extension <a href="extension-valueset-toocostly.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/valueset-toocostly</a>)</td></tr>
</table>

</div>
