<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<h3>Overview</h3>
<p>
The sequence-genetics-variant profile (i.e. Profile for variant) extends the <a href="Sequence.html">Sequence</a> resource to enable reporting one result of structured genetic test. In addition, the variant profile contextualizes well established standards from the field of clinical genetics into the standards of healthcare (e.g. HGNC - HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee's international standard for gene names, symbols, and identifiers).
</p>
<p>
<h4>Genetic Standards and Resources include:</h4>
			<ul> 
				<li>Variant Databases: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/snp_ref.cgi">dbSNP</a> , <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/">ClinVar</a>, and <a href="http://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/cosmic/">COSMIC</a> </li>
				<li>Reference Sequences: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/refseq/">RefSeq</a> and <a href="http://www.ensembl.org/index.html">ENSEMBL</a> </li>
				<li> Gene Symbols and Identifiers: <a href="http://www.genenames.org">HGNC</a> - Human Genee Nomenclature Committee</li>
				<li>Variant Nomenclature: <a href="http://www.hgvs.org">HGVS</a> nomenclature from the Human Genome Variantion Society</li>
				<li>Variant Feature Annotation: <a href="http://www.sequenceontology.org">Sequence Ontology (SO)</a> and <a href="https://loinc.org">LOINC</a> </li>
                <li>Locus: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene">Gene</a></li>
			</ul>
</p>
<h3>Scope and Usage</h3>
<p>
The sequence-genetics-variant profile supports reporting of a DNA variant at the genomic, cDNA, and protein change level. It is strongly encouraged to provide all available information in this profile for any reported variants, because receiving systems (e.g. discovery research, outcomes analysis, and public health reporting) may use this information to normalize variants over time or across sources.  However, these data should not be used to dynamically correct/change variant representations for clinical use outside of the laboratory, due to insufficient information.

</p>
<p>
Implementers should be aware that semantic equivalency of results of genetic variants cannot be guaranteed unless there is an agreed upon standard between sending and receiving systems.
</p>
<p>
These challenges raised above are discussed in the HL7 Clinical Sequencing Domain Analysis Model (passed January 2015 ballot and in process of being published).
</p>
<p>
Hl7 Clinical Genomics Work Group emphasizes the importance of transmitting structured genetic findings within the clinical, translational, and research environments fully integrated with other clinical data, in order to drive outcomes analysis, operational decision making, discovery research, and public health reporting. the standard doesn't currently cover the reporting of clinically relevant negative or wildtype results within genetic data portion of the message.
</p>
<p>
    <a href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public_temp_65DE7F6D-1C23-BA17-0CB30D7343EDE16D/wg/clingenomics/docs/V3DAM_CG_CLINSEQ_R1_O1_2013JAN.pdf">Here</a> is the document of HL7 Version 3 Domain Analysis Model where the examples used in genetics profile are from (Page 5).
</p>

<h3>Relationships</h3>
<p>
    The sequence-genetics-variant profile is designed to be referenced by the <a href="observation-genetics-cg-prf.html">Standard genetics profile</a>. The sequence-genetics-variant profile describes one genetic variant - the DNA variant, DNA variant type, gene and gene region that are inherited from the <a href="sequence.html">Sequence</a> resource and added constrains to code systems. Other attributes such as observed/reference allele are added as extensions. The element type in the <a href="sequence.html">Sequence</a> resource is tied to value - "DNA" and variant information about amino acids is stored in extensions - variantAminoAcidChange and variantAminoAcidChangeType considering the format of genetic test reports.
</p>
<p>
    The Card. of the extension - variant (reference to sequence-genetics variant) in the <a href="observation-genetics-cg-prf.html">Standard genetics profile</a> is 0...* which makes it convenient and flexible to support genetic test results containing a list of gene mutations or variants.
</p>
    
</div>
