<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->

<h2>Notes:</h2>

<h3>Sequence Coordinate System</h3>
<p>
	When saving the variant information, the nucleic acid will be numbered with order. Some files are using 0-based coordiantes (e.g. BCD file format) while some files are using 1-based coordinates (e.g. VCF file format) . The element coordinateSystem in Sequence Resource contains this information.
</p>
<p>
	Sequence.coordinateSystem constraints within two possible values: 0 for 0-based system, which will mark the sequence from number 0, while 1 for 1-based system, which will begin marking the first position with number 1. The significant difference between two system is the end position. In 0-based system, the end position is <b>exclusive</b> , which means the last position will not be contained in the sequence window while in 1-based system, the end position is <b>inclusive</b> , which means the last position is included in the sequence window. Note both systems has an inclusive start position.

</p>
<p>
	For example, ACGTGCAT will be numbered from 1 to 8 in 1-based system and will be numbered from 0 to 8 in 0-based system to mark flanks (i.e. place between two Nucleotide). So the interval [3,5] in 1-based system is GTG while interval [2,5) in 0-based system is same segment GTG.
</p>

<h3>Choice of Strand </h3>

<p>
There are lots of definition concerning with the Directionality of DNA or RNA. Here strand element in Sequence resource is defined to have constraints with value +1 and -1 , to indicate what is the direction for nucleotide series. In order to avoid confusion, we use +1 to express the "plus" strand (5' to 3') and -1 to express the "minus" strand (3' to 5'). Here is a very simple mapping that indicates which number the expression will be represented.
  <table border="1">
    <tr>
      <td><b>+1</b></td>
      <td><b>-1</b></td> 
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Watson</td>
      <td>Crick</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sense</td>
      <td>Antisense</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>positive</td>
      <td>negative</td>
    </tr>
  </table>

</p>

<p>
Here is a small-scale example: if 5' GCGATATCGCAAA 3' is the data, then GC..AAA is plus strand while AAA..CG is the minus strand. 

</p>

<h3> String usage for Reference Sequence and Observed Sequence </h3>
<p>
We hope that string of <b>observedSeq</b> can be constrained more than just any normal string but with notation tables. Here we present what the nucleotide acid stirng should be constrianed within the range:

  <table>
    <tr>
      <td>A --> adenosine </td>
      <td>M --> A C (amino)</td>
      <td>U --> uridine </td>
      <td>H --> A C T</td>
      <td>V --> G C A</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>C --> cytidine</td> 
      <td>S --> G C (strong)</td>
      <td>D --> G A T</td>
    <td>K --> G T (keto)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>G --> guanine </td>
      <td>W --> A T (weak)</td>
      <td>R --> G A (purine)</td> 
      <td>N --> A G C T (any)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>T --> thymidine</td>
      <td>B --> G T C</td>
      <td>Y --> T C (pyrimidine)</td> 
      <td>- --> gap of indeterminate length  </td>
    </tr>
  </table>

while the amino acid string should be constrained within the range:

  <table>
    <tr>
      <td>A alanine </td>
      <td>P proline</td>
      <td>B aspartate or asparagine</td>
      <td>Q glutamine</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>C cystine </td>
      <td>R arginine</td>
      <td>D aspartate</td>
      <td>S serine</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>E glutamate </td>
      <td>T threonine</td>
      <td>F phenylalanine </td>
      <td>U selenocysteine</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>G glycine </td>
      <td>V valine</td>
      <td>H histidine </td>
      <td>W tryptophan </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>I isoleucine </td>
      <td>Y tyrosine </td>
      <td>K lysine </td>
      <td>Z glutamate or glutamine</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>L leucine</td>
      <td> X any </td>
      <td>M methionine </td>
      <td>* translation stop </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>N asparagine </td>
      <td>- gap of indeterminate length </td>
    </tr>
  </table>

</p>


</div>

