<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="notes"></a>

<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<h3>Identifiers</h3>
The <a href="datatypes.html#Identifier">identifier</a> datatype has a <code>type</code> element that may be used to distinguish the identifiers assigned by the requester and the performer of the request (known as the 'Placer' and 'Filler' in the HL7 Version 2 Messaging Standard).  Use the identifier type code "PLAC" for the Placer Identifier and  "FILL" for the Filler identifier as is shown in the example below:
<pre class="xml">

&lt;!-- Placer identifier--&gt;
&lt;identifier&gt;
&lt;type&gt;
&lt;coding&gt;
  &lt;system value="http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/v2-0203"/&gt;
  &lt;code value="PLAC"/&gt;
&lt;/coding&gt;
&lt;text value="Placer"/&gt;
&lt;/type&gt;
&lt;system value="urn:oid:1.3.4.5.6.7"/&gt;
&lt;value value="2345234234234"/&gt;
&lt;/identifier&gt;
&lt;!-- Filler identifier--&gt;
&lt;identifier&gt;
&lt;type&gt;
&lt;coding&gt;
  &lt;system value="http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/v2-0203"/&gt;
  &lt;code value="PLAC"/&gt;
&lt;/coding&gt;
&lt;text value="Placer"/&gt;
&lt;/type&gt;
&lt;system value=" http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/v2-0203"/&gt;
&lt;value value="567890"/&gt;
&lt;/identifier&gt;
</pre>

<h3>Clinically Relevant Time</h3>
	<p>
If the diagnostic procedure was performed on the patient directly, the <a href="diagnosticreport-definitions.html#DiagnosticReport.effective_x_">effective[x]</a> element is a dateTime, the time it was performed.
If specimens were taken, the clinically relevant time of the report can be derived from the specimen collection times, but
since detailed specimen information is not always available, and nor is the clinically relevant time always exactly the specimen collection time (e.g. complex timed tests), the
reports SHALL always include an effective[x] element. Note that <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=185">HL7 v2</a> messages often carry a diagnostically relevant time without carrying any specimen information.
</p>
<h3>Associated Observations</h3>
<ul>
<li>
The DiagnosticReport.code always contains the name of the report itself. The report can also contain a set of Observations in the DiagnosticReport.result element. These Observations can be simple observations (e.g. atomic results) or groups/panels of other observations. The Observation.code indicates the nature of the observation or panel (e.g. individual measure, organism isolate/sensitivity or antibody functional testing).   When relevant, the observation can specify a particular specimen from which the result comes.
<ul>
<li>
 Examples of nesting groups/panels within an observation include reporting a "profile" consisting of several  panels as is shown in <a href="diagnosticreport-example-ghp.html">this example</a>, a group of antibiotic isolate/sensitivities for a bacterial culture, or a set of perinatal measurements on a single fetus.
 </li>
 <li>There is rarely a need for more than two levels of nesting in the Observation tree. One known use is for organism sensitivities - an example of a <a href="diagnosticreport-micro1.html">complex Micro Isolate and Sensitivities</a> is provided.
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Associated Images</h3>
<p>
ImagingStudy and the <code>media</code> element are somewhat overlapping - typically, the list of image references in the image element will also be found in one of the imaging study resources. However, each caters to different types of displays for different types of purposes. Neither, either, or both may be provided.
</p>
<h3>Diagnostic Report Status</h3>
<ul>
<li>
Applications consuming diagnostic reports must take careful note of updated (revised) reports and ensure that retracted reports are appropriately handled.
</li>
<li>
For applications providing diagnostic reports, a report should not be final until all the individual data items
reported with it are final or appended.
</li>
<li>
If the report has been withdrawn following a previous final release, the DiagnosticReport and associated Observations should be retracted by replacing the status codes with the concept "entered-in-error" and setting the conclusion/comment (if provided) and the text narrative to some text like "This report has been withdrawn" in the appropriate language. A reason for retraction may be provided in the narrative.
</li>
</ul>

	<h3>Report Content</h3>
	<p>
Typically, a report is either: all data, no narrative (e.g. Core lab) or a mix of data with some concluding narrative (e.g. Structured Pathology Report, Bone Density), or all narrative (for example a typical imaging report, histopathology).  This resource provides for these 3 different presentations:
</p>
	<ul>
		<li>As atomic data items: a hierarchical set of nested references to Observation resources often including pathologist/radiologist interpretation(s),  one or more images, and possibly with a conclusion and/or one or more coded diagnoses</li>
		<li>As narrative: an XHTML presentation in the standard resource narrative</li>
		<li>As a "presented form": A rich text representation of the report - typically a PDF</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
Note that the conclusion and the coded diagnoses are part of the atomic data and SHOULD be duplicated in the narrative and in the presented form if the latter is present.
The narrative and the presented form serve the same function: a representation of the report for a human. The presented form is included since diagnostic service reports
often contain presentation features that are not easy to reproduce in the HTML narrative. Whether or not the presented form is included, the narrative must be a
clinically safe view of the diagnostic report; at a minimum, this could be fulfilled by a note indicating that the narrative is not proper representation of
the report, and that the presented form must be used, or a generated view from the atomic data. However, consumers of the report will best be served if the
narrative contains clinically relevant data from the form. Commonly, the following patterns are used:
</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Simple Laboratory Reports: A single set of atomic observations, and a tabular presentation in narrative. This is typically encountered in high volume areas such as Biochemistry and Hematology</li>
		<li>Histopathology Report: A document report in a presented form and the narrative. Possibly a few key images, and some coded diagnoses for registries. If the service is creating a structured report, some atomic data may be included</li>
		<li>imaging Report: A document report in a presented form and the narrative, with an imaging study reference and possibly some key images. Some imaging reports such as a Bone Density Scan may include some atomic data</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
Note that the nature of reports from the various disciplines that provide diagnostic reports are changing quickly,
as expert systems provide improved narrative reporting in high volume reports, structured reporting brings additional
data to areas that have classically been narrative based, and the nature of the imaging and laboratory procedures are
merging. Therefore, these patterns described above are only examples of how a diagnostic report can be used.
</p>
	<a name="genetics"></a>
	<h3>Genomic Reports</h3>
	<p>
	Genomic reporting makes heavy use of the DiagnosticReport and Observation resources to capture the genomic data in a highly structured and computable way.  An implementation guide describing how to represent genetic results can be found <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/genomics-reporting/index.html">here</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
	Beyond the structured, computable data available in DiagnosticReport and Observation, metadata about the analysis performed is captured in the <a href="genomicstudy.html">GenomicStudy</a> resource. GenomicStudy aims at delineating relevant information of a genomic study. A genomic study might comprise one or more analyses, each serving a specific purpose. These analyses may vary in method (e.g., karyotyping, CNV, or SNV detection), performer, software, devices used, or regions targeted.
	</p>
</div>
