<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is an <em>event</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.   It is the intent of the Orders and Observation Workgroup to align this resource with  the workflow pattern for <a href="workflow.html#event"><em>event</em> resources</a>.</strong></p>
<p>
A diagnostic report is the set of information that is typically provided by a diagnostic service
when investigations are complete. The information includes a mix of atomic results, text reports, images,
and codes. The mix varies depending on the nature of the diagnostic procedure, and sometimes on the nature
of the outcomes for a particular investigation.  In FHIR, the report can be conveyed in a variety of ways including a <a href="documents.html">Document</a>, <a href="http.html">RESTful API</a>, or <a href="messaging.html">Messaging </a> framework.  Included within each of these, would be the DiagnosticReport resource itself.
</p>
<p>
The DiagnosticReport resource has information about the diagnostic report itself, and about the subject and, in the case of laboratory tests, the specimen of the report.  It can also refer to the request details and atomic observations details or image instances.  Report conclusions can be expressed as a simple text blob, structured coded data or as an attached fully formatted report such as a PDF.</p>
<p>
The DiagnosticReport resource is suitable for the following kinds of diagnostic reports:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Laboratory (Clinical Chemistry, Hematology, Microbiology, etc.)</li>
 <li>Pathology / Histopathology / related disciplines</li>
 <li>Imaging Investigations (x-ray, CT, MRI, etc.)</li>
 <li>Other diagnostics such as Cardiology, Gastroenterology, etc.</li>
 <li>Product quality tests such as pH, Assay, Microbial limits, etc. on product and substance</li>
</ul>
<p>
The DiagnosticReport resource is not intended to support cumulative result presentation (tabular presentation of past and present results in the resource).
The DiagnosticReport resource does not yet provide full support for detailed structured reports of sequencing; this is planned for a future release.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<!--p>
The DiagnosticReport resource has the following aspects:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>status, issued, identifier, performer, category: information about the diagnostic report itself</li>
 <li>subject, diagnostic[x]: information about the subject of the report</li>
 <li>request details: a reference to 0 or more <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest resources</a> to allow the report to connect to clinical work flows</li>
 <li>results: a reference to 0 or more <a href="observation.html">Observation resources</a> which provide
    a hierarchical tree of groups of results</li>
 <li>specimen details: a reference to 0 or more <a href="specimen.html">Specimen resources</a> on which the report is based</li>
 <li>conclusion, conclusionCode: support for structured reporting</li>
 <li>images, representation: image and media representations of the report and supporting images</li>
</ul-->

<b>Diagnostic Report Names</b>

<p>
The words "tests", "results", "observations", "panels" and "batteries" are often used interchangeably when describing
the various parts of a diagnostic report. This leads to much confusion. The naming confusion is
worsened because of the wide variety of forms that the result of a diagnostic investigation can take,
as described above. Languages other than English have their own variations on this theme.
</p>
<p>
This resource uses one particular set of terms. A practitioner "requests" a set of "tests". The
diagnostic service returns a "report" which may contain a "narrative" - a written summary of the
outcomes, and/or "results" - the individual pieces of atomic data which each are "observations".
The results are assembled in "groups" which are nested structures of Observations (traditionally referred to as "panels" or " batteries" by laboratories) that can be used to represent relationships between the individual data items.
</p>


</div>
<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Note that many diagnostic processes are procedures that generate observations and diagnostic reports. In many cases, such an observation does not require an explicit representation of the procedure used to create the observation, but where there are details of interest about how the diagnostic procedure was performed, the <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> resource is used to describe the activity.
</p>

<p>
In contrast to the <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resource, the DiagnosticReport resource typically includes additional clinical context and some mix of atomic results, images, imaging reports, textual and coded interpretation, and formatted representations. Laboratory reports, pathology reports, and imaging reports should be represented using the DiagnosticReport resource. The Observation resource is referenced by the DiagnosticReport to provide the atomic results for a particular investigation.
</p>

<p>
If you have a highly structured report, then use DiagnosticReport - it has data and workflow support.  Details about the request for a diagnostic investigation are captured in the various "request" resources (e.g., the <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a>) and allow the report to connect to clinical workflows. For more narrative driven reports with less work flow (histology/mortuary, etc.), the <a href="composition.html">Composition</a> resource would be more appropriate.
</p>

<p>
Diagnostic studies, such as those involving radiologic images or genomic data, are referenced via the "study" element. 
</p>

<p>
For image studies, the details and actual image instances can be referenced in the DiagnosticReport using the "media" element or through the "study" element to reference <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resources which represent the content produced in a DICOM imaging study or set of DICOM Instances for a patient.
</p>

<p>
When a report includes genomic testing, the complex metadata about the analysis performed can be captured referenced through the "study" element to reference  <a href="genomicstudy.html">GenomcStudy</a> resources. 
</p>

<p>
As other complex laboratory areas develop resources to capture metadata about different types of studies, this attribute will be extended to reference those.
</p>

<p>
Image and media representations of the report and supporting images and data are referenced in the "media" element.
</p>

</div>

</div>
