<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
A diagnostic report is used for the set of information that is typically provided by a diagnostic service 
when investigations are complete. The information includes a mix of atomic results, text reports, images,
and codes. The mix varies depending on the nature of the diagnostic procedure, and sometimes on the nature
of the outcomes for a particular investigation. 
</p>
<p>
The Diagnostic Report Resource is suitable for the following kinds of Diagnostic Reports:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Laboratory (Clinical Chemistry, Hematology, Microbiology, etc.)</li>
 <li>Pathology / Histopathology / related disciplines</li>
 <li>Imaging Investigations (x-ray, CT, MRI etc.)</li>
 <li>Other diagnostics - Cardiology, Gastroenterology etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The Diagnostic Report resource is not intended to support cumulative result presentation (tabular presentation of past and present results in the resource). 
The Diagnostic Report resource does not yet provide full support for detailed structured reports of sequencing; this is planned for a future release.
</p>
<p>
The Diagnostic Report resources has the following aspects:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>status, issued, reportId, performer, serviceCategory: information about the diagnostic report itself</li>
 <li>subject, diagnostic[x]: information about the subject of the report</li>
 <li>requestDetails.*: A set of request information to allow the report to connected to clinical work flows</li>
 <li>results.* &amp; specimen details: a heirachical tree of groups of results. The actual atomic result data are delegated to the <a href="observation.html">common Observation
    resource</a> to make it easier to reuse them in a wider context</li>
 <li>conclusion, codedDiagnosic: support for structured reporting</li>
 <li>images, representation: image and media representations of the report and supporting images</li>
</ul>

<h3>Diagnostic Report Names</h3>

<p>
There is a wide variety of names associated with the various parts of a diagnostic report. Doctors 
request for "tests" or "results" to be done. What the diagnostic service returns is variously called
the "tests" or "results" or the "report". The individual data items are called "results" or "tests"
both collectively and individually. Collections of individual data items are sometimes called "batteries"
or "panels", which have various implications in different contexts. The naming confusion is worsened 
because of the wide variety of forms that the result of a diagnostic investigation can take, as 
described above. Languages other than English have their own variations on this theme.
</p>
<p>
This resource uses one particular set of terms. A practitioner "requests" a set of "tests". The
diagnostic service returns a "report" which contains a "narrative" - a written summary of the 
outcomes, and "results" - the individual pieces of atomic data. The results are assembled
in a "group" which is a nested structure that can be used to define relationships between
the individual data items.
</p>
<!-- profiles? -->
</div>
