<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul>
<li>
This resource includes some elements that relate to the ordering cycle (request identifiers); these are only 
included to the degree that it is useful for the final report to refer back to the orders. For explicit support 
of the ordering cycle, see the Order, OrderResponse, and DiagnosticOrder resources.
</li>
<li>
If the diagnostic procedure was performed on the patient directly, <i>diagnosticTime</i> is the time it was peformed. 
If specimens were taken, the diagnostically relevant time can be derived from the specimen collection times, but 
since the specimen information is not always available, and nor is the diagnostically relevant time always exactly the specimen collection time (e.g. complex timed tests), the
reports must always include a <i>diagnosticTime</i> element. Note that v2 messages often carry a diagnostically relevant time without carrying any specimen information.
</li>
<li>
A report always contains a base group for individual results. As a minimum, this contains the name of the report 
itself. The base group can then contain a mix of results and sub-groups. The group has a code that indicates the 
nature of the grouping (e.g. organism isolate/sensitivity or antibody functional testing).  
</li>
<li>
There is rarely a need for more than two levels of groups. Known uses of 3 levels include the antibody code for a 
goup of antibody related test, or the organism code for a group of isolate/sensitivities, or a set of perinatal 
measurements on a single fetus.
</li>
<li>
Applications consuming diagnostic reports must take careful note of updated reports, and ensure that withdrawn reports are appropriately handled. 
</li>
<li>
For applications providing diagnostic reports, a report shouldn't be final until all the individual data items
reported with it are final or amended. If a report is withdrawn, all the results should be withdrawn by replacing 
every result value with the Concept "withdrawn" in the internal terminology <a href="terminologies.htm">"Special values"</a> 
(url = "http://hl7.org/fhir/special-values"), and setting the conclusion (if provided) and the text narrative to some 
text like "This report has been withdrawn" in the appropriate language. A reason for withdrawal may be provided in the 
narrative. </li>
</ul>


</div>
