<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
	<a name="scope"></a>
	<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
	<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
		<p><b>Note to Balloters for Ballot5</b>: Changes update Specimen's focus, collection, processing, container, search-parameter, example, and terminology surfaces for the current ballot window.</p>
		<p>This resource is referenced from the <a href="diagnostics-module.html">Diagnostics Module</a>; reviewers should also consider related module-page ballot content when reviewing this resource.</p>
		<p><b>Non-compatible</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>Specimen role terminology was aligned toward reusable THO candidate value sets, and the FHIR core specimen-role ValueSet/CodeSystem artifacts were removed. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55276">FHIR-55276</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55481">FHIR-55481</a></li>
			<li><code>Specimen.focus</code> was added as a <code>CodeableReference</code> to represent the entity that is the focus of testing. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53384">FHIR-53384</a></li>
			<li>Additional container information was introduced through <code>Specimen.container.device</code>. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53723">FHIR-53723</a></li>
			<li>Collection body-site modeling changed by replacing <code>Specimen.collection.bodySite</code> with <code>Specimen.collection.bodyStructure</code>. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53723">FHIR-53723</a></li>
			<li>The OO batch update that included the SpecimenDefinition subject binding disposition also touched the Specimen structure set; no separate Specimen-only net effect is isolated in the hydrated evidence. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54840">FHIR-54840</a></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Compatible substantive</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>Specimen status handling was updated in the data-resource status cleanup so background workflow status is not used as a resource status value. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54892">FHIR-54892</a></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Non-substantive</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>The Specimen narrative now includes additional clarification about the relationship between SpecimenDefinition and related resources. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54837">FHIR-54837</a></li>
			<li>Narrative text around nested specimen containers was revised, alongside the container-device model updates. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54598">FHIR-54598</a></li>
			<li>The collection device binding mismatch was addressed as <code>Specimen.collection.device[x]</code> was replaced by <code>Specimen.collection.device</code>. <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54488">FHIR-54488</a></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Additional changes</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>Additional changes as described in <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-56301">FHIR-56301</a> and <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54843">FHIR-54843</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</blockquote>

	<p>Any material sample:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>taken from a biological entity, living or dead</li>
		<li>taken from a physical object or the environment</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
	Some specimens are biological and can contain one or more components including but not limited to cellular molecules, cells, tissues, organs, body fluids, embryos, and body excretory products (source: <a href="http://ncit.nci.nih.gov/">NCI Thesaurus</a>, modified).
	</p>
	<p>The specimen resource covers substances used for diagnostic and environmental testing. The focus of the specimen resource
	  is the process for gathering, maintaining and processing the specimen as well as where the specimen originated.
	  This is distinct from the use of Substance which is only used when these other aspects are not relevant.
	</p>
	</div>
	<div>
	<a name="bnc"></a>
	<h2>Background and Context</h2>
	<p>
	The current definition of the specimen resource contains only basic information about specimen containers. The recursive nature of container should be expressed via Specimen.device.parent. The frequency with which these elements are tracked may depend on the context
	of use; general lab, bio-banking, etc. Comments from reviewers on the appropriate scope for this resource, and the need for tracking
	related specimen management attributes, are welcomed.
	</p>
	</div>
</div>
