<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
	<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
		<p><b>Note to Balloters for Ballot5</b>: Changes update Specimen's focus, collection, processing, container, search-parameter, example, and terminology surfaces for the current ballot window.</p>
		<p>This resource is referenced from the <a href="diagnostics-module.html">Diagnostics Module</a>; reviewers should also consider related module-page ballot content when reviewing this resource.</p>
		<p><b>Non-compatible</b></p>
		<ul>
		  <li>Added <code>Specimen.focus</code> (<code>CodeableReference</code>) to identify the entity that is the focus of testing <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53384">FHIR-53384</a></li>
		  <li><code>Specimen.processing.additive</code> promoted from <code>CodeableReference</code> to a <code>BackboneElement</code> with new <code>additive.type</code> and <code>additive.quantity</code>, and <code>container.device</code> added for richer container detail <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53723">FHIR-53723</a></li>
		  <li>Removed the FHIR-defined <code>specimen-role</code> ValueSet and CodeSystem and rebound the element to a THO (terminology.hl7.org) value set; an explanatory note was added to the introduction <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55481">FHIR-55481</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55276">FHIR-55276</a></li>
		  <li>Added a value set binding for <code>SpecimenDefinition.subject[x]</code> (affects the sibling SpecimenDefinition resource) <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54840">FHIR-54840</a></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Compatible substantive</b></p>
		<ul>
		  <li>Refined the <code>Specimen.status</code> value set to avoid conflating background workflow status with the resource's own data status <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54892">FHIR-54892</a></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Non-substantive</b></p>
		<ul>
		  <li>Corrected the binding mismatch on the collection device element; <code>collection.device[x]</code> replaced by <code>collection.device</code> <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54488">FHIR-54488</a></li>
		  <li>Revised the narrative around nesting specimen containers <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54598">FHIR-54598</a></li>
		  <li>Added narrative bullets describing how SpecimenDefinition relates to other resources (affects the sibling SpecimenDefinition resource) <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54837">FHIR-54837</a></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Additional changes</b></p>
		<ul>
		  <li>Additional changes as described in <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-56301">FHIR-56301</a> and <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54843">FHIR-54843</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</blockquote>
	<a name="scope"></a>
	<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

	<p>Any material sample:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>taken from a biological entity, living or dead</li>
		<li>taken from a physical object or the environment</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
	Some specimens are biological and can contain one or more components including but not limited to cellular molecules, cells, tissues, organs, body fluids, embryos, and body excretory products (source: <a href="http://ncit.nci.nih.gov/">NCI Thesaurus</a>, modified).
	</p>
	<p>The specimen resource covers substances used for diagnostic and environmental testing. The focus of the specimen resource
	  is the process for gathering, maintaining and processing the specimen as well as where the specimen originated.
	  This is distinct from the use of Substance which is only used when these other aspects are not relevant.
	</p>
	</div>
	<div>
	<a name="bnc"></a>
	<h2>Background and Context</h2>
	<p>
	The current definition of the specimen resource contains only basic information about specimen containers. The recursive nature of container should be expressed via Specimen.device.parent. The frequency with which these elements are tracked may depend on the context
	of use; general lab, bio-banking, etc. Comments from reviewers on the appropriate scope for this resource, and the need for tracking
	related specimen management attributes, are welcomed.
	</p>
	</div>
</div>
