<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The VerificationResult can be used where content (such as found in a directory) is aggregated between systems,
and the details and results of this <b>verification process</b> needs to be recorded, to determine the likely accuracy/confidence in the content.<br/>
It does not represent the workflows or tasks related, but does cover the result of who did what when, why, and when it needs to be done again.
</p>
<p>
There are often multiple instances of the VerificationResult over time that reference the same resource, even if the resource has not changed,
as the content was verified as still current. Alternately the process may discover that the content was no longer valid 
(i.e. the practitioner was not able to be verified was still working at the location) and therefore the instance could be updated 
to not be active, or even removed from the directory. 
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
<table class="grid">
<tr>
<td>AuditEvent</td>
<td>Details of where/who the resource came from, along with technical data - typically system adminisrtrative data, often not externally accessible.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Provenance</td>
<td>Business level details of where the content came from and what it can be used for.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VerificationResult</td>
<td>Details of checks/workflow results that were performed to verify the accuracy of the referenced resource.
This informs if the data should be trusted, or how current the information is.</td>
</tr>
</table>
</p>
<p>
(A similar concept exists outside of healthcare in Art/Musical Equipment in Appraisals vs Provenance,
 the provenance of the piece covers its chain of ownership, where an appraisal covers how it was check for its authenticity)
</p>
<p>
Although the resource uses a Reference(any), the initial usage is in the directory space against:
<ul>
<li>Organization</li>
<li>OrganizationAffiliation</li>
<li>Location</li>
<li>Practitioner</li>
<li>PractitionerRole</li>
<li>HealthcareService</li>
</ul>
[%stu-note dstu%]
Other resources may use this approach for verifying currency too, and may be updated to be included here in future 
versions of fhir, or in fhir implementation guides. 
[%end-note%]
<br/>
It is not typically expected that other resources would reference VerificationResult
</p>
</div>

</div>
