<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <a name="statemachine"> </a>
  <h2>State Machine</h2>
  <p>
    The following diagram shows the "typical" state machine diagram for resources following the Request
    pattern.  Note that not all resources will support all states, some resources may choose different names
    for certain states and some resources may introduce sub-states to the listed states.  As well, additional
    transitions may be supported, including from terminal nodes (e.g. from "completed" back to "active").
    That said, most resources should align with this state machine fairly well.
  </p>
  <img src="request-state-machine.svg" alt="Typical state machine diagram for resources following 
  the Request pattern"/>
  <p>
    Note that this state machine does not reflect the <i>execution</i> of the request.  That state is managed
    either through the <a href="event.html">Event</a> resources that are based on the request or via the
    <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource.
  </p>

  <a name="fulfillment"> </a>
  <h2>Fulfillment/Execution information</h2>
  <p>
    Request resources describe what activity is desired/authorized.  They don't describe what activity has actually
    occurred against the request.  I.e. The request resource will not indicate actual performer, actual performance
    time, actual action performed, etc.  Information about what action (if any) has occurred against the request is
    tracked using the corresponding <a href="event.html">Event</a> resource(s).  Events that are associated with
    the request should have a <code>basedOn</code> link referencing the request.  In addition, a linkage can be
    established (and information about progress in execution) may be found in <a href="task.html">Task</a> resources
    that have a focus of this request.
  </p>

  <a name="updating"> </a>
  <h2>Updating requests</h2>
  <p>
    FHIR does not impose any business rules on what sorts of changes may be made to a request.  A generic FHIR server
    could support updating a completed request to change the subject, requester, authorized action, quantity, timing
    and any other such information.  However, most business processes will impose significant constraints on what changes,
    if any, are allowed to request resources, particularly after they have transitioned to "active" or "completed".
    Servers are free to enforce whatever rules they deem appropriate - and to provide appropriate 
    <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> responses detailing constraints if those rules are violated.
  </p>
  
  <a name="compound"> </a>
  <h2>Compound Requests</h2>
  <p>
    There are three different ways to define "compound" requests in FHIR:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Shared requisition id</li>
    <li>"Based on" chain</li>
    <li>RequestGroup</li>
  </ul>
  
  <a name="requisitionid"> </a>
  <h3>Shared requisition id</h3>
  <p>
    The <code>Request.requisitionId</code> element allows multiple requests to be linked as having been created as part 
    of the same "event" - generally by the same practitioner at the same time for the same subject.  The 
    "requisitionId" represents the identifier of the prescription, lab requisition or other form that was
    shared by all items.  The common information (<code>patient</code>/<code>practitioner</code>/<code>authoredOn</code>) 
    can be seen by examining
    any of the Request instances that share that <code>requisitionId</code>  If there are common comments or notes that
    span the entire requisition, they should be captured as <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> or 
    <a href="communication.html">Communication</a> instances linked to relevant Request instances using 
    <code>Request.supportingInfo</code>.
  </p>
  <p>
    Each "component" behaves as an independent request and has its own status that changes independently.  In general the
    requisitionId, practitioner, authoredOn and subject for each will be immutable, but there may be situations where
    some workflows allow them to change.  The shared requisitionId allows business processes dependent on 
    "simultaneous/requisition-based ordering" such as payment rules to know that the requests were ordered at the same time.
  </p>

  <a name="basedon"> </a>
  <h3>"Based on" chain</h3>
  <p>
    In this case "components" of a parent request are not treated as components, but rather as separate orders that are
    executed as part of the fulfillment process for the parent order.  For example, a lab order might spawn child orders
    to draw the specimen, treat the specimen, run several tests and to create the report.  Each "child" Request would use 
    <code>Request.basedOn</code> to reference the original Request.  In this case, there's a relationship between the
    statuses of the base Request and the fulfilling Requests, but they transition separately and may not transition in
    the same manner.  For example, if the original lab order were updated to "suspended", the initial blood draw request might
    be complete.  The other requests might change to either "suspended" or even "aborted" and a subsequent update of the
    lab order back to active might require spawning additional fulfilling orders, perhaps to draw a new specimen.
  </p>
  <p>
    <code>basedOn</code> is distinct from the notion of <code>replaces</code>.  In a "based on" relationship both resources are
    "active" and in force and the authority cascades from the initial request to the request that is based on that original request.
     In a "replaces" relationship, the target resource is no longer in force and should have a status of
    "completed" or "cancelled" or some other terminal state.
  </p>

  <a name="requestgroup"> </a>
  <h3>RequestGroup</h3>
  <p>
    This approach makes use of the <a href="requestgroup.html">RequestGroup</a> resource which allows the assertion of complex
    timing and other dependencies between a collection of requests.  These effectively become one overall Request instance with
    a single status.  All resources referenced by the RequestGroup must have an intent of "option", meaning that they cannot
    be interpretted independently - and that changes to them must take into account the impact on referencing resources.
    Typically these will either be contained resources or tightly controlled or immutable instances based on ActivityDefinitions
    that can safely be referenced without concern of them changing independent of referencing Requests.
  </p>
  <p>
    The status of the parent request automatically cascades to the component "options".  If there is a need for divergent
    statuses, these must be handled by creating "child" using the "basedOn" approach above.  They should have a basedOn relationship
    with both the "parent" Request as well as the specific "option" Request they are tied to.
  </p>

</div>
