<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This is <b>NOT</b> a resource.  It is not part of the FHIR schema and cannot appear directly in FHIR instances.  It is a logical model that defines a pattern adhered to by
other resources.  This pattern serves two purposes:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>It offers guidance to work groups designing resources and helps ensure consistency of content created by different work groups</li>
  <li>It provides a standard "view" that might be useful for implementers in processing and manipulating all resources that adhere to the same pattern.  (Tooling that supports
  this may become available in a future release.)</li>
</ul>
<p>
The notion of "request" encompasses all types of orders (original orders, filler representations of orders, reflex orders, etc.) as well as proposals/recommendations for action to occur, 
plans, scheduling, etc.  Any sort of description of an activity that is "desired" where the description is specific as to the subject of the activity and the 
approximate timing of the activity would be considered a "Request".
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This logical model is one of three common <a href="workflow.html#respatterns">workflow patterns</a>.  The other two patterns are <a href="event.html">Event</a> and
<a href="definition.html">Definition</a>.  This pattern is followed by (or is intended to be followed by a number of <a href="workflow.html#list">other FHIR resources</a>/
</p>
<p>
Requests are distinct from <a href="event.html">events</a> in that an event is primarily focused on what has occurred or is occurring while requests deal with what is "desired"
to occur.  While creating a request or definition can be seen as a type of event, the focus of those other resources is not the "creation" but the desire/intention.  Both
requests and <a href="definition.html">definitions</a> deal with activities that "can" occur, but requests represent a specific intention for something to occur and are bound to
a specific context of subject (e.g. patient) and time, while definitions represent mere "possibility" rather than intention and are independent of a specific subject or timeframe.
</p>
<p>
Requests are related to <a href="task.html">Task</a> in that tasks can both request and track the fulfillment of a request.  In some cases, fulfillment may also result in the
creation of sub-tasks.  Requests do not track their own fulfillment - i.e. requested/accepted/in-progress.  This is managed through Task.  The status of a request only reflects
the status of the "authorization/intention", not how the request is being executed or not.  It is possible for multiple tasks to be associated with the fulfillment of a single
Request.
</p>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
This model represents a pattern.  It provides a standard list of data elements with cardinalities, data types, definitions, rationale and usage notes that will ideally be 
adhered to by resources that fall into the "request" workflow category.  However, adherence to this pattern is not mandatory.  Not all healthcare domains are the same.
Concepts that may be generally applicable (and thus are included in this standard pattern) might still not be relevant everywhere or may be sufficiently uncommon that they
are more appropriate to include as extensions than as core properties of the resource.  Work groups are encouraged to adjust descriptions, usage notes and rationale to be
specific to their resource (e.g. use the term "diagnostic test" or "prescription" rather than "request").  As well, design notes in the comments column marked with [square
brackets] identifies areas where domain variation is expected and encouraged.  Other variation, including differences in names, cardinalities, data types and the decision to
omit an element outright are also possible, but should be discussed with the FHIR Infrastructure work group's Workflow project to ensure the rationale for non-alignment is
understood, to confirm that the deviation is necessary and to identify whether any adjustments to the pattern are appropriate.
</p>
<p>
This pattern provides a linkage to the <a href="w5.html">W5</a> list of standard data elements.  Resources that adhere to this pattern should ensure their w5 mappings are
consistent, as is their data element ordering.
</p>
</div>

</div>
