<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <a name="extensions"> </a>
  <h2>Extensions</h2>
  <p>
    Not all resources that follow the 'Request' pattern will necessarily include all of the above elements.  A set of standard extensions have been defined
    for use with resources where an element might be "applicable" but is not commonly supported.  A list of these can be found on the
    <a href="request-extensions.html">Request Extensions</a>(request-specific) and <a href="workflow-extensions.html">Workflow Extensions</a>(shared by events
    and requests).
  </p>

  <a name="statemachine"></a>
  <h2>State Machine</h2>
  <p>
    The following diagram shows the "typical" state machine diagram for resources following the Request
    pattern.  Note that not all resources will support all states, some resources may choose different names
    for certain states and some resources may introduce sub-states to the listed states.  As well, additional
    transitions may be supported, including from terminal nodes (e.g. from "completed" back to "active").
    That said, most resources should align with this state machine fairly well.
  </p>
  <img src="request-state-machine.svg" alt="Typical state machine diagram for resources following
  the Request pattern"/>
  <p>
    Note that this state machine does not reflect the <i>execution</i> of the request.  That state is managed
    either through the <a href="event.html">Event</a> resources that are based on the request or via the
    <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource.
  </p>

  <a name="fulfillment"></a>
  <h2>Fulfillment/Execution information</h2>
  <p>
    Request resources describe what activity is desired/authorized.  Requests do not track the execution/fulfillment
    of the plan, proposal or order.  I.e. the request resource will not indicate actual performer, actual performance
    time, actual action performed, etc.  Information about what action (if any) has occurred against the request is
    tracked using the corresponding <a href="event.html">Event</a> resource(s).  Events that are associated with
    the request should have a <code>basedOn</code> link referencing the request.  In addition, a linkage can be
    established (and information about progress of execution) may be found in <a href="task.html">Task</a> resources
    that have a focus of this request.
  </p>

  <a name="updating"></a>
  <h2>Updating requests</h2>
  <p>
    FHIR does not impose any business rules on what sorts of changes may be made to a request.  A generic FHIR server
    could support updating a completed request to change the subject, requester, authorized action, quantity, timing
    and any other such information.  However, most business processes will impose significant constraints on what changes,
    if any, are allowed to request resources, particularly after they have transitioned to "active" or "completed".
    Servers are free to enforce whatever rules they deem appropriate - and to provide appropriate
    <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> responses detailing constraints if those rules are violated.
  </p>

  <a name="compound"></a>
  <h2>Compound Requests</h2>
  <p>
    There are three different ways to define "compound" requests in FHIR:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Shared requisition id</li>
    <li>"Based on" chain</li>
    <li>RequestOrchestration</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="requisitionid"></a>
  <h3>Shared requisition id</h3>
  <p>
    The <code>Request.groupIdentifier</code> element allows multiple requests to be linked as having been created as part
    of the same "event" - generally by the same practitioner at the same time for the same subject.  The
    "requisitionId" represents the identifier of the prescription, lab requisition or other form that was
    shared by all items.  The common information (<code>patient</code>/<code>practitioner</code>/<code>authoredOn</code>)
    can be seen by examining
    any of the Request instances that share that <code>requisitionId</code>  If there are common comments or notes that
    span the entire requisition, they should be captured as <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> or
    <a href="communication.html">Communication</a> instances linked to relevant Request instances using
    <code>Request.supportingInfo</code>.
  </p>
  <p>
    Each "component" behaves as an independent request and has its own status that changes independently.  Cancelling or suspending
    request with a shared groupIdentifier has no impact on other requests with the same groupIdentifier. The shared
    requisitionId allows business processes dependent on "simultaneous/requisition-based ordering" such as payment rules to
    know that the requests were ordered at the same time.
  </p>
  <p>
    In general, the requisitionId, requester, authoredOn, and subject for each Request will not change over the lifetime of the
    instance, particularly once the status becomes 'active', though there may be situations where some workflows allow these
    elements to change.  Because of this, there could be situations where the subject, requester, authoredOn could differ between
    Requests that share the same requisitionId. Systems can enforce business rules to prevent such inconsistency from happening if
    it would be problematic.
  </p>

  <a name="basedon"></a>
  <h3>"Based on" chain</h3>
  <p>
    In this case "components" of a parent request are not treated as components, but rather as separate orders that are
    executed as part of the fulfillment process for the parent order.  For example, a lab order might spawn child orders
    to draw the specimen, treat the specimen, run several tests and to create the report.  Each "child" Request would use
    <code>Request.basedOn</code> to reference the original Request.  In this case, there's a relationship between the
    statuses of the base Request and the fulfilling Requests, but they transition separately and might not transition in
    the same manner.  For example, if the original lab order were updated to "suspended", the initial blood draw request might
    be complete.  The other requests might change to either "suspended" or even "aborted" and a subsequent update of the
    lab order back to active might require spawning additional fulfilling orders, perhaps to draw a new specimen.
  </p>
  <p>
    <code>basedOn</code> is distinct from the notion of <code>replaces</code>.  In a "based on" relationship both resources are
    "active" and in force and the authority cascades from the initial request to the request that is based on that original request.
    The source and target of a "replaces" relationship should have the same "intent". I.e. An order can replace another order, but
    can't generally replace a proposal - though an order can be "basedOn" a proposal.
  </p>

  <a name="requestorchestration"></a>
  <h3>RequestOrchestration</h3>
  <p>
    This approach makes use of the <a href="requestorchestration.html">RequestOrchestration</a> resource which allows the assertion of complex
    timing and other dependencies between a collection of requests.  These effectively become one overall Request instance with
    a single status.  All resources referenced by the RequestOrchestration must have an intent of "option", meaning that they cannot
    be interpreted independently - and that changes to them must take into account the impact on referencing resources.
    Typically these will either be contained resources or tightly controlled or immutable instances based on ActivityDefinitions
    that can safely be referenced without concern of them changing independent of referencing Requests.
  </p>
  <p>
    The status of the parent request automatically cascades to the component "options".  It is not possible to cancel, suspend or complete one
    part of the RequestOrchestration without making the same status change to <i>all</i> options.  If there is a need for divergent
    statuses, these must be handled by creating "child" requests using the "basedOn" approach above.  They should have a basedOn relationship
    with both the "parent" Request as well as the specific "option" Request they are tied to.
  </p>
  <p>
    A RequestOrchestration might have a .groupIdentifier if it was created as part of a larger collection of independent orders.  The
    different 'option' requests referenced by the RequestOrchestration SHOULD NOT have a .groupIdentifier specified as they are all
    considered part of the RequestOrchestration order.
  </p>

  <a name="notes"> </a>
  <h2>Notes and Related Information</h2>
  <p>
    Both the 'note' and 'supportingInfo' element provide additional supporting or contextual information about the overall Request.
    However, they have slightling different purposes.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>supportingInfo</code> <i>can</i> be a reference to a <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> containing
      ad-hoc clinical notes, however in most cases, <code>supportingInfo</code> will be other types of resources containing discrete
      information.  In the situation where a DocumentReference is used to contain notes, those notes have an independent existence and
      maintenance cycle from the referencing Request resource and might be linked to multiple Request or other resources.  On the other
      hand, <code>notes</code> are associated with exactly one Request instance.</li>
    <li>Notes are typically added to a request after it has been activated, though they can come before.  A key thing is that you want
      to track who made the note and when.</li>
    <li>Notes can be clinical or administrative in nature.  E.g. "Holding off sending the referral until patient is back from vacation",
      "Expect to resume med roughly 2 weeks post-discharge", "Possible compliance issues, follow up next appointment".</li>
    <li><code>supportingInfo</code> is information typically provided at the time the request is activated, though it can be added later.</li>
    <li><code>supportingInfo</code> is information needed by the filler in order to be able to perform the order (e.g. recent lab tests
      supporting a referral, patient height/weight/age supporting a dosage instruction - or allowing calculation of dosage, previous
      procedures done, etc. to support a Claim.</li>
    <li><code>notes</code> should never be used to reflect information conveyed in <code>supportingInfo</code>.</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="history"> </a>
  <h2>Relevant history</h2>
  <p>
    This pattern contains an element called "relevantHistory" that points to <a href="provenance.html">Provenance</a>.  This allows the
    resource to summarize key events that have happened over the lifespan of the resource.  For example, when the request was created,
    when it was suspended, when it was released, etc.  The list of referenced Provenence entries don't necessarily include <i>all</i> events
    that have occurred over the lifespan of the resource.  Instead, they list those the author considers 'significant' and relevant to
    downstream users.  Modifications to drafts or small corrections that do not impact fulfillment might not be needed.  In some cases,
    Provenance for changes to other resources (e.g. fulfilling events) might also be included if the source system tracks those as
    'events' tied to the Request.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>IMPORTANT:</b> the relevantHistory generally excludes the most recent change on 'pure' FHIR repositories.  That is because in
    pure FHIR environments, the Provenance instance must be created after the update has been made - because it needs to point to the new
    'version' of the resource that has been created.  This means that if there is a desire to include the 'current' change in relevant history,
    it is necessary to first make the change, then update the resource to add the event to recentHistory.  More typically, recentHistory
    simply won't include the most recent event.  If the full history is needed, the system will need to retrieve both the history as well as
    the Provenance that points to the current release.
  </p>
  <p>
    For systems that don't store history separately from the base resource, the relevantHistory Provenance instances can be conveyed
    as <a href="references.html#contained">contained resources</a>.  In this circumstance, there might also not be an issue with relevantHistory
    also including the 'most recent' change as the history is updated at the same time the change is applied.
  </p>
  <p>
    The full set of potential Provenance information may be overkill for those systems that are only interested in it from a
    relevantHistory perspective.  The <a href="provenance-relevant-history.html">Provenance Relevant History</a> profile is included to give guidance
    on what data elements are most likely to be relevant for systems looking at Provenance from the perspective of relevantHistory.
  </p>
</div>
