<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is a <em>definition</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective</strong> - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>, specifically <a href="workflow.html#definition">Definition</a>.</p>

<p>The ServiceDefinition defines a module of clinical decision support functionality made available by a decision support service. For example, a service may provide immunization modules, drug-drug interaction checking, or appropriate use assessment.</p>

<p>Each module defines three main features related to its functionality:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Input and output parameters</li>
	<li>Data requirements</li>
	<li>Triggers</li>
</ul>

<p>Input and output parameters are used to specify any named parameters used by the module. These are typically patient-independent configuration parameters such as an A1c threshold for a diabetes control module, but they may also be used to return calculations performed by the module.</p>

<p>Data requirements are used to specify the set of data that must be provided (or available) to the module in order to achieve a successful evaluation. For example, if the module requires A1c lab results within the last 6 months, or information on bilateral or both left and right amputation at or below the knee.</p>

<p>Triggers are used to advertise when the module should be invoked. On encountering a specific trigger, a clinical application can invoke the modules associated with the trigger using the <a href="servicedefinition-operation-evaluate.html">$evaluate</a> operation. Any data required by the module can be sent as part of the request, and any suggested <i>actions</i> and other output data are returned via the <a href="guidanceresponse.html">GuidanceResponse</a> resource.</p>

<p>For a more detailed discussion of the evaluation process, refer to the <a href="clinicalreasoning-cds-on-fhir.html">Clinical Decision Support</a> topic in the Clinical Reasoning module.</p>

<p><i>Note to implementers: The user-facing external clinical decision support use case supported by the ServiceDefinition/$evaluate operation of the Clinical Reasoning module has significant overlap with the functionality provided by the <a href="http://cds-hooks.org">CDS Hooks</a> specification. As part of FHIR Release 4, it is the intention to unify the CDS Hooks specification with the Clinical Reasoning module, ensuring that implementers have a single consistent mechanism to support this use case that meets the requirements of both the Clinical Quality Framework and CDS Hooks communities. Although the functionality in both specifications is conceptually aligned, this unification will likely result in changes to both specifications. The CQF and CDS Hooks project teams are committed to this unification and will work to ensure that the resulting changes have as little impact as possible on current and ongoing implementation efforts, while meeting the needs of both communities. The project team is planning on a workable implementation tested at the connectathon in May of 2017, with a trial ballot following in September 2017, targeting publication as part of the FHIR Release 4 specification.</i></p>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>The ServiceDefinition is similar in structure and purpose to <a href="operationdefinition.html">OperationDefinition</a>. However, ServiceDefinition also represents more information about <i>what</i> service is being described than an operation definition supports. This information is critical to the effective use of the resource as part of a decision support service repository, as it enables searching and selection of functionality based on this additional information.</p>

<p>In addition, the way the $evaluate operation of the ServiceDefinition resource is defined enables all decision support services to share a common set of parameters without having to redeclare them for every module, while still supporting service-specific parameters on each module.</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
