<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is a <em>definition</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective</strong> - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>, specifically <a href="workflow.html#definition">Definition</a>.</p>

<p>An ActivityDefinition is a shareable, consumable description of some activity to be performed. It may be used to specify actions to be taken as part of a workflow, order set, or protocol, or it may be used independently as part of a catalog of activities such as orderables.</p>

<p>For more information on how activity definitions can be used to construct request resources, see the Realizing an ActivityDefinition topic below.</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>In general, an activity definition is simply a conceptual description of some specific action that should be taken. An instance of an ActivityDefinition does not indicate that any action has been performed (as an <a href="workflow.html#event">event</a> resource does), nor does it indicate the actual <i>intent</i> to carry out any particular action (as a <a href="workflow.html#request">request</a> resource does). Instead, an activity definition provides a reusable template that can be used to construct specific <i>request</i> resources such as <a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a> and <a href="medicationrequest.html">MedicationRequest</a>. </p>

<p>Note that this is conceptually similar to the <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource as well, with the distinction being that ActivityDefinition represents the description of a task in the abstract, while the Task resource is used to track a specific instance of a task as it moves through the steps of a workflow.</p>

</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
