<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
A TestPlan defines how an systems, ecosystems or specifications (which can be represented by FHIR artifacts or by narrative) are to be tested.
It contains the business- and planning-language aspects of test planning, along with a set of the detailed test cases with their inputs and 
success criteria.
</p>
<p>
A TestPlan describes the purpose, the dependencies, scope, test environment, test framework, test output, etc. 
It contains test cases which can describe technical or narrative test enter/exit criteria, test data, etc. 
A key aspect of the TestPlan design is that it nominated a 'runner', which is the specification of the system/software/rules
that actually administer the tests. Note that some TestPlan resources are directly executable by conformance testing 
tools, while others are intended to be used as a specification for manual testing.
</p>

</div>


<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The FHIR Specification defines another resource type called <a href="testscript.html">TestScript</a> that is used 
define test cases for the FHIR RESTful API. The TestScript resource differs from TestPlan in that it has a pre-defined
implicit test runner that is suitable for its stated purpose of testing FHIR RESTful APIs. 
</p>
<p>
As such, TestScript covers a subset of what TestPlan can do, and does so with much more precision and detail, 
and without the requirement for an external runner definition. TestPlan should not be used for tests that can
be specified using a TestScript resource. Note that the TestScript resource predates the TestPlan resource,
and is not expected to be withdrawn or replaced. 
</p>

</div>


<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
