<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>
Notes
</h2>
<ul>
<li>Questionnaires can be authored by clinicians, the patient his/herself or a patient's relatives (or even owner in the case of animals). Clinicians
may author questionnaires, where the answers are provided by others on behalf of the patient his/herself. Additionally, information gathered for the
purpose of a patient may be about the patient's relatives (e.g. in family anamnesis). Therefore, Questionnaire makes a distinction between the author,
the subject and the source of information.</li>
<li>A QuestionnaireAnswers may be stand-alone or may point to the form that defines the questions in <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>.  In
this second case, the linkage between the questions and groups in the two resources is established using the <code>linkId</code> element.</li>
<li>Because of the lack of explicit support for Questionnaires in HL7v3, HL7 CDA Documents frequently used named sections with
Observations to model Questionnaires. Such use cases should now utilize the QuestionnaireAnswers Resource instead.</li>
<li>The Questionnaire's <i>encounter</i> element can be used to link to the encounter during which the Questionnaire was taken. This can be relevant since the
encounter gives context to the answers and can be used to relate information in the Questionnaire to orders and observations that were done during the same Encounter.</li>
<li>The order of questions within groups, groups within groups and groups within questions is relevant and must be retained for display and capture.</li>
</ul>

<p>
Refer to additional guidance provided in the <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resource dealing with designs of questionnaires.
</p>

<h2>
Security
</h2>
<p>
QuestionnaireAnswers can have answers with values of type Attachment.  These attachments will typically be selected by the user answering the questionnaire and
this selection may be done in an uncontrolled environment.  Systems should ensure that the attachment is of the desired type and take precautions before
rendering or executing any attached content.
</p>

<h2>
Access Control
</h2>
<p>
For most resources, the type of information that can be conveyed in the resource is determined by the resource and the key attributes that
determine the sensitvity level of the information are also known.  E.g. drug, observation type, etc.  However, for QuestionnaireAnswers, the
sensitivity of an instance is dependent on what type of Questionnaire it's associated with.  And the data elements that determine that
sensitivity could be the answers to any of the questions.  This makes automatically enforcing access control rules more challenging.  Designers
should take these challenges into account and may need to place stricter access controls around QuestionnaireAnswers to ensure that access to
information is not granted improperly.
</p>

</div>
