<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
<b>QuestionnaireAnswers</b> provides a complete or partial list of answers to a set of questions.  The questions may be included directly or by
reference to a <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resource that defines the questions as well as the constraints on the allowed answers.  In
some cases, both may be provided to provide both formal rules for editing the questionnaire (via link to <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>) as
well as sufficient local information to allow rendering of the questionnaire.
</p>
<p>
Questionnaires cover the need to communicate data originating from forms used in medical history examinations, research questionnaires and sometimes full
clinical specialty records. In many systems this data is collected using user-defined screens and forms. Questionnaires record specifics about data capture -
exactly what questions were asked, in what order, what choices for answers were, etc. Each of these questions is part of the Questionnaire, 
and as such the Questionnaire is a separately identifiable Resource, whereas the individual questions are not.
</p>
<p>
Examples of Questionnaires include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Past medical history (PMH)</li>
<li>Family diseases</li>
<li>Social history</li>
<li>Research questionnaires/Clinical research forms (CRFs)</li>
<li>Quality and evaluation forms</li>
<li>Patient intake form (e.g. clipboard)</li>
<li>Insurance claim form</li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>QuestionnaireAnswers</b> can be validated against their corresponding <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> to verify that required
groups and questions are answered and that answers fit constraints in terms of cardinality, data type, etc.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The <b>QuestionnaireAnswers</b> resource captures the responses to a questionnaire, while <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> represents
the definition of the questionnaire form, including what questions are asked, how they're organized and the constraints on the allowed answers.
</p>
<p>
While <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, with its nested <code>relatedObservation</code> structure, can create complex hierarchies of 
questions and answers, the focus is different.  First, <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> is used primarily for capturing data elements that
are "true" observations - lab measurements, vital signs, social assessments, etc.  On the other hand, <b>QuestionnaireAnswers</b> can be used to capture
any types of data, including data that would typically map to other resources (<a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a>, <a href="patient.html">Patient</a>,
<a href="medicationstatement.html">MedicationStatement</a>, etc.)  In addition, the focus of <b>QuestionnaireAnswers</b> includes the specific phrasing
and organization of the questions.  All data must be explicitly captured as a question.  With <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, the focus is
only on the meaning of the answer, not what question was asked (assuming a question was even asked at all).  Additional information such as normal
ranges, interpretation, date, etc. may also be captured.
</p>
</div>

<!--<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
</p>
</div>-->

</div>





