<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<!-- content goes here -->
	<div>
		<a name="scope"/>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>The CatalogEntry resource allows to organize resources representing the definition of
			{products|services|knowledge artifacts|plans|observations|chemical or biological
			substances|professionals|roles|organizations|locations|physical objects} within catalogs
			or compendia assisting practitioners and|or patients in processes of healthcare
			delivery.</p>
		<p>Examples of such catalogs include:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>a pharmacy formulary</li>
			<li>a laboratory procedures compendium</li>
			<li>a radiology procedures compendium</li>
			<li>a dietary nutrition order catalog</li>
			<li>a supply charge master</li>
			<li>a CDS catalog of knowledge artifacts</li>
			<li>a directory of healthcare services</li>
			<li>a manufacturer catalog of medical devices</li>
			<li>the list of tests that an in vitro diagnostic device is able to perform</li>
		</ul>
		<p>A catalog or compendium for healthcare is represented in FHIR as an instance of the
			Composition resource, constrained by the Catalog profile. Such a resource contains
			nestable sections, each of which contains a number of entry elements referencing
			CatalogEntry resources. </p>
		<p>Thus, a CatalogEntry resource represents an entry of a Catalog. It acts as a wrapper that
			contextualizes the inclusion into the catalog of an item (product, service, artifact,
			location ...) directly orderable/selectable by catalog consumers. </p>
		<p> The CatalogEntry specifies the period of usability of the item by consumers of the
			catalog. It holds the current status of the item in the catalog as well as its
			orderability, the charges, limitations, constraints and regulations associated with the
			item in the context of this catalog. CatalogEntry facilitates the maintenance of the
			catalog over time, enabling to retire entries and to replace them by others, tracking
			who updates them. </p>
	</div>
	<div>
		<a name="bnr"/>
		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
		<p> CatalogEntry does not specify attributes that are pertinent to the item that it wraps if
			those attributes hold true regardless of the catalog context. For instance, a catalog
			entry does not provide attributes to describe the hierarchical relationship of an item
			to other items (e.g., drug class or other such ontological relationships) since that
			information holds outside of the context of a catalog and thus should reside in the
			referenced item itself. A catalog entry may, however, specify a status of a given item
					<b><i>in the context of the catalog</i></b> such as whether that item is
			orderable in the context of this catalog. Catalog entries can also be related to one
			another. Only relationships that hold within the context of a catalog and not generally
			for the items referenced by the catalog entries are supported this way. For instance, in
			the context of a given laboratory service compendium, a laboratory orderable service may
			be preferred over other laboratory services. The other laboratory services in this use
			case may thus be related to the preferred service using an 'is-replaced-by' relationship
			and assigned a new status of 'retired'. Conversely, other definitional relationships
			such as the specimen or expected input and output observation definitions associated
			with a particular laboratory test, relationships that generally hold outside of a
			laboratory catalog context, reside at the level of the definitional resource itself.
			That is, laboratory orderable procedures often state the required input observation
			specifications, the format of the expected observation output, and the attributes of the
			required specimens. These kind of relationships are described outside of the
			CatalogEntry within the referenced item. </p>
		<p> CatalogEntry is referenced by Composition.section[.section]*.entry, where Composition is
			constrained by the Catalog profile. CatalogEntry may also be referenced by
			CatalogEntry.relatedEntry.target, enabling entries of the catalog to refer to other
			entries that supersede them, or that may be automatically included at time of ordering
			or reporting. </p>
		<p> CatalogEntry.referencedItem references the resource representing the definitional item
			hooked to an entry of the catalog. The types of resources supported are:
			DeviceDefinition, Organization, Practitioner, PractitionerRole, HealthcareService,
			ActivityDefinition, PlanDefinition, SpecimenDefinition, ObservationDefinition,
			MedicationKnowledge, Medication, Substance, Location. </p>
	</div>
</div>