<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
	<a name="scope_and_usage"> </a>
	<h3>Scope and Usage</h3>
	
<p>
This profile sets expectations for use of the <a href="encounter.html">Encounter</a> resource within the <a href="daf.html">Data Access Framework (DAF)</a> Implementation Guide. This profile identifies which core elements, extensions, vocabularies and value sets must be <i>Supported</i> by DAF actors.
For the definition of <i>Supported</i> please refer to <a href="daf.html">DAF FHIR IG</a>. The data elements identified by the profile are based on ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC and DAF use cases. 
The mappings between the ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC data elements and DAF data elements are captured in the table below, where the first column identifies the ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC data element name, 
the second column maps the ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC data elements to DAF data elements which are derived from ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC standards and DAF use cases and lastly the third column identifies the mapping to FHIR resources and attributes.
</p>
</div>

<div>
	<a name="MU_data_element_mapping"> </a>
	<h3>Meaningful Use Data Element Mapping</h3>
<p>
The DAF Encounter profile mapping to Meaningful Use data elements and FHIR Resources are as shown below.
</p>
<br/>
	<table class="grid">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Meaningful Use Data Element Name</th>
			<th>Mapping to Priority DAF Data Elements</th>
            <th>FHIR Resource Mapping</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
		  <tr>
			<td>Encounter Diagnoses</td>
			<td/>
			<td/>
		  </tr>
          <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Encounter Start/End Time</td>
			<td>Encounter.period</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Specific Encounter Type</td>
			<td>Encounter.type</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Encounter class</td>
			<td>Encounter.class</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Encounter Location</td>
			<td>Encounter.location.location</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Encounter Admission and Discharge Dates</td>
			<td>Encounter.hospitalization.period</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Performer</td>
			<td>Encounter.participant.individual</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td/>
			<td>Encounter Reason</td>
			<td>Encounter.reason</td>
		  </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>

</div>


<div>
	<a name="boundaries_and_relationships"> </a>
	<h3>Boundaries and Relationships</h3>
<p>
This profile relies on the following other profiles:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="patient-daf.html">DAFPatient</a> which defines DAF Patient profile is used by DAFEncounter profile to refer to patients.</li>
  <li><a href="extensibility.html">FHIR Extensibility</a> defines how extensions can be applied to FHIR resources and data types. 
  Specifically the <a href="extension-data-absent-reason.html">data-absent-reason</a> extension can be used to code data elements with missing information when appropriate.
  See <a href="daf.html">DAF FHIR IG</a> for additional guidance.</li>
</ul>
</div>


</div>





