<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p> 
A patient encounter is further characterized by the setting in which it takes place. Amongst them are ambulatory,
 emergency, home health, inpatient and virtual encounters. An Encounter encompasses the lifecycle from pre-admission, 
 the actual encounter (for ambulatory encounters), and admission, stay and discharge (for inpatient encounters). 
During the encounter the patient may move from practitioner to practitioner and location to location.
</p>
<p>
Because of the broad scope of Encounter, not all elements will be relevant in all settings. For this reason, 
admission/discharge related information is kept in a separate Hospitalization component within Encounter. 
The <i>class</i> element is used to distinguish between these settings, which will guide further validation and
application of business rules.
</p>
<p>
There is also substantial variance from organization to organization (and between jurisdictions and countries) 
on which business events translate to the start of a new Encounter, or what level of aggregation is used for Encounter. For example, each
single visit of a practitioner during a hospitalization may lead to a new instance of Encounter, but depending on
local practice and the systems involved, it may well be that this is aggregated to a single instance for a whole hospitalization.
Even more aggregation may occur where jurisdictions introduce groups of Encounters for financial or other reasons.
Encounters can be aggregated or grouped under other Encounters using the <i>partOf</i> element. 
See <a href="#examples">below</a> for examples.
</p>

<p>
Encounter instances may exist before the actual encounter takes place to convey pre-admission information, including
using Encounters elements to reflect the planned start date, planned accommodation or planned encounter locations. In 
this case the <i>status</i> element is set to 'planned'.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p> 
Appointment information is out of scope for Encounter, the Appointment resource (yet to be defined) needs to be used for that. 
Note that in many systems outpatient encounters (which are in scope for Encounter) and Appointment are used 
concurrently. In FHIR, Appointment is used for establishing a date for the encounter, while Encounter is 
applicable to information about the actual Encounter, i.e. the patient showing up.
</p>
</div>

</div>
