<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Notes</h2>
<p>
<ul>
<li>The <i>class</i> element describes the setting (in/outpatient etc.) in which the Encounter took place. Since this is important for 
interpreting the context of the encounter, choosing the appropriate business rules to enforce and for the management of the process, this element
is required.</li>
<li>In future versions of FHIR, some kind of charge posting vehicle (e.g. Account) will be added.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<a name="examples" />
<h2>Example usage</h2>
<p>As stated, Encounter allows a flexible nesting of Encounters using the partOf element. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>A patient is admitted for two weeks - This could be modeled using a single Encounter instance,
in which the start and length are given for the duration of the whole stay. The admitting doctor and
the responsible doctor during the stay are specified using the Participant component.</li>
<li>During the encounter, the patient moves from the admitting department to the Intensive Care unit and back - 
Three more detailed additional Encounters can be created, one for each location in which the patient stayed.
Each of these Encounters has a single location (twice the admitting department and once
the Intensive Care unit) and one or more participants at that location. These Encounters may use the partOf 
relationship to indicate these movements occurred during the longer overarching Encounter.</li>
<li>During the last part of the stay, the patient is visited by the members of the multi-disciplinary team that
treated him for final evaluation - If relevant, for each of these short visits, an Encounter may be created
with a single participant. Since these took place during the last part of the stay, the partOf element can be
used to associate these short visits with either the third patient movement or the bigger overall encounter.</li>
</ul>
<p>Exactly how the Encounter is used depends on information available in the source system, the relevance of exchange
of each level of Encounter and demands specific to the communicating partners. The expectation is that for each
domain of exchange, Profiles are used to limit the flexibility of Encounter to meet the demands of the usecase.</p>

</div>
