<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
	<div>

		<h2>Status Management</h2>
		<h3>History and Period</h3>
		<p>
			When an Organization assumes responsibility for a patient, then the EpisodeOfCare is created and a start date
			entered to show when it has begun.<br/>
			As the Organizations responsibility changes, as does the status of the EpisodeOfCare.<br/>
			This is described via an example below for an example intake workflow.
		</p>
		<p></p>
		<h3>Leave Handling</h3>
		<p>
			With long term care there is often a concept of the provision of care being suspended for various reasons.
			Many systems have extensive Leave Management/Tracking solutions which consider the complexities of this space,
			however this EpisodeOfCare resource is NOT intended to provide this level of tracking.<br/>
		  Extension(s) may be used on the status/status history to track the onhold reason which can facilitite the processing.
		</p>
		<p>A more complete Leave Management solution may have to deal with:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Leave Types</li>
			<li>Leave Entitlements</li>
			<li>Billing/Funding implications while on different types of leave</li>
		</ul>

		<p></p>
		<h3>Example Intake Workflow</h3>
		<p>
			This example sequence demonstrates some status transitions and how other resources interact.<br/>
			The context could be in a Community/Aged Care/Disability/Mental Health setting.
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>ReferralRequest received</li>
			<li>
				<i>
					intake clerk processes referral and decides that the first level eligibility has been met<br/>
					(e.g. Have capacity in the facility for the patient, the patient is covered by VA)
				</i>
			</li>
			<li>EpisodeOfCare created with status of planned which is allocated as fulfilling the ReferralRequest</li>
			<li>
				<i>Further assessment of needs is scheduled to be taken, a care manager is probably allocated at this point</i>
			</li>
			<li>Assessment Practitioner sees the Patient and completes a series of relevant Questionnaires to rank the patient</li>
			<li>The assessments are reviewed and a formal CarePlan is created</li>
			<li>The EpisodeOfCare is updated to be marked as active, and the CareTeam is likely filled in</li>
			<li>
				<i>The provision of care is then managed through the care plan, with all activities will also being linked to the EpisodeOfCare</i>
			</li>
			<li>
				The patient is admitted to hospital for some procedures, EpisodeOfCare is marked as onhold<br/>
				Some of the services on the CarePlan (or scheduled appointments) would be reviewed to determine if they
				can be performed without the patient (e.g. Home Maintenance), or if they should be suspended while the
				patient is onhold.
			</li>
			<li>The patient returns from the hospital and the EpisodeOfCare is marked as active again (and services reviewed again)</li>
			<li>
				<i>Patient wished to move to another area to be closer to family</i>
			</li>
			<li>Organization creates an outgoing ReferralRequest to a new Organization to continue the care</li>
			<li>The EpisodeOfCare is closed</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
			In some jurisdictions an Organization may be funded by a government body for the days that a patient is under
			their care. These are known as "active days". This does not mean that they are actively receiving a service (an encounter),
			but that the organization is responsible for managing their care.<br/>
			This monthly reporting value can be easily extracted from the status history as described above.<br/>
			The actual provision of services may also be funded separately, and this would be via the Encounters.
		</p>

		<h3>EpisodeOfCare Outcomes Review</h3>
		<p>
			An Organization may perform analytics on their Episodes Of Care to have an understanding of how their business is performing.<br/>
			Observing that there was a 60/40 split of episodes being finished/cancelled is not very informative. The organization would
			prefer to know the reason why the episodes are completing so that they can plan their business effectively.<br/>
			They’d be more interested in knowing whether it was due to services hitting their mandatory end date, client passing away, 
			client transitioning to a higher level of services provided by them or to another provider etc.
		</p>
		<p>
			Currently there are no attributes on this resource to provide this information.
			This would be very specific to each implementation and usage, so it would be recommended to use extensions to achieve this functionality.
		</p>
	</div>

	<div>
		<h2>Example Scenarios</h2>
		<p>
			A General Practitioner wants to review how well his patient is managing his diabetes over time from information
			within his clinic and also the regional community care organization's system(s).
		</p>
		<p>
			The EpisodeOfCare enables the practitioner to easily separate the diabetes activities from the mental health problem's activities.
		</p>
		<p>
			A Community Care organization wants to track all activities that occur with a patient relating to their disability
			to simplify the reporting to the government to receive funding to care for the patient
		</p>
	</div>
</div>
