<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
The VisionPrescription resource represents an authorization for corrective optical lenses to be provided to a patient. Eye glasses and contact lenses usually require a prescription for patient-specific lenses. Details about the fulfillment of the authorization are handled by the <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource. For further information about this separation of responsibilities, refer to the link <a href="request.html#fulfillment">Fulfillment/Execution</a> section of the Request pattern.
		</p>
		<p>
Vision prescriptions may only be issued by providers who have optical diagnosis within their scope of practice, typically ophthalmologists  
and optometrists. The prescription is a time-limited, typically two years, authorization for the provision of an unlimited number of lenses, 
glasses or contacts, which conform to the authorized specification by providers which have lens provision within their scope of practice, typically ophthalmologists  
, optometrists and opticians. 
		</p>
		<p>Health insurers typically require a copy of the prescription to ensure that a vision professional has examined the patient and that the
 power of the lenses exceeds some minimum, such as +- 0.75 diopters, to qualify for reimbursement under the insurance coverage.</p>
		<p>The VisionPrescription resource is an "request" resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html#request">Workflow Request.</a></p>
		<h3>Additional Information</h3>
		<p>
Additional information regarding resources conveying electronic claims content and usage may be found at:
		</p>		
		<ul>
			<li><a href="financial-module.html#resource-status">Financial Resource Status Lifecycle</a>: how .status is used in the financial resources.</li>
		</ul>
	</div>
	<div>
		<a name="bnr"></a>
		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

		<p>The VisionPrescription resource is used to provide the authorized specification of lenses for glasses and contacts which 
		have well known and internationally consistent requirements, which is distinct from other types of health care authorizations detailed below.
		</p>
		<b>The health care domain includes a number of related resources</b>

		<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="2" frame="box">
			<tr>
				<td>VisionPrescription (this resource)</td>
				<td>This resource is used to prescribe, authorize, and request provision of lenses for glasses or contacts.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><a href="devicerequest.html">DeviceRequest</a></td>
				<td>This resource is used to prescribe, authorize, and request provision of a health care device such as a halter monitor or a wheelchair services.
				</td>
			</tr>			
			<tr>
				<td><a href="medicationrequest.html">MedicationRequest</a></td>
				<td>This resource is used to prescribe, authorize, and request provision of medications such a pharmaceuticals and vaccines.
				</td>
			</tr>			
			<tr>
				<td><a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a></td>
				<td>This resource is used to prescribe, authorize, and request provision of health care services such as consultative or rehabilitative services.
				</td>
			</tr>	
			<tr>
				<td><a href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/oo-incubator/StructureDefinition-SupplyRequest.html">SupplyRequest</a></td>
				<td>This resource is used for inventory management of a supply item (which may include a medication, substance or device).
				</td>
			</tr>		
		</table>

	</div>
</div>	