<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="notes"></a>
<h2>Notes</h2>
  <h3>Imaging Selection Subsets</h3>
  <p>Some DICOM SOP Instances contain sub-resources, such as frames, segments, etc.</p>
  <p>An Imaging Selection resource can specify the subset of these that are included in the selection using the following elements.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>instance.frameNumber</code> - Frames selected from a multiframe SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced Frame Number (0008,1160) </li>
        <li>Each value specifies a frame included in the selection</li>
        <li>Note: Frame number is implicit, and the first frame is denoted as frame 1</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.referencedContentItemIdentifier</code> - Referenced Content Item Identifiers selected from a DICOM SR or other structured document SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced Content Item Identifier (0040,DB73)</li>
        <li>Each value specifies the node in the DICOM SR tree that is selected at each level</li>
        <li>See <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part03/sect_C.17.3.2.5.html">DICOM PS 3.3 C.17.3.2.5</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.segmentNumber</code> - Segments selected from a segmentation SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced Segment Number (0062,000B)</li>
        <li>Each value specifies a segment included in the selection</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.regionOfInterest</code> - Regions of interest selected from a radiotherapy structure set SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced ROI Number (0002,000E)</li>
        <li>Each value specifies a region of interest included in the selection</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.waveFormChannel</code> - Channels selected from a waveform SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Specified as a pair of values (M,C), where the first value is the Item number of Waveform Sequence (5400,0100) in the referenced object (i.e., the Multiplex Group Number), and the second Value is the Item number of Channel Definition Sequence (003A,0200) (i.e., the Channel Number) within the multiplex group</li>
        <li>Each value pair specifies a channel included in the selection</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>The value of the <code>instance.sopClass</code> element determines which type of subset can be present.</p>
  <p>For example:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>If <code>instance.sopClass</code> has a value of <code>urn:oid:1.2.840.10008.5.1.4.1.1.2.1</code>, this indicates that the instance is Enhanced CT, which is a multiframe image instance and therefore <code>instance.frameNumber</code> can be included to specify a list of frames</li>
    <li>If <code>instance.sopClass</code> has a value of <code>urn:oid:1.2.840.10008.5.1.4.1.1.88.22</code>, this indicates that the instance is Enhanced SR and therefore <code>instance.referencedContentItemIdentifier</code> can be included to specify a list of content item identifiers</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Note: Because an imaging selection instance is limited to a single DICOM Series and each DICOM Series can contain only one type of instance - image, SR document, radiotherapy object, etc. - each imaging selection instance can only contain one type of subset.</p>

  <h3>Use of ImagingSelection.code and ImagingSelection.category</h3>
  <p>
  The code and category element can be used to provide information relevant for applications that want to identify specific types of ImagingSelection resources.
  </p>
  <p>
  For example, if an ImagingSelection is used to identify a set of images that make up a volume rendered view, the code could contain a code indicating Volume Rendering - such as RadLex RID35862 - and the category could contain values of the DICOM Image Type <code>(0008,0008)</code> attribute - such as DERVIED and SECONDARY.
  </p>
  <pre>
  {
    "resource": {
      "resourceType": "ImagingSelection",
      "id": "fa8e0948175f3117a3b8c4be2ff972ec",
      "subject": {
        "reference": "Patient/acb045960122378999c97cd7ca532f8b"
      },
      "code": {
        "coding": [
          {
            "system": "http://radlex.org/",
            "code": "RID12769",
            "display": "volume rendering"
          }
        ]
      },
      "category": [
        {
          "text": "DERIVED"
        },
        {
          "text": "SECONDARY"
        }
      ]
    }
  }
</pre>

<a name="req-by-type"></a>
<h3>Element Requirements by Selection Type</h3>

<p>
This section outlines several imaging selection types, each listing a set of resource elements that are required and/or typically present in the selection. Some types require only a minimal set of elements, while others require a comprehensive list to ensure clarity.
</p>

<h4>Single-Frame Image Selection</h4>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to one single-frame image requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>studyUid</code> to identify the DICOM Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>seriesUid</code> to identify the Series within the Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>instance</code> containing a single entry that specifies:
  <ul>
    <li><code>uid</code> to identify the SOP Instance UID of the selected image</li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
While not required, this type of selection typically includes:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system of the image</li>
<li><code>instance.sopClass</code> to specify the SOP Class UID of the selected image</li>
</ul>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-single-frame-image-selection.html">Single-Frame Image Selection example</a>.
</p>

<h4>Multiframe Image Selection</h4>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to frames in a multiframe image requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>studyUid</code> to identify the DICOM Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>seriesUid</code> to identify the Series within the Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>instance</code> containing a single entry that specifies:
  <ul>
    <li><code>uid</code> to identify the SOP Instance UID of the selected image</li>
    <li><code>frameNumber</code> to identify the list of frames included in the selection</li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
While not required, this type of selection typically includes:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system of the image</li>
<li><code>instance.sopClass</code> to specify the SOP Class UID of the selected image</li>
</ul>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-multiframe-image-selection.html">Multiframe Image Selection example</a>.
</p>

<h4>2D Image Selection</h4>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to a 2D region on an image requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>studyUid</code> to identify the DICOM Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>seriesUid</code> to identify the Series within the Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>instance</code> containing a single entry that specifies:
  <ul>
    <li><code>uid</code> to identify the SOP Instance UID of the selected image</li>
    <li><code>imageRegion2D</code> containing
      <ul>
        <li><code>regionType</code> specifying the type of image region</li>
        <li><code>coordinate</code> specifying the x and y coordinates that define the image region in image pixel space</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
While not required, this type of selection typically includes:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system of the image</li>
<li><code>instance.sopClass</code> to specify the SOP Class UID of the selected image</li>
</ul>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-2d-image-region-selection.html">2D Image Region Selection example</a>.
</p>

<h4>3D Image Selection</h4>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to a 3D region requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system that includes the specified coordinates</li>
<li><code>imageRegion3D</code> containing
  <ul>
    <li><code>regionType</code> specifying the type of image region</li>
    <li><code>coordinate</code> specifying the x, y and z coordinates that define the 3D region</li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
This type of selection can also specify a set of images but this is not required. The 3D region selection can be applied to any images that share the same Frame of Reference UID.
</p>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-3d-image-region-selection.html">3D Image Region Selection example</a>.
</p>

<a name="endpoints"></a>
<h3>ImagingSelection Endpoints</h3>
<p>
The ImagingSelection.endpoint elements indicate network 
services that can be used to access the imaging data referenced by the imaging selection; for example, a DICOM WADO-RS server.  
Systems can determine if the relevant imaging data is available or offline by interacting with the endpoint.
</p>
<p>
Different Endpoint connection types can have different capabilities, protocols or requirements.
Furthermore, the specified 
<code>Endpoint.address</code> 
identifies the DICOM Web Service Base URI (see <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/sect_8.2.html">DICOM PS 3.18 Section 8.2</a> ). 
The URL needed to retrieve image data might need to be constructed from this base URL. See below for the details on use of imaging-related Endpoint connection types.
</p>
<a name="wado-rs"></a>
<h4>WADO-RS</h4>
<p>
An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-rs</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-RS service. 
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-RS (Web Access to DICOM Objects, RESTful mode) service uses a RESTful approach to instance retrieval.
This service allows for retrieval of native DICOM SOP instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including
JPEG and MPEG. The media type of a response is specified by the request Accept header (preferred); or, by the <code>accept</code>
query parameters. Supported media types depend on the  capabilities of the WADO-RS server and the classification of the instance 
as "single frame", "multi-frame", "video", "text", or "other". The WADO-RS service also allows retrieval of study
or series level information.
</p>
<p>
The path to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate sub-resource paths to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingSelection resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-RS service base URL of <code>https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>“urn:dicom:uid”</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Series Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.uid</code>, and</li>
<li>the DICOM SOP Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.instance.uid</code></li>
</ul>
we can construct the WADO-RS URL to issue an HTTP GET for a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file (if consistent with the Accept header):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2

</pre>
<a name="wado-uri"></a>
<h4>WADO-URI</h4>
<p>An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-uri</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-URI service. 
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-URI (Web Access to DICOM Objects, URI mode) service uses HTTP query parameter syntax. This service allows
for retrieval of native DICOM instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including JPEG and MPEG. The media
type of a response is specified by the request Accept header (preferred); or, by the contentType query parameter.
Supported media types depend on the classification of the instance as "single frame", "multi-frame", "video", "text", or "other."
</p>
<p>
The query to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate query parameters to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingSelection resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-URI service base URL of <code>https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>urn:dicom:uid</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Series Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.uid</code>, and</li>
<li>the DICOM SOP Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.instance.uid</code></li>
</ul>
we can construct the WADO-URI URL to issue an HTTP GET for a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file (if consistent with the Accept header):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2

</pre>

  <a name="laterality"></a>
  <h3>Body Site and Laterality</h3>
  <p>
    The <code>bodySite</code> element can include the laterality of the (possibly paired) anatomic structures examined – e.g., left knee, bilateral lungs, etc. This can be conveyed in several ways:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>bodySite</code> contains an anatomic code that includes laterality, e.g.
      <pre class="json">
"bodySite": {
  "concept": {
    "coding": [{
      "system": "http://snomed.info/sct",
      "code": "5951000",
      "display": "Left wrist"
    }]
  }
}
      </pre>
    </li>
    <li><code>bodySite</code> contains a reference to a <code>BodyStructure</code> resource whose <code>includedStructure.structure</code> element contains an anatomic code that includes laterality</li>
    <li><code>bodySite</code> contains a reference to a <code>BodyStructure</code> resource whose <code>includedStructure</code> element includes a laterality value. See this <a href="bodystructure-example-dicom-includedStructure.html">example BodyStructure representation of the Left Wrist, with laterality and SNOMED coding for anatomical structure</a>.</li>
  </ul>
</div>
