<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <a name="scope"></a>
    <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
    <p>This resource is an <a href="workflow.html#event">
      <em>event resource</em>
    </a> from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.</p>
    <p>A selection of DICOM SOP instances and/or frames within a single Study and Series which might include additional specifics such as region or other DICOM UIDs, for example, ObservationUID, TrackingUID or SegmentationUID, allowing linkage to an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> or transferring this information along with the <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>.</p>
    <p><b>Note:</b> DICOM SOP Instances can include images, videos, waveforms or documents.</p>
    <p>Uses for ImagingSelection resources include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Referencing a specific image, frame or region in an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a></li>
      <li>Referencing the set of images, frames or segments constituting a volume in an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a></li>
      <li>Referencing the set of image coordinates that relate to a measurement in an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a></li>
      <li>Linking a node in a DICOM Structured Report SOP Instance to an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a></li>
      <li>Referencing key images selected from an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a></li>
      <li>Referencing presentation states to be applied to a set of images from an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a></li>
      <li>Referencing the set of loaded images or frames from a study that are "in context" in a context-sharing environment</li>
    </ul>
    <p>All DICOM SOP Instances referenced shall be part of the same DICOM Series (and therefore also the same DICOM Study). In order to reference SOP Instances in multiple Studies or Series it is necessary to create multiple ImagingSelection resources.</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <a name="bnr"></a>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
    <p>An <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> references an ImagingSelection to specify the set of DICOM images, frames, waveforms or documents used to make the <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>. By contrast, an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> references an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> if it does not depend on any specific set of images, frames, waveforms or documents.</p>
    <p>An <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> references an ImagingSelection to specify an image region corresponding to the measurement value expressed in the <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>.</p>
    <p>While an ImagingSelection is restricted to a single DICOM Series, a single <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> references multiple ImagingSelection resources if it relates to multiple Studies and / or Series – for example, to reference multiple images over different cardiac phases or a PET and a CT image.</p>
    <p>A <a href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a> might directly reference an ImagingSelection that includes one or more Observations derived from ImagingSelection resources.</p>
    <p>In contrast with a <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a>, an ImagingSelection includes the ability to specify a region within an image, an observation node within a DICOM Structured Reporting (SR) and the ability to specify one or more Endpoint resources for retrieval of the referenced images, frames, waveforms or documents. Additionally, <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> has limited ability to reference multiple images or frames and can only specify the Study, Series and SOP Instance UIDs implicitly via the URL.</p>
    <p><a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> might be appropriate for including a rendered DICOM image in cases where the full image context is not important.</p>
  </div>

</div>
