<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="notes"></a>
<h2>Notes</h2>
  <h3>Imaging Selection Subsets</h3>
  <p>Some DICOM SOP Instances contain multiple sub-resources, such as frames, segments, etc.</p>
  <p>An Imaging Selection resource MAY specify the subset of these that are included in the selection using the <code>instance.subset</code> element.</p>
  <p>The defined types of subsets are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Frames selected from a multiframe SOP Instance</li>
    <li>Referenced Content Item Identifiers selected from a DICOM SR or other structured document SOP Instance</li>
    <li>Segments selected from a segmentation SOP Instance</li>
    <li>Regions of interest selected from a radiotherapy structure set SOP Instance</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The type of subset is determined by the SOP Class of the parent instance.</p>
  <p>Subsets can only reference sub-resources that are already defined within the selected DICOM SOP Instance.</p>

  <h3>Use of ImagingSelection.code and ImagingSelection.category</h3>
  <p>
  The code and category element can be used to information relevant for applications that want to identify specific types of ImagingSelection resources.
  </p>
  <p>
  As code is required and limited to a single value, it holds the primary purpose of the ImagingSelection. Additional applicable values populate the category element.
  </p>
  <p>
  For example, if an ImagingSelection is used to identify a set of images that make up a volume rendered view, the code could contain a code indicating Volume Rendering - such as RadLex RID35862 - and the category could contain values of the DICOM Image Type <code>(0008,0008)</code> attribute - such as DERVIED and SECONDARY.
  </p>
  <pre>
  {
    "resource": {
      "resourceType": "ImagingSelection",
      "id": "fa8e0948175f3117a3b8c4be2ff972ec",
      "subject": {
        "reference": "Patient/acb045960122378999c97cd7ca532f8b"
      },
      "code": {
        "coding": [
          {
            "system": "http://radlex.org/",
            "code": "RID12769",
            "display": "volume rendering"
          }
        ]
      },
      "category": [
        {
          "text": "DERIVED"
        },
        {
          "text": "SECONDARY"
        }
      ]
    }
  }
</pre>
<p></p>

</div>
