<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="notes"></a>
<h2>Notes</h2>
  <h3>Imaging Selection Subsets</h3>
  <p>Some DICOM SOP Instances contain sub-resources, such as frames, segments, etc.</p>
  <p>An Imaging Selection resource can specify the subset of these that are included in the selection using the following elements.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>instance.frameNumber</code> - Frames selected from a multiframe SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced Frame Number (0008,1160) </li>
        <li>Each value specifies a frame included in the selection</li>
        <li>Note: Frame number is implicit, and the first frame is denoted as frame 1</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.referencedContentItemIdentifier</code> - Referenced Content Item Identifiers selected from a DICOM SR or other structured document SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced Content Item Identifier (0040,DB73)</li>
        <li>Each value specifies the node in the DICOM SR tree that is selected at each level</li>
        <li>See <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part03/sect_C.17.3.2.5.html">DICOM PS3.3 C.17.3.2.5</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.segmentNumber</code> - Segments selected from a segmentation SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced Segment Number (0062,000B)</li>
        <li>Each value specifies a segment included in the selection</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.regionOfInterest</code> - Regions of interest selected from a radiotherapy structure set SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Corresponds to the value of DICOM Referenced ROI Number (0002,000E)</li>
        <li>Each value specifies a region of interest included in the selection</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.waveFormChannel</code> - Channels selected from a waveform SOP Instance
      <ul>
        <li>Specified as a pair of values (M,C), where the first value is the Item number of Waveform Sequence (5400,0100) in the referenced object (i.e., the Multiplex Group Number), and the second Value is the Item number of Channel Definition Sequence (003A,0200) (i.e., the Channel Number) within the multiplex group</li>
        <li>Each value pair specifies a channel included in the selection</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.imageRegion2D</code> - A selected 2D image region
      <ul>
        <li>Defined by a region type and a set of 2D coordinates in pixel space</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><code>instance.imageRegion3D</code> - A selected 3D image region
      <ul>
        <li>Defined by a region type and a set of 3D coordinates</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>The value of the <code>instance.sopClass</code> element determines which type of subset can be present.</p>
  <p>For example:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>If <code>instance.sopClass</code> has a value of <code>urn:oid:1.2.840.10008.5.1.4.1.1.2.1</code>, this indicates that the instance is Enhanced CT, which is a multiframe image instance and therefore <code>instance.frameNumber</code> can be included to specify a list of frames</li>
    <li>If <code>instance.sopClass</code> has a value of <code>urn:oid:1.2.840.10008.5.1.4.1.1.88.22</code>, this indicates that the instance is Enhanced SR and therefore <code>instance.referencedContentItemIdentifier</code> can be included to specify a list of content item identifiers</li>
    <li>If <code>instance.sopClass</code> has a value of <code>urn:oid:1.2.840.10008.5.1.4.1.1.2</code>, this indicates that the instance is CT, which is an image instance and therefore <code>instance.imageRegion2D</code> can be included to specify an image region in pixel space</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="code-and-category"></a>
  <h3>Use of ImagingSelection.code and ImagingSelection.category</h3>
  <p>
  The code and category element can be used to provide information relevant for applications that want to identify specific types of ImagingSelection resources.
  </p>
  <p>
  For example, if an ImagingSelection is used to identify a set of images that make up a volume rendered view, the code could contain a code indicating Volume Rendering - such as DICOM 121347 - and the category could contain DICOM 128196, indicating that the selection was made for segmentation purposes.
  </p>
  <pre>
  {
    "resource": {
      "resourceType": "ImagingSelection",
      "id": "fa8e0948175f3117a3b8c4be2ff972ec",
      "subject": {
        "reference": "Patient/acb045960122378999c97cd7ca532f8b"
      },
      "code": {
        "coding": [
          {
            "system": "http://dicom.nema.org/resources/ontology/DCM",
            "code": "121347",
            "display": "Volume corresponding to spatially-related acquisition frames"
          }
        ]
      },
      "category": [
        {
          "coding": [
            {
              "system": "http://dicom.nema.org/resources/ontology/DCM",
              "code": "128196",
              "display": "For Segmentation"
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  }
</pre>

<a name="use-cases"></a>
<h3>Element Requirements by Use Case</h3>

<p>
This section outlines several imaging selection use cases, and for each, lists a set of resource elements that are required and/or typically present in the selection. Some types require only a minimal set of elements, while others require a comprehensive list to ensure clarity.
</p>

<a name="use-case-1"></a>
<h4>Use Case 1 – Referencing a specific image from an Observation</h4>
<p>
  When an observation is made based on an image within an imaging study, an imaging selection can be used to reference the specific image that:
</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Best displays the anatomic structure or pathology related to the observation</li>
    <li>Represents a specific point in a temporal cycle (e.g. a cardiac phase)</li>
    <li>etc.</li>
  </ul>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to one single-frame image requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>studyUid</code> to identify the DICOM Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>seriesUid</code> to identify the Series within the Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>instance</code> containing a single entry that specifies:
  <ul>
    <li><code>uid</code> to identify the SOP Instance UID of the selected image</li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
While not required, this type of selection typically includes:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system of the image</li>
<li><code>instance.sopClass</code> to specify the SOP Class UID of the selected image</li>
</ul>
<p>
  The resulting imaging selection would be referenced by the derivedFrom element of the associated <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>.
</p>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-single-frame-image-selection.html">Single-Frame Image Selection example</a>.
</p>

  <a name="use-case-2"></a>
  <h4>Use Case 2 – Referencing a set of frames from an Observation</h4>
  <p>
    When an observation is made based on a set of frames within an imaging study, an imaging selection can be used to reference the specific set of frames that were:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Used to create a volume rendered view</li>
    <li>Selected to represent a specific point in a temporal cycle (e.g. a cardiac phase)</li>
    <li>etc.</li>
  </ul>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to frames in a multiframe image requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>studyUid</code> to identify the DICOM Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>seriesUid</code> to identify the Series within the Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>instance</code> containing a single entry that specifies:
  <ul>
    <li><code>uid</code> to identify the SOP Instance UID of the selected image</li>
    <li><code>frameNumber</code> to identify the list of frame numbers included in the selection</li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
While not required, this type of selection typically includes:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system of the image</li>
<li><code>instance.sopClass</code> to specify the SOP Class UID of the selected image</li>
</ul>
  <p>
    The resulting imaging selection would be referenced by the derivedFrom element of the associated <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>.
  </p>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-multiframe-image-selection.html">Multiframe Image Selection example</a>.
</p>

  <a name="use-case-3"></a>
  <h4>Use Case 3 – Referencing a set of 2D image coordinates that relate to an Observation</h4>
  <p>
    When an observation relates to a 2D region of a specific image, an imaging selection can be created to reference:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>The specific image coordinates that correspond to a measurement</li>
    <li>The image region relating to observed pathology</li>
    <li>etc.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
An imaging selection that points to a 2D region on an image requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>studyUid</code> to identify the DICOM Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>seriesUid</code> to identify the Series within the Study that contains the image</li>
<li><code>instance</code> containing a single entry that specifies:
  <ul>
    <li><code>uid</code> to identify the SOP Instance UID of the selected image</li>
    <li><code>imageRegion2D</code> containing
      <ul>
        <li><code>regionType</code> specifying the type of image region</li>
        <li><code>coordinate</code> specifying the x and y coordinates that define the image region in image pixel space</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
While not required, this type of selection typically includes:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system of the image</li>
<li><code>instance.sopClass</code> to specify the SOP Class UID of the selected image</li>
</ul>
  <p>
    The resulting imaging selection would be referenced by the derivedFrom element of the associated <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>.
  </p>
<p>
See <a href="imagingselection-example-2d-image-region-selection.html">2D Image Region Selection example</a>.
</p>
<p>
Note that the <code>imageRegion2D</code> and <code>imageRegion3D</code> elements are mutually exclusive; an imaging selection cannot include both types of image region.
</p>

  <a name="use-case-4"></a>
  <h4>Use Case 4 – Referencing a set of 3D coordinates that relate to an Observation</h4>
  <p>
    When an observation relates to a 3D region within a specific frame of reference, an imaging selection can be created to reference:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>The specific 3D coordinates that correspond to a measurement</li>
    <li>The 3D image region relating to observed pathology</li>
    <li>etc.</li>
  </ul>
<p>
An imaging selection that points to a 3D region requires:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>frameOfReferenceUid</code> to identify the coordinate system that includes the specified coordinates</li>
<li><code>imageRegion3D</code> containing
  <ul>
    <li><code>regionType</code> specifying the type of image region</li>
    <li><code>coordinate</code> specifying the x, y and z coordinates that define the 3D region</li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
This type of selection can also specify a set of images but this is not required. The 3D region selection can be applied to any images that share the same Frame of Reference UID.
</p>
  <p>
    The resulting imaging selection would be referenced by the derivedFrom element of the associated <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    See <a href="imagingselection-example-3d-image-region-selection.html">3D Image Region Selection example</a>.
  </p>
<p>
Note that the <code>imageRegion2D</code> and <code>imageRegion3D</code> elements are mutually exclusive; an imaging selection cannot include both types of image region.
</p>

  <a name="use-case-5"></a>
  <h4>Use Case 5 – Referencing a key image from a diagnostic report</h4>
  <p>
    An imaging selection can be created to reference a key image that has been identified for inclusion within an observation included in a diagnostic report.
  </p>
  <p>
    The encoding of this type of imaging selection is the same as <a href="imagingselection.html#use-case-1">Use Case 1</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    The resulting imaging selection would be referenced from the diagnostic report – e.g., via its relationship to a relevant observation – or from a composition that describes the presentation of the report.
  </p>

  <a name="endpoints"></a>
<h3>ImagingSelection Endpoints</h3>
<p>
The <code>ImagingSelection.endpoint</code> elements indicate network
services that can be used to access the imaging data referenced by the imaging selection; for example, a DICOM WADO-RS server.  
Systems can determine if the relevant imaging data is available or offline by interacting with the endpoint.
</p>
<p>
Different <a href="endpoint.html">Endpoint</a> connection types can have different capabilities, protocols or requirements.
Furthermore, the specified 
<code>Endpoint.address</code>
identifies the DICOM Web Service Base URI (see <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/sect_8.2.html">DICOM PS3.18 Section 8.2</a> ).
The URL to retrieve image data is from this base URL. See below for the details on the use of imaging-related <a href="endpoint.html">Endpoint</a> connection types.
</p>
<a name="wado-rs"></a>
<h4>WADO-RS</h4>
<p>
An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-rs</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-RS service (see <a href="endpoint-example-wadors.html">example of DICOM WADO-RS endpoint)</a>.
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-RS (Web Access to DICOM Objects, RESTful mode) service uses a RESTful approach to instance retrieval.
This service allows for retrieval of native DICOM SOP instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including
JPEG and MPEG. The preferred media type of a response is specified by the request Accept header; or, by the <code>accept</code>
query parameters. Supported media types depend on the  capabilities of the WADO-RS server and the classification of the instance 
as "single frame", "multiframe", "video", "text", or "other". The WADO-RS service also allows retrieval of study
or series level information.
</p>
<p>
The path to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate sub-resource paths to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingSelection resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-RS service base URL of <code>https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>“urn:dicom:uid”</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Series Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.uid</code>, and</li>
<li>the DICOM SOP Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.instance.uid</code></li>
</ul>
we can construct the WADO-RS URL to issue an HTTP GET for a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file:
</p>
<pre>

GET https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2 HTTP/1.1
Accept: multipart/related; type="application/dicom"

</pre>
<p>
Query parameters on the "rendered" sub-resource can control other aspects of the rendering including: the rendered dimensions, the
quality (compression ratio), the region of interest to render, the brightness/contrast (window center/width)
adjustments, and whether to “burn” patient or study demographics into the rendered result. Specific frames
of a multiframe instance can be retrieved using the frames sub-resource.
</p>
<p>
The example above can be
extended with parameters that request an image of a region extending from
the top-left corner of the original image to 1000 pixels across and 3000 pixels right, to be rendered to a size of 400 columns by 400 rows:
</p>
<pre>

GET https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2<b>/rendered?viewport=400,400,0,0,1000,3000</b> HTTP/1.1
Accept: image/jpeg

</pre>
<p>
If the specified WADO-RS service supports the DICOMweb thumbnail resource, a representative image of the study can be requested, for example, to display alongside the study. The URL would look as follows:
</p>
<pre>

GET https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/thumbnail HTTP/1.1
Accept: image/jpeg

</pre>
<p>
For further details on DICOM WADO-RS capabilities including additional rendering parameters,
see <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/sect_10.4.html">DICOM PS3.18 Section 10.4</a>.
</p>
<a name="wado-uri"></a>
<h4>WADO-URI</h4>
<p>
An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-uri</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, identifies a DICOM WADO-URI service (see <a href="endpoint-example-wado-uri.html">example of DICOM WADO-URI endpoint</a>).
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-URI (Web Access to DICOM Objects, URI mode) service uses HTTP query parameter syntax. This service allows
for retrieval of native DICOM instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including JPEG and MPEG. The preferred media
type of a response is specified by the request Accept header; or, by the contentType query parameter.
Supported media types depend on the classification of the instance as "single frame", "multiframe", "video", "text", or "other."
</p>
<p>
The query to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate query parameters to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingSelection resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-URI service base URL of <code>https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910</code> found in an <code>ImagingSelection.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>urn:dicom:uid</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Series Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.uid</code>, and</li>
<li>the DICOM SOP Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2</code> found in <code>ImagingSelection.series.instance.uid</code></li>
</ul>
we can construct the WADO-URI URL to issue an HTTP GET for a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file:
</p>
<pre>

GET https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2 HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/dicom

</pre>
<p>
Additional query parameters can control other aspects of the rendering including rendered dimensions, quality (compression
ratio), the region of interest within the image to render, brightness/contrast (window center/width) adjustments, whether
to “burn” patient or study demographics into the rendered result, and which frame of a multiframe instance to retrieve.
</p>
<p>
The example above can be extended with
parameters that request a 100x100 image thumbnail of the left half of the image to be retrieved:
</p>
<pre>

GET https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2&amp;<b>rows=100&amp;columns=100&amp;region=0,0,0.5,1 </b> HTTP/1.1
Accept: image/jpeg

</pre>
<p>
For further details on DICOM WADO-URI capabilities including additional rendering parameters,
see <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/chapter_9.html">DICOM PS3.18 Chapter 9</a>.
</p>

  <a name="laterality"></a>
  <h3>Body Site and Laterality</h3>
  <p>
    The <code>bodySite</code> element can include the laterality of the (possibly paired) anatomic structures examined – e.g. left knee, bilateral lungs, etc. This can be conveyed in several ways:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>bodySite</code> contains an anatomic code that includes laterality, e.g.
      <pre class="json">
"bodySite": {
  "concept": {
    "coding": [{
      "system": "http://snomed.info/sct",
      "code": "5951000",
      "display": "Left wrist"
    }]
  }
}
      </pre>
    </li>
    <li><code>bodySite</code> contains a reference to a <a href="bodystructure.html">BodyStructure</a> resource whose <code>includedStructure.structure</code> element contains an anatomic code that includes laterality</li>
    <li><code>bodySite</code> contains a reference to a <a href="bodystructure.html">BodyStructure</a> resource whose <code>includedStructure</code> element includes a laterality value. See this <a href="bodystructure-example-dicom-includedStructure.html">example BodyStructure representation of the Left Wrist, with laterality and SNOMED coding for anatomical structure</a>.</li>
    <li>The <code>bodySite</code> element can also reference a <a href="bodystructure.html">BodyStructure</a> resource when – in addition to laterality – a referenced body site requires specifying position relative to a specific body landmark. See this <a href="bodystructure-example-breast-mass.html">example BodyStructure of a breast mass with body landmark orientation specified</a>.</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="dicom-uids"></a>
  <h3>DICOM UIDs as Identifiers</h3>
  <p>
    In some cases, the <code>ImagingSelection.identifier</code> will be a DICOM UID, such as an Observation UID (see <a href="https://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part03/sect_C.17.3.4.html#table_C.17-6">DICOM PS3.3 Table C.17-6</a>).
  </p>
  <p>
    When using a DICOM UID as the identifier, use the Identifier system of <code>"urn:dicom:uid"</code>, and prefix the UID value with <code>"urn:oid:"</code>.
  </p>
  <a name="status"></a>
  <h3>ImagingSelection.status</h3>
  <p>
    Typically, an ImagingSelection is a FHIR representation of imaging data that has been selected for a specific clinical purpose. The value of the status element reflects the status of this representation and does not necessarily reflect the status of either the underlying imaging data or any <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a> or <a href="task.html">Task</a> resources that resulted in the ImagingSelection being created.
  </p>
  <p>
    Typically, an ImagingSelection is created with an initial status of <code>available</code>. At this stage the ImagingSelection can be presented to viewing applications.
  </p>
  <p>
    If the ImagingSelection is incorrect — e.g., due to the wrong images being selected — it might be corrected with an update operation or set to <code>entered-in-error</code> and replaced with a new ImagingSelection.
  </p>
  <p>
    If the ImagingSelection is no longer valid – e.g., an automated selection was made by an application and deemed not to be relevant by a user – the status should be set to <code>inactive</code>.
  </p>
</div>
