<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is an <em>event</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.   It is the intent of the Orders and Observation Workgroup to align this resource with  the workflow pattern for <a href="workflow.html#event"><em>event</em> resources</a>.</strong></p>
<p>
The Transport resource captures the requested movement and movement history of persons and items in the healthcare spectrum. The Transport resource documents the movement of a person or item. Since it follows the event pattern, it can be used in the request of a transport event, but it can be used in conjunction with the Task resource to operationalize a movement event in a workflow. While the current use cases are focused on the lab and the movement of patients, this resource will be easily extensible to handle the movement of anything in healthcare. Sample use cases for the laboratory are as follows: 
<ul>
<li>Movement of a specimen between distinct healthcare locations (clinic to lab, lab to lab, lab to biorepository) without the use of a third-party transport system (e.g. a courier)</li>
<li>Movement of a specimen between distinct healthcare locations (clinic to lab, lab to lab, lab to biorepository) with the use of a third-party transport system (e.g. a courier)</li>
<li>Accessing the current location (tracking) and the complete location history (audit) for a given specimen.</li>
</ul>
Sample use cases involving patients include 
<ul>
<li>Movement of a patient within a healthcare setting (changing floors of the hospital)</li>
<li>Movement of a patient between healthcare settings (moving a patient from one hospital to another)</li>
</ul> 
</p>
</div>

<div>
    <a name="bnc"></a>
    <h2>Background and Context</h2>
    <p>
    With the emergence of IHE profiles on the movement of laboratory specimens (<a href="https://wiki.ihe.net/index.php/Specimen_Event_Tracking#:~:text=The%20Specimen%20Event%20Tracking%20(SET,future%20usage%2C%20and%20to%20final">SET</a>) and the growing needs around the movement of patients (documentation, scheduling, real-time updates), there is a need to capture the data around the movement of a patient or item in the healthcare setting. While the Task resource captures some of the data generated around an event, the Transport resource is built to capture the documentation along with the request/fulfillment of a transport event. 
    </p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The Transport resource can be requested by a ServiceRequest or by a Task, as shown in the diagram below. Also, this resource is only for the documentation of the physical movement of material items (people, animals, things). To operationalize the movement of people and things, Task should be used. Provenance can be used to document the steps but that is for the resource aspect, not the actual movement history of the item.

During the movement of a patient, the business status (change in the level of care/patient class) might change. To allow for the capture of the current business status of the patient, the reason element should be used. 
</p>
<img src="transport-resource-event.png" alt="Diagram showing Transport resource event flow"/>

</div>

</div>
