<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

    <blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
    <p><b>Note to Balloters:</b> To ensure this resource is ready for Normative status, we are seeking ballot comment on the substantive content. The key changes made since R5 include:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>Removed the instantiates workflow elements NutritionOrder.instantiatesCanonical, NutritionOrder.instantiatesUri and NutritionOrder.instantiates; and advise implementers to use the <a href="workflow-extensions.html">workflow instantiates extensions</a></li>
        <li>Renamed NutritionOrder.orderer to NutritionOrder.requester to align with the workflow pattern</li>
        <li>Renamed NutritionOrder.oralDiet.texture.foodType to NutritionOrder.oralDiet.texture.type</li>
        <li>Removed NutritionOrder.oralDiet.fluidConsistencyType</li>
        <li>Added NutritionOrder.oralDiet.caloricDensity and NutritionOrder.supplement.caloricDensity</li>
        <li>Updated NutritionOrder.enteralFormula backbone</li>
        <li>Pulled NutritionOrder.additive into its own backbone (previously part of NutritionOrder.enteralFormula)</li>
    </ul>
    </blockquote>


<blockquote class="stu-note">
<p><b>Note to Implementers:</b> For an overview of this resource and others in the Nutrition domain, also see the <a href="nutrition-module.html">module page</a>.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>
The NutritionOrder resource describes a request for oral diets (including general diets such as General Healthy diet, or therapeutic diets such as Consistent Carbohydrate, 2-gram Sodium, or Fluid Restricted), oral nutrition supplements (such as nutritionally complete pre-packed drinks), enteral nutrition (tube feedings) and infant formula which govern the distribution of food and nutritional products used to feed patients within a patient setting. It does not cover orders for parenteral (IV) nutrition which are typically filled by pharmacy. These nutrition orders are combined with information on a patient's food allergies and intolerances, and ethnic or cultural food preferences (e.g. Kosher or Vegetarian) to inform healthcare personnel about the type, texture, and/or quantity of foods that the patient should receive or consume.
</p>
<p>
Enteral orders are distinguished from supplements because they have some unique attributes and typically include administration information whereas oral nutritional supplements may simply be supplied (e.g. home health or outpatient settings).  In a simple case, the requestor may designate the type of product, product name, and the route of administration along with free text instructions without having to complete the additional structured details.
</p>
<p>
This resource is intended to be used by practitioners from a variety of specialties such as physicians, dietitians/nutritionists, or speech therapists.  One practitioner may simply order a base element oral diet such as General Healthful diet.   Another practitioner, based on the scope of practice, may use other elements to communicate additional therapeutic needs or patient preferences. The optionality included gives an ordering practitioner the capability to write a simple order for an oral diet, nutritional supplement or formula with minimal requirements beyond that of specifying the diet, supplement or formula product, but also supports  the ability to provide more detailed information that may be further augmented by a dietitian or nutrition specialist. For example, a physician may order a 2 g sodium diet.  A speech therapist, based on the results of a swallowing evaluation, then orders an International Dysphagia Diet Standardisation Initiative Framework - Soft and Bite-Sized Level 6 food (regime/therapy).
</p>
</div>


<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
    The NutritionOrder resource is used for requesting oral diets, oral nutrition supplements, enteral feedings, and infant formula. The <a href="medicationrequest.html">MedicationRequest</a> resource should be used for requesting parenteral (IV) nutrition and prescribing dietary supplements such as vitamin or mineral supplements.</p>
<p>
The Nutrition Order is a record of the request for the supply of a diet, oral supplement, enteral formulas, and infant formula for a patient. However, to initiate the request requires the use of the <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource and its associated workflow with the Nutrition Order referenced from Task.basedOn, or by using the nutrition Task resource in the context of a messaging or service workflow where the request is explicit or implicit.  For further information about this separation of responsibilities, refer to the <a href="request.html#fulfillment">Fulfillment/Execution section</a> of the Request pattern.
</p>
</div>



<!--div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
</p>
</div-->


</div>
