<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is a <em>definition</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective</strong> - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>, specifically <a href="workflow.html#definition">Definition</a>.</p>

<p>The scope of the EvidenceVariable Resource is to describe an element that knowledge (evidence) is about. The EvidenceVariable Resources are expected to be used with <a href="evidence.html">Evidence</a> Resources to facilitate searching and knowledge representation.</p>

<p>Evidence may be reported for different types of knowledge.  One commonly used format for expression of what evidence is about is the "PICO" format. PICO stands for:</p>

<p>Population - the population within which exposures and outcomes are being considered</p>
<p>Intervention - the conditional state or exposure state being described for which one is expressing the risk of or effect on an outcome</p>
<p>Comparison - the alternative conditional state or alternative exposure state when one is comparing states for the effect on an outcome</p>
<p>Outcome - the result or effect of an intervention or exposure in a population</p>
<p>PICO (and its variants like PECO or PICOT) is a universal acronym used in evidence-based medicine communities to clearly express research questions and evidence findings.</p>

<p>The EvidenceVariable Resource allows expression of the components of a PICO question in codeable and reusable formats.  As an exception, the Population specification will NOT use the EvidenceVariable Resource. The Population specification will use the <a href="group.html">Group</a> Resource to facilitate interoperability in matching <a href="evidence.html">Evidence</a> Resources to actual groups.</p>
<p><strong>Ballot question:</strong> The EvidenceVariable Resource has been modified to support expressions of complex eligibility criteria for implementer communities seeking alternatives to Group Resource for eligibility criteria for clinical trials. With these changes, the current EvidenceVariable Resource has greater flexibility than the Group Resource for Population specification. Please submit a ballot comment to note if you support a proposed change to the EvidenceVariable Scope and Usage to delete "As an exception, the Population specification will NOT use the EvidenceVariable Resource" and "The Population specification will use the Group Resource to facilitate interoperability in matching Evidence Resources to actual groups."</p>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>The Resource describing evidence findings (<a href="evidence.html">Evidence</a>) will reference EvidenceVariable to describe what the evidence findings are about.</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
This resource may describe the intervention or exposure for which an evidence summary is applicable, or may describe the outcome or measured variable that an evidence summary is about.

These descriptions could be used in coded specifications of recommendations from clinical practice guidelines to facilitate the translation from guidelines to clinical decision support artifacts.

These descriptions could be used in Summary of Findings tables from systematic reviews to facilitate the representation of medical knowledge when creating recommendations.

These descriptions could be used in classification of new evidence reports to facilitate recognition of signal for updating existing evidence summaries and recommendations.
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
