<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is a <em>definition</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective</strong> - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>, specifically <a href="workflow.html#definition">Definition</a>.</p>

<p>The scope of the EvidenceVariable resource is to describe a "PICO" element that knowledge (evidence, assertion, recommendation) is about. PICO stands for:

Population - the population within which exposures and outcomes are being considered
Intervention - the conditional state or exposure state being described for which one is expressing the risk of or effect on an outcome
Comparison - the alternative conditional state or alternative exposure state when one is comparing states for the effect on an outcome
Outcome - the result or effect of an intervention or exposure in a population
PICO (and its variants like PECO or PICOT) is a universal acronym used in evidence-based medicine communities to clearly express research questions and evidence findings.

The EvidenceVariable resource allows expression of the components of a PICO question in codeable and reusable formats.</p>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>Multiple resources describing evidence findings (Evidence, EffectEvidenceSynthesis, EffectEvidenceBit, RiskEvidenceSynthesis, RiskEvidenceBit) will reference EvidenceVariable to describe what the evidence findings are about.</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
This resource may describe the population for which a recommendation or evidence summary is applicable, or may describe the intervention or exposure for which a recommendation or evidence summary is applicable, or may describe the outcome that an evidence summary is about

These descriptions could be used in coded specifications of recommendations from clinical practice guidelines to facilitate the translation from guidelines to clinical decision support artifacts.

These descriptions could be used in Summary of Findings tables from systematic reviews to facilitate the representation of medical knowledge when creating recommendations.

These descriptions could be used in classification of new evidence reports to facilitate recognition of signal for updating existing evidence summaries and recommendations.
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
