<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The StructureDefinition resource describes a structure - a set of data element definitions, and their associated rules of usage.
These structure definitions are used to describe both the content defined in the FHIR specification 
itself - Resources, data types, the underlying infrastructural types, and also are used to describe how 
these structures are used in implementations.
This allows the definitions of the structures to be shared and published through 
repositories of structure definitions, compared with each other, and used as the basis
for code, report and UI generation. 
</p>
<p>
Note that  as part of the specification itself, a <a href="downloads.html#profiles">full 
set of structure definitions</a> for all resources and data types is published.
</p>
</div> 

<div> 
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2> 
<ul>
 <li>StructureDefinitions are used by <a href="conformance.html">Conformance</a> instances for specifying how resources are used</li>
 <li>StructureDefinitions use <a href="valueset.html">Value Sets</a> to specify the content of coded elements</li>
 <li>StructureDefinitions define concrete elements and structures for use with FHIR alone and that have defined wire representations (XML, JSON, etc.).
 This is distinct from <a href="datadelement.html">DataElement</a> which defines abstract elements that might appear anywhere - FHIR,
 questionnaire questions, CDA, v2, X12, OpenEHR, a proprietary database, etc.  DataElements may map to FHIR resources, data types and/or extensions
 but do not have any defined wire format of their own.</li>
</ul>

</div> 

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Implementers should be familiar with with the 
background and concepts described in <a href="profiling.html">Profiling FHIR</a> 
before working with this resource.
</p>

<h3>Metadata</h3>
<p>
The StructureDefinition resource has a set of metadata that is mostly shared with the <a href="valueset.html">Value Set</a>,
<a href="conformance.html">Conformance</a> and other infrastructure resources. The metadata describes the structure, and helps 
find the structure when registered in profile repositories. 
</p>

<table class="grid">
 <tr><td>url</td><td>The identifier that is used to identify this structure when it is referenced in a specification, model, design or an instance. This URL is where the structure can be accessed</td></tr>
 <tr><td>identifier</td><td>Other identifiers that are used to identify this structure</td></tr>
 <tr><td>version</td><td>
   <p>The identifier that is used to identify this version of the structure when it is referenced in a specification, model, design or instance. This is an arbitrary value managed by the structure author manually and the value should be a timestamp.</p>
   <p>Note that there may be multiple resource versions of the structure that have this same identifier. The resource will have updates that create new versions for technical reasons, whereas the stated version number needs to be under the author's control</p>
   </td></tr>
 <tr><td>name</td><td>A free text natural language name identifying the structure	</td></tr>
 <tr><td>publisher</td><td>Details of the individual or organization who accepts responsibility for publishing the structure. This helps establish the "authority/credibility" of the structure.</td></tr>
 <tr><td>telecom</td><td>Contact details to assist a user in finding and communicating with the publisher</td></tr>	
 <tr><td>description</td><td>A free text natural language description of the structure and its use</td></tr>	
 <tr><td>requirements</td><td>The Scope and Usage that this structure was created to meet</td></tr>	
 <tr><td>code</td><td>A set of terms from external terminologies that may be used to assist with indexing and searching of profiles</td></tr>
 <tr><td>status</td><td>The status of the structure	allows filtering of profiles that are appropriate for use vs. not. See the <a href="structure-definition-status.html">Status Codes</a></td></tr>
 <tr><td>experimental</td><td>This structure was authored for testing purposes (or education/evaluation/marketing), and is not intended to be used for genuine usage</td></tr>
 <tr><td>date</td><td>The date that this version of the structure was published	</td></tr>
 <tr><td>fhirVersion</td><td>The version of the FHIR specification on which this structure is based. It is not necessary to specify the version, as most profiles are valid across multiple versions, and the validity of a structure against a particular version of FHIR can easily be checked by tooling.	</td></tr>
 <tr><td>type</td><td>todo</td></tr>
 <tr><td>contextType</td><td>todo</td></tr>
 <tr><td>context</td><td>todo</td></tr>
</table>

<p>Notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>The name of the structure is not required to be globally unique, but the name should have some scoping information (i.e. Acme Inc. (USA), Allergy List)</li>
<li>Multiple codes may be assigned to the structure. These may either describe the structure, the focus of the structure or both. They are solely to help find the structure by searching for structured concepts</li>
<li>The 3 status codes (draft, active, and retired) are the codes that are relevant to structure consumers. Authors may wish to use the <a href="#author-status">authoring-status</a> extension to track the life cycle of a structure as it is prepared</li>
</ul>  

</div>


</div>
