<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<!--<p>
Notes:
</p>
<h2>Section Title</h2>-->
	  <h2>Realm specifics</h2>
	  <h3>US Realm sample Use-Cases</h3>
	  <p>
		Five categories of Privacy Consent Directives are described in the Office of the National Coordinator for 
		Health Information (ONC) Consent Directives Document released March 31, 2010, and include the following 
		US-specific “Core consent options” for electronic exchange:
	  </p>
	  <ol>
	  <li>No consent: Health information of patients is automatically included—patients cannot opt out;</li>
	  <li>Opt-out: Default is for health information of patients to be included automatically, but the patient can opt out completely;</li>
	  <li>Opt-out with exceptions: Default is for health information of patients to be included, but the patient can opt out completely or allow only select data to be included;</li>
	  <li>Opt-in: Default is that no patient health information is included; patients must actively express consent to be included, but if they do so then their information must be all in or all out; and</li>
	  <li>Opt-in with restrictions: Default is that no patient health information is made available, but the patient may allow a subset of select data to be included.</li>
	  </ol>
	  <h3>Canada Realm sample Use-Cases</h3>
	  <p>
	  The following scenarios are based on existing jurisdictional policy and are realized in existing systems in 
	  Canada. The default policy is one of implied consent for the provision of care, so these scenarios all deal 
	  with withdrawal or withholding consent for that purpose. In other jurisdictions, where an express consent 
	  model is used (Opt-In), these would examples would contain the phrase "consent to" rather than "withhold" 
	  or "withdraw" consent for.
	  </p>
	  <ol>
	    <li>Withhold or withdraw consent for disclosure of records related to specific domain (e.g. DI, LAB, etc.)</li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw consent for disclosure of a specific record (e.g. Lab Order/Result) </li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw consent for disclosure to a specific provider organization </li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw consent for disclosure to a specific provider agent (an individual within an organization) </li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw consent for disclosure of records that were authored by a specific organization (or service delivery location). </li>
		<li>Combinations of the above </li>
	  </ol>

</div>
