<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
      <a name="PCD"> Privacy Consent Directive (PCD) </a>
 	  <p>
	  The purpose of this Resource is to be used to express a Privacy Consent Directive.
	  </p><p>
		Privacy policies define how Individually Identifiable Health Information (IIHI) is to be collected, accessed, 
		used and disclosed.  A Privacy Consent Directive is a record of a client’s (e.g., patient, consumer) 
		health information privacy policy.  A Privacy Consent Directive grants or withholds authorization to collect, 
		access, use, or disclose IIHI about the client. A client may author/publish their privacy preferences as a 
		self-declared Privacy Consent Directive.  Effective Privacy Consent Directives are a bilateral agreement between 
		the client and an individual/organization that is in accord with law, regulation and organizational policies with 
		regard to their content. In addition, Privacy Consent Directives provide the ability for a healthcare client 
		to delegate authority to a Substitute Decision Maker who may act on behalf of that individual.
	  </p><p>
		The Privacy Consent Directive on FHIR provides support for alternative representations for expressing 
		health information privacy consent directives in a standard form for the exchange of privacy policies 
		that can be enforced by consuming systems (e.g., scanned documents, computable structured entries).
	  </p><p>
		The Resource also supports backward compatibility by enabling references to CDA Consent Directives 
		following the 
		<a href="http://gforge.hl7.org/gf/project/cbcc/frs/?action=FrsReleaseView&amp;release_id=732">HL7 CDAR2 ConsentDirective Implementation Guide</a> 
		which incorporated the 
		<a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php?title=Basic_Patient_Privacy_Consents">IHE Basic Patient Privacy Consents (BPPC)</a> 
		mechanism of acknowledging a Privacy Policy identifier and expanded upon it with privacy policy 
		attributes captured in the CDA document according to the CDA-CD-IG specification.  This guide allows for the 
		capture of a scanned document in the structuredBody of a CDA document to support manual interpretation of the 
		meaning of the privacy consent directive as well as to support the capture of a client’s wet signature.
	  </p><p>
		This guide supports sending a computable representation of privacy consent directives using structured 
		entries based on a mapping of the 
		<a href="http://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public/standards/dstu/V3DAM_MR_CPCD_DSTU_R2_2010APR.pdf">HL7 Version 3 Domain Analysis Model: Medical Records; Composite Privacy Consent Directive, Draft Standard for Trial Use (DSTU) Release 2 (CPCD DAM)</a> 
		to HL7 FHIR Contract attributes, or by using standard access control markup languages (XACML, XrML and others).  
		It is expected that other SDOs will use the Privacy domain analysis model to create profiles (e.g., OASIS 
		Cross-Enterprise Security and Privacy Authorization (XSPA) Technical Committee) and that for encoding 
		capabilities, formal policy languages will be used.
	  </p><p>
	    The Consent resource is structured with a base policy, followed by a listing of exceptions to that policy. This works for both Positive (Opt-IN)
		and Negative (Opt-Out) consents or authorizations. 
		</p>
      <h3>Scope</h3>
      <p>The scope of this Resource is a Privacy Consent Directive in a structured and coded way so 
	  so that the rules can be enforced.
      </p><p>
	  The enforcement of the Privacy Consent Directive is not included, but is expected that 
	  enforcement can be done using various Access Control enforcement methodologies (e.g. XACML).
	  </p>
 

</div>

</div>
