<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Policies</h2>

<p>
This speciifcation defines 2 magic values for consent policies:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr>
  <td><b>URI</b></td>
  <td><b>Description</b></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>http://hl7.org/fhir/ConsentPolicy/opt-in</td>
  <td>The basic policy is to grant no authority. No actions are approved, unless they are explicitly detailed in the exceptions</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>http://hl7.org/fhir/ConsentPolicy/opt-out</td>
  <td>The basic policy is to grant all authority. All actions are approved, unless they are explicitly detailed in the exceptions</td>
 </tr>
</table>
<p>
Other jurisdictions (e.g. HL7 Affiliates) may define their additional lists of consent policy URI values that represent consent policies established by law or regulation
</p>
<p>
The Consent resource has a reference to a single <code>policy</code>. Many organizations will work in a context where multiple different consent regulations and policies apply. 
In these cases, the single policy reference refers to a policy document that resolves and reconciles the various policies, and presents a single policy for patient
consent. If it is still necessary to track which of the underlying policies an exception is make in regard to, an <a href="extension-consent-basis.html">extension</a> may be used.
</p>
<h2>General Model</h2>
<p>
The following is the general model of Privacy Consent Directives.
</p>
<p>
There are context setting parameters:
</p>
<ol>
<li>Who - The <td><b>patient</b></td></li>
<li>What - The <td><b>data</b></td> - specific resources are listed, empty list means all data covered by the consent.</li>
<li>Where - The <td><b>domain</b></td> and <td><b>authority</b></td> - what is the location boundary and authority boundary of this consent</li>
<li>When - The <td><b>issued</b></td> or captured</li>
<li>When - The timeframe for which the Consent <td><b>applies</b></td> </li>
<li>How - The <td><b>actions</b></td> covered. (such as purposes of use that are covered)</li>
<li>Whom - The <td><b>recipient</b></td> are grantees by the consent. </li>
</ol>
<p>
A Privacy Consent may transition through many states including: that no consent has been sought, consent has been proposed, 
consent has been rejected, and consent approved.
</p>
<p>There are set of patterns.</p>
	  <ol>
	  <li>No consent: All settings need a policy for when no consent has been captured. Often this allows treatment only.;</li>
	  <li>Opt-out: <a href="consent-example-Out.html">No sharing allowed for the specified domain, location, actions, and purposes</a>;</li>
	  <li>Opt-out with exceptions: No sharing allowed, with some exceptions where it is allowed. Example: <a href="consent-example-Emergency.html">Withhold Authorization for Treatment except for Emergency Treatment</a>;</li>
	  <li>Opt-in: Sharing for some purpose of use is authorized <a href="consent-example.html">Sharing allowed for Treatment, Payment, and normal Operations</a>; and</li>
	  <li>Opt-in with restrictions: Sharing allowed, but the patient may make exceptions (See the Canadian examples).</li>
	  </ol>
      <p>For each of these patterns (positive or negative pattern), there can be exceptions. 
	  These exceptions are explicitly recorded in the <td><b>except</b></td> element. 
      </p>	
<h2>Realm specifics</h2>
 <h3>US Realm sample Use-Cases</h3>
	  <p>
		Five categories of Privacy Consent Directives are described in the Office of the National Coordinator for 
		Health Information (ONC) Consent Directives Document released March 31, 2010, and include the following 
		US-specific “Core consent options” for electronic exchange:
	  </p>
	  <ol>
	  <li>No consent: Health information of patients is automatically included—patients cannot opt out;</li>
	  <li>Opt-out: Default is for health information of patients to be included automatically, but the patient can <a href="consent-example-Out.html">opt out completely</a>;</li>
	  <li>Opt-out with exceptions: Default is for health information of patients to be included, but the patient can opt out completely or allow only select data to be included;</li>
	  <li>Opt-in: Default is that no patient health information is included; patients must actively <a href="consent-example.html">express consent</a> to be included, but if they do so then their information must be all in or all out; and</li>
	  <li>Opt-in with restrictions: Default is that no patient health information is made available, but the patient may allow a subset of select data to be included.</li>
	  </ol>
	  <p>
	  A common exception is to explicitly exclude or explicitly include <a href="consent-example-notTIme.html">a period of time</a>.
	  </p>
 <h3>Canada Realm sample Use-Cases</h3>
	  <p>
	  The following scenarios are based on existing jurisdictional policy and are realized in existing systems in 
	  Canada. The default policy is one of implied consent for the provision of care, so these scenarios all deal 
	  with withdrawal or withholding consent for that purpose. In other jurisdictions, where an express consent 
	  model is used (Opt-In), these examples would contain the phrase "consent to" rather than "withhold" 
	  or "withdraw" consent for.
	  </p>
	  <ol>
	    <li>Withhold or withdraw consent for disclosure of records related to specific domain (e.g. DI, LAB, etc.)</li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw <a href="consent-example-notThis.html">consent for disclosure of a specific record</a> (e.g. Lab Order/Result) </li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw <a href="consent-example-notOrg.html">consent for disclosure to a specific provider organization</a> </li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw <a href="consent-example-notThem.html">consent for disclosure to a specific provider agent</a> (an individual within an organization) </li>
		<li>Withhold or withdraw <a href="consent-example-notAutor.html">consent for disclosure of records that were authored by a specific organization</a> (or service delivery location). </li>
		<li>Combinations of the above </li>
	  </ol>
 <h3>Non Treatment Use-Cases</h3>
	  <p>
	  Also shown is an example where a <a href="consent-example-grantor.html">Patient has authorized disclosure to a specific individual for purposes directed by the patient</a> (possibly not a treatment case).
	  </p>

</div>
