<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<p><b>Definitions:</b></p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr><td>Consent</td><td>The record of a healthcare consumer’s policy choices, which permits or denies identified recipient(s) or recipient role(s) to perform one or more actions within a given policy context, for specific purposes and periods of time</td></tr>
 <tr><td>Consent Directive</td><td>The legal record of a healthcare consumer's agreement with a party responsible for enforcing the consumer’s choices, which permits or denies identified actors or roles to perform actions affecting the consumer within a given context for specific purposes and periods of time</td></tr>
 <tr><td>Policy context</td><td>Any organizational or jurisdictional policies, which may limit the consumer’s policy choices, and which includes the named range of actions allowed</td></tr>
 <tr><td>Healthcare Consumer</td><td>The individual establishing his/her personal consent (i.e. Consenter). In FHIR, this is referred to as the 'Patient' though this word is not used across all contexts of care</td></tr>
</table>
<p>
The purpose of this Resource is to be used to express a Consent regarding Healthcare. There are 3 possible
uses for consent:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Privacy Consent: consent to share information</li>
 <li>Treatment Consent: consent to undergo a specific treatment (or record of refusal to consent)</li>
 <li>Research Consent:  privacy and medical consent to participate in clinical trial, translational medicine, or to permit collection, use, or disclosure of health information and specimen to registries or directly to research projects for use in e.g., biomedical research and population origins or ancestry research</li>
 <li>Advance Care Directives (e.g. DNR)</li>
</ul>
<p>
This resource is scoped to cover all 3 uses, but at this time, only the privacy use case
is investigated, and the scope of the resource may change when the other possible scopes are 
investigated and tested. 
</p>

<h3><a name="PCD"> Privacy Consent Directive (PCD)</a></h3>

<p>
Privacy policies define how Individually Identifiable Health Information 
(IIHI) is to be collected, accessed, used and disclosed. A Privacy Consent 
Directive as a legal record of a patient's (e.g. a healthcare consumer) 
agreement with a party responsible for enforcing the patient's choices, 
which permits or denies identified actors or roles to perform actions 
affecting the patient within a given context for specific purposes and 
periods of time. All consent directives have a policy context, which is
any set of organizational or jurisdictional policies which may limit the 
consumer’s policy choices, and which include a named range of actions allowed.
In addition, Privacy Consent Directives provide the ability for a healthcare client 
to delegate authority to a Substitute Decision Maker who may act on behalf of that individual.
Alternatively, a client may author/publish their privacy preferences as a self-declared Privacy Consent Directive.  
</p>
<p>
The Consent resource on FHIR provides support for alternative representations for expressing 
health information privacy consent directives in a standard form for the exchange of privacy policies 
that can be enforced by consuming systems (e.g., scanned documents, computable structured entries).
It may be used to represent the Privacy Consent Directive itself, or a derived consent statement 
that is not the original Consent Directive.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"> </a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

<p>
Consent management - particularly privacy consent - is complicated by the fact that consent to share 
is often itself necessary to protect. The need to protect the privacy of the privacy statement itself
competes with the execution of the consent statement. For this reason, it is common to deal with 
'consent statements' that are only partial representations of the full consent statement that the 
patient provided. 
</p>
<p>
For this reason, the consent resource contains two elements that refer back to the source: a master
identifier, and a direct reference to content from which this Consent Statement was derived. That
reference can be one of several things:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A reference to another consent resource from which this limited statement was derived</li>
 <li>A reference to a document format for the original source (e.g. PDF or CDA - see the 
 <a href="http://gforge.hl7.org/gf/project/cbcc/frs/?action=FrsReleaseView&amp;release_id=732">HL7 CDAR2 ConsentDirective Implementation Guide</a>, 
 which incorporated the <a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php?title=Basic_Patient_Privacy_Consents">IHE Basic Patient Privacy Consents (BPPC)</a> ), either directly, or in a reference</li>
 <li>The source can be included in the consent as an attachment</li>
</ul>
<p>
The consent statements represent a chain that refers back to the original source consent
agreement. Applications may be able to follow the chain back to the source, but should
not generally assume that they are authoriszd to do this.
</p>
<p>
Consent statements are often signed - either on paper, or digitally. Consent Signatures will
be found in the <a href="provenance.html">Provenance</a> resource (example <a href="consent-example-signature.html">consent</a> and 
<a href="provenance-consent-signature.html">signature</a>). Implementation Guides will generally 
make rules about what signatures are required, and how they are to be shared and used.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
The Consent resource is structured with a base policy which is either opt-in or opt-out, 
followed by a listing of exceptions to that policy.  The exceptions can be additional positive 
or negative exceptions upon the base policy. The set of exceptions include a list of data objects, 
list of authors, list of recipients, list of Organizations, list of purposeOfUse, and Date Range.
</p>
<p>
The enforcement of the Privacy Consent Directive is not included, but is expected that 
enforcement can be done using a mix of the various Access Control enforcement methodologies (e.g. OAuth, UMA, XACML).
This enforcement includes the details of the enforcement meaning of the elements of the Privacy Consent Directive, 
such as the rules in place when there is an opt-in consent would be specific about which 
organizational roles have access to what kinds of resources (e.g. RBAC, ABAC). 
The specification of these details are not in scope for the Consent resource.
</p>

</div>

</div>
