<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
			Slot resources are used to provide time-slots that can be booked using an appointment.
			They do not provide any information about appointments that are available, just the time,
			and optionally what the time can be used for. These are effectively spaces of free/busy time.<br/>
      Slots can also be marked as busy without having appointments associated.
    </p>
		<p>
			A slot can have more than one appointment allocated to it. A scheduling system may permit
			multiple allocations up to a specific number of places. An example of this type of usage 
      could be where the slot is being used for a group service that permits 5 participants at 
      the same time.
		</p>
		<p>
			A slot can be marked as over-booked indicating that there are too many appointments allocated
			to it.
		</p>
		<p>
			In some situations a service may have a specific set of slots reserved for specific uses, such 
			as "walk-ins" or a specific Organisation has a "standing booking" for Thursday mornings.
			These should be represented using the type field with a specified and agreed value.<br/>
			Security Permissions or specific business rules on the system could enforce that only eligible
			appointments are allocated to them.
		</p>
    <p>
      If a service had a weekly schedule created that permitted eight 1 hour appointments each
      day of a working week (Monday - Friday), this would be constructed by a single Schedule
      resource with the dates for the start and end of the week set, and then 40 (5x8) Slot 
      resources associated with it.<br/>
      As appointments fill up the schedule, these slots would individually be marked as busy
      as the appointments are filled into the slots.<br/>
      The slots in a schedule do not need to be the same size, and can be different for different
      days of the week.<br/>
      Slot instances do not have any recurrance information included. If recurring information is
      desired, this will be managed outside these resources, or included as extensions.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
