<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="registration"> </a>
<h3>Publishing Extension Definitions</h3>
<p>
As well as defining the base element structure for resources, HL7 also publishes extensions. HL7 publishes such data definitions
as extensions rather than as part of the base resource structure in order to keep the base
resource structure simple and concise, and to allow implementers not to engage with an entire world's
worth of functionality up front. Note that HL7 does not define "modifier" extensions - if
HL7 publishes an element that modifies the meaning of other elements, it will be part of the resource
content itself, since everyone has to understand the extension anyway.
</p>
<p>
Before extensions can be used in instances, their definition SHALL be published. 
HL7 maintains two extension registries:
</p>
<ol>
 <li>HL7 approved extensions, approved by an appropriate part of the HL7 community following a review process, and with have formal standing</li> 
 <li>Provided as a service to the community, where anyone can register an extension</li>
</ol>
<p>
Users are encouraged to register their extensions in the second registry, though this is not required. 
All that is required is that the extension is published in a context that is available for users 
of the extension. So, for example, if a particular
extension is used within a single institution, the definition of the extension
can be placed on the institution's intranet. However since, by their nature, resources
tend to travel well, it's always better to use the HL7 or other publicly accessible extension registries.
</p>
<p>
HL7 extension definition registries. 
</p>
<table class="codes">
 <tr><th>Registry</th><th>Search</th><th>Submit</th></tr>
 <tr><td>HL7 Approved</td><td>[TBD]</td><td>[TBD]</td></tr>
 <tr><td>Community</td><td>[TBD]</td><td>[TBD]</td></tr>
 <tr><td>Interim</td><td><a href="http://fhir-dev.healthintersections.com.au/open/StructureDefinition/_search">http://fhir-dev.healthintersections.com.au/open/StructureDefinition/_search</a></td>
 <td><a href="http://fhir.healthintersections.com.au/open/StructureDefinition/upload">http://fhir.healthintersections.com.au/open/StructureDefinition/upload</a></td></tr>
</table>
<p>
HL7 extension definitions may be balloted alongside resource content as part of the FHIR specification or may
be published as part of separate specifications.
When HL7 publishes extension definitions as part of the FHIR specification, these extensions SHALL
be used for this data whenever the data is represented in instances. Applications SHOULD use other
HL7-defined extensions published to represent equivalent data in the interest of maximum interoperability.
</p>
<p>
To minimize complexity for implementers, HL7 will not elevate content defined in an HL7-approved extension to
be content defined in a core resource in future versions of the resource once that resource is normative.
</p>
<p>
In some cases, an HL7 work group or other body may publish a profile whose sole
purpose is to define extensions expected to be needed by implementers in a particular context.  E.g. extensions needed
to map a particular set of v2 segments or a v3 model.
</p>
<p>
Implementations are encouraged to share their extensions with HL7 and register them with the HL7 extension registry. The domain committees will work
to elevate the extensions into HL7 published extensions or, if adopted by a broad enough portion of the implementer community, the into the base resource structure itself.
</p>
<!-- Todo: point to actual registry once it's up and running -->
<p>To avoid interoperability issues, extensions SHALL NOT change their definition once published.  (Small clarifications to descriptions
that do not affect interoperability are permitted.)  Rather than modifying an existing extension, a new extension should be introduced.
Revisions to an extension may extend the set of contexts in which the extension apply but may not remove or constrain any context previously listed</p>
<!-- Todo: Figure out how to manage "deprecating" extensions and pointing at their new versions -->


</div>
