<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The Extension Definition resource provides a forml definition of an extension used 
in a FHIR resource, that can used as the basis for validation, and code, report and UI generation. 
</p>
</div> 

<div> 
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2> 
<ul>
 <li>Every extension in a resource refers directly to it's definition</li>
 <li>ExtensionDefinitions are used by <a href="profile.html">Profile</a> instances when specifying that extensions are used in a resource</li>
</ul>

<p>
Whenever resources containing extensions are exchanged, the definitions of the extensions SHALL be available to all the parties that share the resources.
Each extension contains a URI that references the source of the definitions as a Resource Profile. The source SHOULD be a literal reference, such as an
http: url that refers to an end-point that responds with the contents of the definitions - preferably a <a href="http.html">FHIR RESTful server</a>
supporting the Resources Profile, or a logical reference (e.g. using a urn:) - for instance, to a national published
standard.
</p>
</div> 

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Extensions may be defined by any project or jurisdiction, up to and including international standards organizations such as HL7 itself. 
Extensions are always defined against some particular context - the type of element 
that they may be used to extend. The following are possible contexts for an extension:
</p>
<table class="codes">
 <tr><th>Context type</th><th>Context format</th><th>Examples</th></tr>
 <tr><td>A particular element (including the root) in a single resource</td><td>The element path for that element<br/>Note: If the context is an element that can have multiple types, then use (e.g.) value[x] if the extension works on all choice types, or otherwise an enumeration of explicitly named elements if not</td><td>Profile.resource.element; Person</td></tr>
 <tr><td>A particular element (including the root) in a particular data type</td><td>The data type name for primitive types or the element path for complex data types</td><td>Address.part.value; string</td></tr>
 <tr><td>A particular context in one of the mapped reference models</td><td>The name of the reference model followed by the mapping path</td><td>RIM: Act[moodCode="EVN"]</td></tr>
 <tr><td>Another extension</td><td>The profile uri of the extension followed by the extension code</td><td>http://myextensions.org#someExtension</td></tr>
 <tr><td>A set of some combination of the above</td><td>As above, separated by ';'</td><td>Address; Contact</td></tr>
</table>
<p>
In addition, an extension definition might apply additional constraints with
regards to particular element values of the target that make its use appropriate.
Extensions SHALL only be used on a target for which they are defined.
</p>


</div>


</div>
