<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul>
 <li>The resources referenced by the enterer, author and responsible elements may 
  all be included in the bundle or left out on the basis that the recipient (and any intermediaries) are able to locate/resolve the resources
  independently. The former would be suitable for loosely coupled systems, and the latter for tightly coupled systems. The messaging conformance 
  statement for an application may reference <a href="profile.html">a profile</a> that describes how the bundling occurs</li>
 <li>The actual content of the data resource is specified for each message event. The data resource is always included in the bundle</li>
 <li>If <i>Message.source.endpoint</i> and <i>Message.destination.endpoint</i>, are literal URLs, then they SHOULD identify
  the addresses to which messages can be be delivered. If they are logicail URIs (i.e. non-dereferenceable), 
  message delivery intermediaries must know how to deliver the message to the destination application. </li>
 <li>The author and the receiver are not the actual technical systems</li>
 <li>A receiver is not obligated to reject messages which do not explicitly identify it as receiver (e.g. a tracker will get messages that are destined for some other system)</li>
</ul>  



<a name="Events"></a>
<a name="events"></a>
<h2>Event List</h2>

<p>
The <i>message.code</i> element carries a <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a> that identifies the event that the message conveys. 
This table lists the message event codes defined in this specification (the system value for these is "http://hl7.org/fhir/message-type"):
</p>

[%events%]

<p>
In this table, the request and response columns list the focus resource for the event, along with other resources that should also be carried in the message directly (if they exist).
Additional events may be defined elsewhere, though this specification does not yet define how. DSTU: Input on this is sought during the trial use period.
</p>

<a name="mailbox"></a>
<h2>Mailbox</h2>
<p>
The mailbox is the standard name for a service hosted on a RESTful server that accepts messages and processes 
them as transactions and returns a message response appropriate for the message received. The server is under
no obligation to do anything particular with the resources except as required by the semantics of the event code in the 
message resource. A server may choose to retain the resources and make them available on a RESTful interface, but 
is not required to do so. If the server returns 200 Ok, it SHALL return a valid message that indicates what the outcome
of the event processing is. An HTTP error indicates that the message was not processed successfully and that it should
be resubmitted (and doing so should not result in a duplicate message response).  Repeated failures indicate either a
fatal problem with the message or a problem with the receiving application.
</p>
<p>
The mailbox can also be used to accept documents. In this case, the document is "accepted" (the server 
takes responsibility for custody of the received document) and an HTTP status of 204 No Content is returned, 
or an HTTP error is returned. The server is under no obligation to do anything with the document except as 
specific trading partner agreements dictate.
</p>
<p>
The following rules apply to the mailbox:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>The mailbox only accepts POST transactions - any other HTTP method will result in an HTTP error</li>
 <li>The request content type submitted is always <a href="extras.html#bundle">a bundle</a> containing a message or document resource as the first resource</li>
 <li>The response content type returned is always an HTTP error, <a href="extras.html#bundle">a bundle</a> containing a message as the first resource, or empty (if a document was received)</li>
 <li>If the response is an error, the body SHOULD be an <a href="operationoutcome.html">Errors &amp; Warning</a> resource with full details</li> 
 <li>The URL never takes any parameters</li>
 <li>The mailbox may be authenticated using standard HTTP authentication methods, including OAuth</li>
</ul>
<p>
This simple mailbox profile can be used by any HTTP end point that accepts FHIR messages or documents, not just 
FHIR RESTful servers.
</p>
<p>
In order to ensure consistency of processing, the <a href="#reliable">logical rules regarding processing of envelope id and 
message id described above</a> SHALL be followed when messages are processed using the mailbox. No such rules apply regarding
documents - if the client receives no response, it should continue to submit the document until it does. Servers SHALL 
accept multiple document submissions and process them correctly.
</p>

</div>
