<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
  The Person resource serves as a linkage resource that may provide a reference set of common demographics 
  for an individual (human or animal) across multiple roles.<br/>
  This linkage can be direct to role-specific FHIR resources (Patient, Practitioner and RelatedPerson)
  residing on the same or possibly distinct FHIR systems/applications, or indirectly through the use of
  business identifiers.
</p>
  <p>
  The Person resource may be used in many situations/contexts, including:
  </p>
  <ul>
  <li>A set of demographics that can be used to co-ordinate the maintenance of this
  de-normalized information across practitioners, patients and/or related persons<br/>
  <i>e.g. link known resources of the different types together within a system</i></li>

  <li>A state/network based Master Person Index<br/>
  <i>e.g. A National Identifier Index or a Network membership/subscriber list</i></li>

  <li>A central register that links patient resources from multiple servers, indicating they
  all correspond to the same individual<br/>
  <i>e.g. Within a large organization with many systems to be able to link the various records, 
  without having to modify the source information with external links</i></li>

  <li>A support for access monitoring software that is able to assert what practitioner, 
  patient and related person records correspond to the same human being to assist in 
  detecting improper querying.<br/>
  <i>e.g. asserting that a Patient A is the same individual as a RelatedPerson B who is
  related to Patient C, who is also Practitioner D.  As such, monitoring for Practitioner
  D’s accesses to Patient A’s records should be carefully scrutinized.</i></li>

  <li>Local record(s) on a mobile device listing links to remote server patient resources<br/>
  <i>e.g. A mobile phone application storing references to the hospitals they have access to</i></li>
  </ul>

  [%stu-note advanced%]
    The Person resource is an advanced feature.  Many systems don’t have a way
    to relate information across resource types, or systems, especially from Patient to
    Practitioner, and therefore might not implement this functionality. Some do have ways
    of relating the Patient and RelatedPerson resource types. FHIR is also able to do this
    without the Person resource, utilizing the Patient.link property
    <a href="patient.html#maternity">(as shown in the Mother and newborn relationship example)</a>
  [%end-note%]
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
  <p>
    Person resources may have references to Patient, RelatedPerson and/or Practitioner resources. 
    These linkages assert that all the records relate to the same individual.
  </p>
  <p>
    Person instances are NEVER directly referenced as actors (authors, subjects, performers, etc.)
    Individual actors are always identified as either Patient, Practitioner or RelatedPerson, depending on the role
    of the individual when undertaking the action. Therefore this resource SHALL NOT be referenced by any
    other clinical or administrative resources.<br/>
    E.g. it can be the focus of an operation or message or included in a Bundle, 
    but cannot be a member of a List or Group, the subject of an Observation, or other similar non-infrastructural usage.<br/>
    Note that the usage of Practitioner is broader in FHIR than the term may suggest, and can encompass individuals who 
    are not licensed healthcare practitioners.
  </p>
  <p>
    In some use cases the linkages will be indirect, and through business Identifiers, such as in the case of
    the various types of Master Person Indexes, where the records are not there for the purpose of healthcare, 
    but simply describing a population of people, and has other purposes and not just to represent a population patients.
  </p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->
</div>
