<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <h2>De-normalized Data</h2>
  <p>
    Most of the properties of the Person resource are replicated within the other resources that they
    are shared with. This is intentional and highlights that the "disconnectedness" of the resources.
  </p>
  <p>
    Not many systems actually implement a shared Person record, and as such the values DO become out of
    sync with each other. The inclusion of this resource does permit a capability for systems to identify
    other instances of this actual person's data via a centralized registry that can assist in keeping things
    up to date.
  </p>
  
  <h2>
    Person and Linking
  </h2>
  <p>
  The <i>link</i> element is used to relate resources under a common person record. 
  This element supports two primary scenarios where other resources refer to the same person resource.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <i>link</i> element cannot be used to link to RelatedPerson entries. So we can utilize a Person
    resource to relate these elements together identifying them as the same individual.
  </p>

  <h2>
  Cross-Domain Patient Directory
  </h2>
  <p>
    In a data sharing network, finding the location of patient records across different systems is a 
    necessary pre-requisite for accessing external patient data. Using the <i>link</i> element, systems associate
    patient resources from different organizations. The assuranceLevel associated with the <i>link</i> provides
    a way for a system to qualify its confidence in the asserted <i>link</i>. For example, a relationship from
    the person to a patient using a probabilistic matching algorithm may be represented using a <i>link</i> with
    an assurance level of level1, while a relationship established using a government-issued photo ID may
    be created with an assurance level of level3.
  </p>
  
  <h2>
    Cross-Domain Provider Directory
  </h2>
  <p>
    Similarly, providers working in multiple healthcare service settings may be linked across different 
    organizations using the <i>link</i> element. The various practitioner resources can be related using a common 
    person resource with a <i>link</i> for each of the practitioner resources located in other organizations.
  </p>

  <h2>
    Client Portal
  </h2>
  <p>
    Client Portals provide consumer access to a window of their data locked up in healthcare systems. 
    In many cases these sytems are externally integrated and do not have access to the legacy CIS/PAS systems.
  </p>
  <p>
    In contrast to most systems where a user has access to multiple patients depending on their roles and permissions,
    a client portal provides a consumer with direct access to their data (with permissions applied).
    This can also include not just their data (via the Person.link Patient entries), but also to information that they
    have entered, or were involved with (via the Person.link RelatedPerson entries), such as observations that they 
    entered.<br/>
    With appropriate permissions/consent applied, the user could have access to other Patient records linked via 
    a RelatedPerson.
  </p>
</div>
