<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="dedata"></a>
  <h2>De-normalized Data</h2>
  <p>
    Most of the properties of the Person resource are replicated within the other resources that they
    are shared with. This is intentional and highlights the loose coupling of the resources.
  </p>
  <p>
    Not many systems implement a shared Person record, and as such the values DO become out of
    sync with each other. The inclusion of this resource does permit a capability for systems to identify
    other instances of this actual person's data via a centralized registry that can assist in keeping things
    up to date.
  </p>
  
<a name="linking"></a>
  <h2>
    Person and Linking
  </h2>
  <p>
  The <i>person.link</i> element is used to relate resources under a common person record. 
  This element supports two primary scenarios where other resources refer to the same person resource.
  </p>
  <blockquote class="stu-note">
    <p>
      <b>Note:</b> In previous versions of the FHIR specification the <i>patient.link</i> element was not able link
      to RelatedPerson entries, leaving the Person resource to link them. Since STU3 the patient.link property
      was updated to also support RelatedPerson, reducing the need to link using the Person resource, however this
      can still be done.
    </p>
  </blockquote>

<a name="xdomain"></a>
  <h2>
  Cross-Domain Patient Directory
  </h2>
  <p>
    In a data sharing network, finding the location of patient records across different systems is a 
    necessary pre-requisite for accessing external patient data. Using the <i>link</i> element, systems associate
    patient resources from different organizations. The assuranceLevel associated with the <i>link</i> provides
    a way for a system to qualify its confidence in the asserted <i>link</i>. For example, a relationship from
    the person to a patient using a probabilistic matching algorithm may be represented using a <i>link</i> with
    an assurance level of level1, while a relationship established using a government-issued photo ID may
    be created with an assurance level of level3.
  </p>
  
<a name="xdomain2"></a>
  <h2>
    Cross-Domain Provider Directory
  </h2>
  <p>
    Similarly, providers working in multiple healthcare service settings may be linked across different 
    organizations using the <i>link</i> element. The various practitioner resources can be related using a common 
    person resource with a <i>link</i> for each of the practitioner resources located in other organizations.
  </p>

<a name="pmi"></a>
<h2>
  Person Master Index
</h2>
<p>
  Many national and state programs maintain a central register of people, and their key Identifiers.
  These systems do not store any health related information, they are purely a validated set data, often
  provided by government departments. These may contain identifiers for patients, practitioners from various
  departments for various purposes. Access to these systems typically requires some form of professional
  role or permission, such as those in healthcare, law enforcement, or other internal government uses.
</p>
<p>
  These may also operate outside of government in the private sector, such as associations or networks
  that a person may be involved with and may work in the same was as they do inside government.
  The usage of the data into the healthcare environment is not the only use of the register.
</p>
<blockquote class="stu-note">
  <p>
    <b>Note:</b>  This style of system may use the Person resource without any FHIR references
    to Patient or Practitioner resources. In these environments the Master Index is likely to
    have a master identifier that performs this logical linking.<br/>
    This style of usage has fewer security implications, as it doesn’t disclose where the
    information is being used.
  </p>
</blockquote>

<a name="portal"></a>
  <h2>
    Client Portal
  </h2>
  <p>
    Client Portals provide consumer access to a window of their data locked up in healthcare systems. 
    In many cases these systems are externally integrated and do not have access to the legacy CIS/PAS systems.
  </p>
  <p>
    In contrast to most systems where a user has access to multiple patients depending on their roles and permissions,
    a client portal provides a consumer with direct access to their data (with permissions applied).
    This can also include not just their data (via the Person.link Patient entries), but also to information that they
    have entered, or were involved with (via the Person.link RelatedPerson entries), such as observations that they 
    entered.<br/>
    With appropriate permissions/consent applied, the user could have access to other Patient records linked via 
    a RelatedPerson.
  </p>

<a name="security"></a>
  <h2>
    Security and Privacy Considerations
  </h2>
  <p>
    The Person resource may contain identifying and demographic information about an individual, therefore it must
    be protected as Identifying Information.
  </p>
  <p>
    The Person resource may contain references to the individual's other various Patient, Practitioner,
    and RelatedPerson resources, where the referenced record might be to very sensitive information.
    The access to the linked sensitive Resource may be protected, but the link itself may expose information.<br/> 
    For example where a Practitioner and Patient resource are linked through a Person resource, inspecting the
    Patient URL could reveal that the Practitioner has a record at a sensitive medical health clinic (e.g. Drug Rehabilitation Clinic).
  </p>
  <p>
    When implementing the Person resource consideration should be given to the security and privacy
    of this information. Some mitigations to these risks include higher access control protections, filling
    out the Person resource as sparsely as practical for the given use-cases, and masking some data elements for
    certain users of the information. Additional security guidance can be found on the <a href="security.html">security page</a>.
  </p>
</div>
