<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<!-- TODO: Is there a pattern that this resource does fit? Metadata? Artifact?
<p><strong>This resource is a <em>definition</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective</strong> - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>, specifically <a href="workflow.html#definition">Definition</a>.</p>
 -->

<p>
The Requirements Resource a set of statements that are requirements for some design artifact to meet.
The requirements resource is intended to meet two principle use cases:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Documenting known regulatory, business, functional and technical requirements for interoperability specifications,
particularly those published as <a href="implementationguide.html">Implementation Guides</a></li>
<li>Performing the same role for clinical processes as documented in <a href="plandefinition.html">PlanDefinition</a>
and <a href="activitydefinition.html">ActivityDefinition</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
The Requirements Resource is focused on gathering known requirements and providing 
traceability from solutions to the requirements they are intended to meet. 
</p>

<p>
In any set of requirements, some of them may already be met by preexisting specifications,
while others are requirements that must be fulfilled by some specification or design that 
is created with or subsequent to the requirements. For this reason, requirements can
directly identify features of specifications that satisfy the stated requirement, but in 
most cases, it is expected that the specifications and designs that meet the requirements
will provice traceability to the requirement.
</p>
<p>
Each Requirements resource carries a set of statements about requirements. Each 
statement has:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><b>identity</b>: Computable and humn identification of the statement</li>
 <li><b>requirement</b>: The wording of the requirement</li>
 <li><b>conformance</b>: The strength associated with the statement. The strength is almost always embedded in the language of the requirement, but this allows for filtering and a degree of automated processing</li>
 <li><b>source</b>: Source information about who was the source of the requirement</li>
 <li><b>satisfied by</b>: A reference to some pre-existing specification element that satisfies the requirement</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

<p>
Requirements may by referenced from almost any resource by the <a href="extension-satisfies-requirement.html">Requirements Satisfied</a> extension.
Generally, this extension will be found in the <a href="canonicalresource.html">Canonical Resources</a> but this is 
not a hard rule.
</p>

<p>
If requirements are satisfied by an existing specification, they SHOULD reference
a FHIR resource by <code>{url}</code> or a particular element by <code>{url}#id</code>,
but the target of a reference does not need to be a resource at all.
</p>

<p>
The requirements resource carries minimal provenance information - the name of the publisher,
and the source of the statements. Additional provenance information should be carried in a 
<a href="provenance.html">Provenance</a> resource.
</p>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
A number of stakeholders publishing FHIR implementation guides wish to do formal 
requirements tracing. This resource exists for them.
</p>
</div>

</div>
