<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <div>
    <a name="scope"></a>
    <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
    <p>
      The subscription resource is used to establish proactive event notifications from a FHIR server to another system.  Subscribers request event notifications within a predefined <a href="subscriptiontopic.html">SubscriptionTopic</a> that the server supports, and can further refine their notifications by supplying filters. Each <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> resource defines a set of allowed filters (<code>SubscriptionTopic.canFilterBy</code>), which a subscriber refer to within a <code>Subscription</code> resource (<code>Subscription.filterBy</code>).  Once a subscription is created, any event matching a specified SubscriptionTopic that meets the filtering criteria will cause a notification to be sent using the provided channel.
    </p>
    <p>
      Subscriptions are active resources; a server can only accept a subscription
      if it will execute the specified channel for any resources subsequently
      received. The subscription is no longer active once it is deleted from
      the server.
    </p>
    <p>
      By adjusting <code>Subscription.channel.payload.content</code>, subscribers can request event notifications that include full resource content; or just the ID of the triggering resource; or an empty notification body.
    </p>
    <p>
      Several channels are defined in the core specification:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#rest-hook"><b>rest-hook</b></a>: Notifications are sent via HTTPS POST to the <code>Subscription.channel.endpoint</code> URL (e.g., <code>https://...</code>)</li>
      <li><a href="#websockets"><b>websocket</b></a>: Notifications are sent via WS/S to a client connected via a WebSocket</li>
      <li><a href="#email"><b>email</b></a>: Notifications are sent via SMTP/S, S/MIME, or Direct to the <code>Subscription.channel.endpoint</code> email URI (e.g., <code>mailto:...</code>)</li>
      <li><a href="#messaging"><b>message</b></a>: Notifications are sent via <a href="messaging.html">FHIR messaging</a> to the application identified in the <code>Subscription.channel.endpoint</code> URI</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Additional channel types can be <a href="#channel-extending">defined</a> by external implementation guides.
      See below for further discussion of the various channels.
    </p>
  </div>

  <div>
    <a name="bnr"></a>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
    <p>
      As an alternative to subscriptions, the RESTful API describes a
      polling-based method for observing events using <a href="bundle.html">bundles</a>
      and the <a href="http.html#history">history operation</a>. This method
      of polling allows for a much tighter relationship between the client and
      the server that doesn't involve missing updates and/or deletes.
    </p>
    <p>
      When using the <code>Subscription</code> resource, the FHIR server combines
      the roles of publisher and information distributer. Other arrangements
      of the publish and subscribe pattern describe separate agents for the two roles.
      Implementers may implement the <code>Subscription</code> resource using an
      architecture with separate agents, or using any other pub/sub architectire
      (e.g. see <a href="http://fhircast.org/">FHIRCast</a>, or, more generally,
      <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/websub/">W3C Pub/Sub</a>).
    </p>
    <p>TODO: Does this imply that Subscriptions can be built on top of FHIRCast?</p>
  </div>

</div>
