<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<a name="safety" />
	<h2>Safety and Security</h2>
	<p>
		Applications are responsible for following <a href="security.html">FHIR security guidance</a>. Some
		recommendations specific to subscriptions are provided on the <a href="subscriptions.html#safety">Subscriptions
			Framework</a> page.
	</p>

	<a name="multi-resource" />
	<h2>Multi-Resource Subscriptions</h2>
	<p>
		As indicated on the <a href="subscriptions.html#multi-resource-topics">Subscriptions Framework</a> and 
		<a href="subscriptiontopic.html#resource-scope">SubscriptionTopic resource</a> pages, subscriptions can have
		more than a single resource in scope (e.g., a subscription that triggers on both <code>Condition</code> and
		<code>Observation</code> resources, a topic tied to all resources, etc.). If there are filters that do not apply
		to every resource available in a topic, clients SHOULD ensure that the <code>Subscription.filterBy.resourceType</code>
		element is filled appropriately. More detail can be found in the 
		<a href="subscriptions.html#resource-filters">Filters and Resource Types</a> section of the Subscriptions
		Framework page.
	</p>

	<a name="payloads" />
	<h2>Notification Content</h2>
	<p>
		There are three options available when specifying the amount of content a notification will contain: <code>empty</code>,
		<code>id-only</code>, and <code>full-resource</code>. These options change the level of detail conveyed in the
		notification <code>Bundle</code>.
	</p>
	<p>
		When deciding which payload type to request, systems SHOULD consider both ease of processing and security of PHI
		(Personal health information). To mitigate the risk of information leakage, systems SHOULD use the minimum level
		of detail consistent with the use case. In practice, <code>id-only</code> provides a good balance between
		security and performance for many real-world scenarios.
	</p>
	<p>
		If a server cannot or will not honor a payload type (e.g., will not send <code>full-resource</code> over HTTP),
		it SHOULD reject the Subscription request. A server MAY instead accept the subscription with modifications and
		return the accepted and modified version to the client.
	</p>
	<p>
		When sending event notifications servers SHALL populate the <a
			href="subscriptionstatus-definitions.html#SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent">SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent</a>
		structure with relevant information, depending on the payload type.
	</p>

	<a name="payloads-empty" />
	<h3>empty</h3>
	<p>
		An example notification with an <code>empty</code> payload can be found <a
			href="notification-empty.html">here</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
		With the content type of <code>empty</code>, all information about the resources involved in triggering the
		notification is only available via channels other than the Subscription itself (e.g., the REST API or <a
			href="subscription-operation-events.html">$events</a> operation). This mitigates many security concerns by
		both removing most PHI from the notification and allows servers to consolidate authorization and authentication
		logic. When the subscriber receives a notification of this type, it may query the server to fetch all the
		relevant resources based on the <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> and applicable filters. The client might include
		a <code>_lastUpdated</code> query parameter, supplying its last query timestamp to retrieve only the most recent
		resources. For example, if the notification is for a topic about patient admission, the subscriber will
		generally query for recent Encounters for a patient or group of patients, then fetch them as needed.
	</p>
	<p>
		When populating the <code>SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent</code> structure for a notification with an
		<code>empty</code> payload, a server SHALL NOT include references to resources (e.g., <a
			href="subscriptionstatus-definitions.html#SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.focus">SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.focus</a>
		and <a
			href="subscriptionstatus-definitions.html#SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.additionalContext">SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.additionalContext</a>
		SHALL NOT be present).
	</p>
	<p>
		When the content type is <code>empty</code>, notification bundles SHALL NOT contain <code>Bundle.entry</code>
		elements other than the <code>SubscriptionStatus</code> for the notification.
	</p>

	<a name="payloads-id-only" />
	<h3>id-only</h3>
	<p>
		An example notification with an <code>id-only</code> payload can be found <a
			href="notification-id-only.html">here</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
		With the content type of <code>id-only</code>, the resources involved in triggering the notification are only
		available through other channels (e.g., REST API), but notifications include URLs which can be used to access
		those resources. This allows servers to consolidate authorization and authentication logic, while removing the
		need for expensive queries by subscribers. When a subscriber receives a notification of this type, it may
		directly fetch all the relevant resources using the supplied resource ids. For example, if the notification is
		for a topic about patient admission, the subscriber may fetch the Encounter(s) for a patient or group of
		patients.
	</p>
	<p>
		When the content type is <code>id-only</code>, the <code>SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent</code> structure
		SHALL include references to the appropriate focus resources in the <a
			href="subscriptionstatus-definitions.html#SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.focus">SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.focus</a>
		element. This provides clients a fixed location to consolidate IDs for all notification types.
	</p>
	<p>
		Additionally, notification bundles MAY contain, in addition to the <code>SubscriptionStatus</code>, at least one
		<code>Bundle.entry</code> for each resource relevant to the notification. For example, a notification for a
		topic based on Encounter MAY include a reference to the Encounter and MAY also include additional resources
		deemed relevant (e.g., the linked Patient).
	</p>

	<a name="payloads-full-resource" />
	<h3>full-resource</h3>
	<p>
		An example notification with a <code>full-resource</code> payload can be found <a
			href="notification-full-resource.html">here</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
		With the content type of <code>full-resource</code>, the resources involved in triggering the notification are
		included in the notification bundle. When a subscriber receives a notification of this type, resources are
		already present in the bundle, though the subscriber may need to fetch additional resources from the server. For
		example, the if the notification is for a topic about patient admission, the subscriber may require related
		<code>Observation</code> resources.
	</p>
	<p>
		When the content type is <code>full-resource</code>, the <code>SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent</code>
		structure SHALL include references to the appropriate focus resources in the <a
			href="subscriptionstatus-definitions.html#SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.focus">SubscriptionStatus.notificationEvent.focus</a>
		element. This provides clients a fixed location to consolidate IDs for all notification types.
	</p>
	<p>
		Notification bundles for <code>full-resource</code> subscriptions SHALL contain, in addition to the
		<code>SubscriptionStatus</code>, at least one <code>Bundle.entry</code> for each resource relevant to the
		notification. For example, a notification for a topic based on Encounter SHALL include an Encounter and MAY
		include additional resources deemed relevant (e.g., the relevant Patient). Each <code>Bundle.entry</code> for a
		<code>full-resource</code> notification SHALL contain a relevant resource in the <code>entry.resource</code>
		element. If a server cannot include the resource contents due to an issue with a specific notification, the
		server SHALL populate the <code>entry.request</code> and/or <code>entry.response</code> elements.
	</p>

	<a name="batching" />
	<h2>Batching Results</h2>
	<p>
		Subscriptions allow servers to batch multiple notifications into a single <code>subscription-notification</code>
		Bundle. For example, if a server has a high-frequency of updates (e.g., several per second), it could be
		beneficial to combine notifications to reduce traffic and overhead. Note that servers SHALL NOT delay sending
		notification longer than time span specified by <code>Subscription.heartbeat</code>.
	</p>
	<p>
		The <code>Subscription.maxCount</code> element allows clients to specify the maximum number of events
		that can be combined in a single notification. When present, servers SHALL NOT include more than the
		specified number of events in a notification bundle. Note that this is not a strict limit on the total
		number of entries in a bundle, as dependent resources (e.g., included related resources) can be 
		present in Bundles, in addition to the event notifications.
	</p>

	<a name="channels" />
	<h2>Channels</h2>

	<a name="channels-deciding" />
	<h3>Deciding on Channel Type</h3>
	<p>
		This specification defines a core set of channel types to cover the majority of common use cases. Servers MAY
		define additional channel types as needed. Below is some guidance for implementers to consider when selecting a
		channel type.
	</p>

	<a name="deciding-rest-hook" />
	<h4>REST-Hook</h4>
	<p>
		The FHIR standard makes extensive use of the RESTful model. Given the popularity of REST and widespread
		adoption, most implementers should consider using REST-hook channels whenever possible. In general, REST-based
		systems are well-supported (e.g., tooling, infrastructure, documentation, etc.), and will present the lowest bar
		for implementation.
	</p>

	<a name="deciding-websocket" />
	<h4>Websocket</h4>
	<p>
		Websockets are unique in the pre-defined channel types in being the only channel that does not require the
		client to have an endpoint. Due to this property, the websocket channel is very useful for clients where
		creating an endpoint would be difficult or impossible (e.g., mobile clients, web-based clients, etc.).
	</p>
	<p>
		The websocket channel type is still undergoing testing and refinement - current details can be found in the 
		<a href="https://hl7.org/fhir/uv/subscriptions-backport/">FHIR Subscriptions Backport Implementation Guide</a>.
	</p>

	<a name="deciding-email" />
	<h4>Email</h4>
	<p>
		The Email channel is the only channel that could contest REST in non-FHIR implementations. That said, Email
		communication is often high-latency and is typically used for communication to individuals - not applications.
		Email channels are particularly useful in the context of these non-application use cases, such as public health
		notifications. For example, if a public health agency does not have the ability or desire to build a custom
		RESTful solution (e.g., creating and maintaining an endpoint to receive notifications, as well as software to
		consume those notifications), it is straightforward to map notifications to email addresses or aliases.
	</p>

	<a name="deciding-messaging" />
	<h4>FHIR Messaging</h4>
	<p>
		FHIR Messaging is a mechanism defined to allow for non-RESTful communication between FHIR servers and clients.
		One common use case is when connectivity is an issue (e.g., remote sites that batch all communications when
		connections are available). This channel defines how to integrate topic-based subscriptions with the FHIR
		Messaging model.
	</p>

	<a name="deciding-custom" />
	<h4>Custom Channels</h4>
	<p>
		For use cases that are not well-met by any of the predefined channels, the Subscriptions Framework allows for
		custom channel definitions. Some examples of scenarios where custom channels may be applicable include:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>requirements for reliable (guaranteed) delivery (e.g., message queues)</li>
		<li>implementations using other communication protocols (e.g., protocols specific to a cloud-based provider)
		</li>
		<li>implementations using a non-standard serialization format</li>
	</ul>

	<a name="rest-hook" />
	<h3>REST Hook</h3>
	<p>
		To receive notifications via HTTP/S POST, a client requests a subscription with the channel type of `rest-hook`
		(from the <code>subscription-channel-type</code> Code System) and and an endpoint
		(<code>Subscription.endpoint</code>) with the desired URL. Note that this URL must be accessible by the hosting
		server.
	</p>

	<p>
		To convey an event notification, the server POSTs a <code>notification Bundle</code> to the client's nominated
		endpoint URL per the format requests in the Subscription:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>The <code>content-type</code> of the POST SHALL match the MIME type on the Subscription <a
				href="subscription-definitions.html#Subscription.contentType">Subscription.contentType</a>.</li>
		<li>Each <a href="subscription-definitions.html#Subscription.parameter">Subscription.parameter</a> indicates an
			HTTP request header and SHALL be sent as <code>{parameter.name}: {parameter.value}</code>.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>
		When a subscription is created for a REST Hook channel type, the server SHALL set initial status to
		<code>requested</code>, pending verification of the nominated endpoint URL. After a successful
		<code>handshake</code> notification has been sent and accepted, the server SHALL update the status to
		<code>active</code>. Any errors in the initial <code>handshake</code> SHALL result in the status being changed
		to <code>error</code>.
	</p>

	<p>
		An example workflow for establishing a <code>rest-hook</code> subscription is shown below.
	</p>

	<figure>
		<img src="subscription-channel-rest-hook.svg" />
		<figcaption>Diagram showing a possible workflow for rest-hook subscriptions</figcaption>
	</figure>

	<ol type="1">
		<li>
			Client creates a <code>Subscription</code> with the <code>channelType</code> set to <code>rest-hook</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server responds with a success code and creates the subscription with a state of <code>requested</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server performs an HTTP POST to the requested endpoint with a <code>handshake</code> notification.
		</li>
		<li>
			Client Endpoint accepts the POST and returns a success HTTP code (e.g., <code>200</code>).
		</li>
		<li>
			Server sends a notification of type <code>heartbeat</code> at any time (SHOULD at least once per
			<code>heartbeatPeriod</code>).
		</li>
		<li>
			Client Endpoint accepts a <code>heartbeat</code> via HTTP POST and returns an HTTP success code (e.g.,
			<code>200</code>).
		</li>
		<li>
			Server sends a notification of type <code>event-notification</code> when triggered.
		</li>
		<li>
			Client Endpoint accepts an <code>event-notification</code> via HTTP POST and returns an HTTP code (e.g.,
			<code>200</code>).
		</li>
	</ol>

	<a name="rest-hook-security" />
	<h4>Channel Security Notes</h4>
	<p>
		HTTP is neither a secure nor an encrypted channel, nor does it provide endpoint verification. It is strongly
		recommended that implementations refuse requests to send notifications to URLs using the HTTP protocol (use
		HTTPS instead).
	</p>

	<a name="email" />
	<h3>Email</h3>
	<p>
		While the primary interface for FHIR servers is the FHIR REST API, notifications need not occur via REST.
		Indeed, some subscribers may be unable to maintain an outward-facing HTTP server to receive triggered
		notifications. For example, a public health organization may want to be notified of outbreaks of various
		illnesses. This can be accomplished using an <code>email</code> notification channel.
	</p>
	<p>
		To receive notifications via Email, a client requests a subscription with the channel type
		(<code>Subscription.channelType</code>) of <code>email</code> (from the <code>subscription-channel-type</code> 
		Code System) and an endpoint (<code>Subscription.endpoint</code>) with the desired email URI (e.g.,
		<code>mailto:public_health_notifications@example.org</code>).
	</p>
	<p>
		The server will send a new message each time a notification should be sent (e.g., per event or per batch). The
		server will create a message based on the values present in the <code>Subscription.contentType</code> and
		<code>Subscription.content</code> fields. If a server cannot honor the requested combination, the server should
		reject the Subscription request rather than send unexpected email messages.
	</p>
	<p>The email channel sets two guidelines about content:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Message Body content SHALL be human readable</li>
		<li>Message Attachments SHOULD be machine readable</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
		Due to these guidelines, the <code>Subscription.contentType</code> refers to the content of the body of the
		message. Attachment type information can be appended as a MIME parameter, for example:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li><code>text/plain</code>: a plain-text body with no attachment</li>
		<li><code>text/html</code>: an HTML body with no attachment</li>
		<li><code>text/plain;attach=application/fhir+json</code>: a plain-text body with a FHIR JSON bundle attached
		</li>
		<li><code>text/html;attach=application/fhir+xml</code>: an HTML body with a FHIR XML bundle attached</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
		The <code>Subscription.content</code> field SHALL be applied to any attachments, and MAY be applied to body
		contents (depending on server implementation). However, a server must not include a body which exceeds the
		specified content level. For example, a server may choose to always include a standard message in the body of
		the message containing no PHI and vary the attachment, but cannot include PHI in the body of an email when the
		content is set to <code>empty</code>.
	</p>

	<p>
		An example workflow using the <code>email</code> channel type is included below.
	</p>

	<figure>
		<img src="subscription-channel-email.svg" />
		<figcaption>Diagram showing a possible workflow for email subscriptions</figcaption>
	</figure>

	<ol type="1">
		<li>
			Client creates a <code>Subscription</code> with the <code>channelType</code> set to <code>email</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server MAY respond with a success code and create the subscription with a state of <code>active</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server MAY respond with a success code and create the subscription with a state of <code>requested</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server sends an initial message via the specified email server (e.g., verify the request, opt-out
			instructions, etc.).
		</li>
		<li>
			Email Server responds with a channel appropriate response code (e.g., <code>250: OK</code>).
		</li>
		<li>
			Server may send an email for a notification of type <code>heartbeat</code> at any time (SHOULD at least once
			per <code>heartbeatPeriod</code>).
		</li>
		<li>
			Server may send an email for a notification of type <code>event-notification</code> at any time.
		</li>
	</ol>

	<a name="email-security" />
	<h4>Channel Security Notes</h4>
	<p>
		Email (SMTP) is not a secure channel. Implementers must ensure that any messages containing PHI have been
		secured according to their policy requirements (e.g., use of a system such as <a
			href="https://directtrust.org/standards/the-direct-standard">Direct</a>).
	</p>

	<a name="messaging" />
	<h3>Messaging</h3>
	<p>
		There are times when it is desirable to use Subscriptions as a communication channel between FHIR servers that
		are connected via Messaging instead of REST. This can be accomplished using a <code>Subscription</code> with the
		channel type of <code>message</code>.
	</p>
	<p>
		To receive notifications via messaging, a client should request a subscription with the channel type
		(<code>Subscription.channelType</code>) of <code>message</code> and set the endpoint
		(<code>Subscription.endpoint</code>) to the destination FHIR server base URL. Note that this URL must be
		accessible by the hosting server.
	</p>
	<p>
		The FHIR server hosting the subscription (server) will send FHIR messages to the destination FHIR server
		(endpoint) as needed. These messages will, as the contents of the message, have a fully-formed
		<code>subscription-notification</code> Bundle. An example message can be found <a
			href="notification-message-full-resource.xml.html">here</a>.
	</p>

	<p>
		An example workflow using the <code>message</code> channel type is included below.
	</p>
	<figure>
		<img src="subscription-channel-messaging.svg" />
		<figcaption>Diagram showing a possible workflow for FHIR Messaging subscriptions</figcaption>
	</figure>
	<ol type="1">
		<li>
			Client creates a <code>Subscription</code> with the <code>channelType</code> set to <code>message</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server responds with a success code and creates the subscription with a state of <code>requested</code>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server sends a FHIR Message to the requested endpoint with a <code>handshake</code> notification.
		</li>
		<li>
			Client Endpoint accepts the Message and returns success.
		</li>
		<li>
			Server may send a Message containing a notification of type <code>heartbeat</code> at any time (SHOULD at
			least once per <code>heartbeatPeriod</code>).
		</li>
		<li>
			Server may send a Message containing a notification of type <code>event-notification</code> at any time.
		</li>
	</ol>

	[%stu-note msg%]
	The Messaging channel type needs more testing and feedback to ensure all requirements are met before finalizing the
	specification.
	[%end-note%]


	<a name="message-security" />
	<h4>Channel Security Notes</h4>
	<p>
		Servers MAY require that the end-point is white-listed prior to allowing these kinds of subscriptions.
		Additionally, servers MAY impose authorization/authentication requirements for server to server communication
		(e.g., certificate pinning, etc.).
	</p>


	<a name="channel-extending" />
	<h2>Defining Channel Types</h2>
	<p>
		Defining a new channel type requires clear communication to implementers of both clients and servers around
		requirements and expectations. Below are some areas which should be considered when creating a channel. Anyone
		defining a channel type is encouraged to publish their definition at <a
			href="https://registry.fhir.org/">registry.fhir.org</a>.
	</p>

	[%stu-note ch%]
	Warning: This section is still in early drafting; feedback from topic authors is welcome to refine the following
	guidance.
	[%end-note%]

	<a name="channel-extending-basics" />
	<h3>Channel Basics</h3>
	<p>
		At a minimum, the following items should be defined:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>A system for Subscription.channelType that reflects the publisher of the definition (e.g.,
			"https://myorg.example.org" instead of "urn:uuid:be35238b-0ed6-4062-93cf-818b8023a103")</li>
		<li>A generally descriptive code for <code>Subscription.channelType</code> (e.g., 'secure-mq' instead of
			'channel')</li>
		<li>The type of data required in <code>Subscription.endpoint</code> (e.g., URI, etc.)</li>
		<li>The meaning of <code>Subscription.parameter</code> field values (e.g., <a href="#rest-hook">REST-hook</a>
			defines as HTTP headers included in a POST). Note that channels can specify general behavior and/or specific
			parameters by <code>name</code>.</li>
		<li>Any additions or variations on MIME types for <code>Subscription.contentType</code> (e.g., <a
				href="#email">email</a> defines this as the email body, with allowable attachments.)</li>
		<li>Whether <code>handshake</code> notifications are used, and guidance on usage if they are</li>
		<li>Whether <code>heartbeat</code> notifications are used, and guidance on timings if they are</li>
	</ul>

	<a name="channel-extending-security" />
	<h3>Channel Security Considerations</h3>
	<p>
		Defining a channel has security implications. While it is not expected that authors cover all aspects of
		security, guidance specific to the channel SHOULD be provided. For example, when discussing REST-hooks, this
		specification includes guidance about using HTTPS over HTTP.
	</p>
	<p>
		If the channel CANNOT be secured, that should be stated with a warning not to transfer PHI. If the channel is or
		can be secured, guidance should be given on how configurations relate to PHI safety, for example:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Does the channel determine the legitimacy of both endpoints?</li>
		<li>Is the channel secure from third-party monitoring?</li>
	</ul>

	<a name="errors" />
	<h2>Managing Subscriptions and Errors</h2>
	<p>
		Subscriptions can be used to manage long-lived requests for notifications. For details about management and
		expectations regarding errors, see <a href="subscriptions.html#errors">Managing Subscriptions and Errors</a> on
		the Subscriptions Framework page.
	</p>

	<a name="authorization-hint"></a>
	<h2>Authorization Hinting in Notifications</h2>

	<p>
	It can be appropriate for a server to include authorization information alongside notifications. This information 
	could be used to inform a recipient about how authorization should be done when querying-for or retrieving resources 
	from a notification (e.g., when querying based on an <code>empty</code> notification), or to provide tokens or other
	information needed to access resources referenced in the notification (e.g., when retrieving resources based on an
	<code>id-only</code> notification).
	</p>
	<p>
	Depending on the channel used, notifications MAY or MAY NOT be secure from third parties. Implementers SHOULD ensure 
	that any authorization information included complies with security best practices (e.g., providing a token exchanged 
	during an OAuth workflow, along with other data such as a client authentication token, for an access token).
	</p>
	<p>
	When including authorization information in a notification, servers SHOULD use security best practices (e.g., short-lived
	and single-use tokens, temporary access codes, etc). For more information, see the 
	<a href="security.html">FHIR Security Guidance</a> document.
	</p>

</div>