<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <div>
    <a name="scope"></a>
    <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
    <p>
      The <code>Subscription</code> resource is used to establish proactive event notifications from a FHIR server to another system.  Subscribers request event notifications within a predefined <a href="subscriptiontopic.html">SubscriptionTopic</a> that the server supports, and can further refine their notifications by supplying filters. Each <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> resource defines a set of allowed filters (<code>SubscriptionTopic.canFilterBy</code>), which a subscriber refer to within a <code>Subscription</code> resource (<code>Subscription.filterBy</code>).  Once a subscription is created, any event matching a specified SubscriptionTopic that meets the filtering criteria will cause a notification to be sent using the provided channel.
    </p>
    <p>
      Subscriptions are active resources; a server can only accept a subscription
      if it will execute the specified channel for any resources subsequently
      received. The subscription is no longer active once it is deleted from
      the server.
    </p>
    <p>
      By adjusting <code>Subscription.channel.payload.content</code>, subscribers can request event notifications that include full resource content; or just the ID of the triggering resource; or an empty notification body.
    </p>
    <p>
      Several channels are defined in the core specification:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#rest-hook"><b>rest-hook</b></a>: Notifications are sent via HTTPS POST to the <code>Subscription.channel.endpoint</code> URL (e.g., <code>https://...</code>)</li>
      <li><a href="#websockets"><b>websocket</b></a>: Notifications are sent via WS/S to a client connected via a WebSocket</li>
      <li><a href="#email"><b>email</b></a>: Notifications are sent via SMTP/S, S/MIME, or Direct to the <code>Subscription.channel.endpoint</code> email URI (e.g., <code>mailto:...</code>)</li>
      <li><a href="#messaging"><b>message</b></a>: Notifications are sent via <a href="messaging.html">FHIR messaging</a> to the application identified in the <code>Subscription.channel.endpoint</code> URI</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Additional channel types can be <a href="#channel-extending">defined</a> by external implementation guides.
      See below for further discussion of the various channels.
    </p>
  </div>

  <div>
    <a name="bnr"></a>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
    <p>
      There is a close relationship between <a href="subscriptiontopic.html">SubscriptionTopic</a> and <code>Subscription</code>.
      <ul>
        <li>
          A <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> defines the <b>data</b> and <b>change</b> a <code>Subscription</code> uses to trigger notifications.
        </li>
        <li>
          A <code>Subscription</code> describes a particular client's request to be notified about events defined in a <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> and how those notifications should be delivered.
        </li>
        <li>
          A <code>Subscription</code> may define additional filters to be applied when detecting events for notifications, but only as defined and allowed in the relevant <code>SubscriptionTopic</code>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      The use of Subscriptions requires the use of SubscriptionTopics - without an underlying SubscriptionTopic, a Subscription has no meaning and will not trigger any client notifications.
    </p>
    <p>
      As an alternative to subscriptions, the FHIR REST API describes a
      polling-based method for observing events using <a href="bundle.html">bundles</a>
      and the <a href="http.html#history">history operation</a>. This method
      of polling allows for a more straightforward implementation, but can cause delays
      in process (e.g., time between polling operations) and will result in higher computational
      costs on the server (e.g., processing queries when there are no state changes).
    </p>
    <p>
      When using the <code>Subscription</code> resource, the FHIR server combines
      the roles of publisher and information distributer. Some arrangements
      of the 'publish and subscribe' pattern describe separate agents for the two roles.
      This specification makes no recommendations towards the internal architecture of 
      server implementations.
    </p>

    <a name="relationtofhircast" />
    <h3>Relation to FHIRcast</h3>
    <p>
      <a href="http://fhircast.org">FHIRcast</a> is a HTTP-based framework for user-activity synchronization across applications.  FHIRcast and Subscription are both conceptually based <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/websub/">W3 WebSub</a>, and while the mechanics of two projects look similar, they are fundamentally different projects used to address different use cases.  In particular:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>FHIRcast is designed to be used by multiple applications on the same device</p>
          <p>Subscriptions are designed to be used by multiple distinct systems</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>FHIRcast sends only single-event notifications</p>
          <p>Subscriptions allow servers to batch multiple notifications in high-frequency scenarios</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>FHIRcast is designed around short-lived sessions</p>
          <p>Subscriptions are intented to be long-lived resources</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

  </div>

</div>
