<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <div>
    <a name="scope"></a>
    <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
    <p>
      The subscription resource is used to define a push-based transaction from a server to another system.  A suscriber subscribes to one or more predefined <a href="topic.html">Topics</a> which the server supports. Subscribers typically receive only a subset of the total event notifications for a given topic by filtering on the content. The allowed filtering criteria are defined by the <code>Topic</code> resource, while requested filters are specified within the <code>Subscription</code> resource.  Once a subscription is created, any resource change covered by a specified topic that meets the filtering criteria will cause a notification to be sent using the provided channel.
    </p>
    <p>
      The server is able to send notifications without any information about the matching resource, with the ID of the matching resource, or with the entire resource.
    </p>
    <p>
      Several different types of channels are supported:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#rest-hook"><b>rest-hook</b></a>: Notifications are sent via HTTP/S POST to a URL identified in the Subscription resource</li>
      <li><a href="#websockets"><b>websocket</b></a>: Notifications are sent via WS/S to a client connected via a WebSocket</li>
      <li><a href="#email-sms"><b>email/sms</b></a>: Notifications are sent via SMTP or SMS to the nominated email address or phone number</li>
      <li><a href="#messaging"><b>message</b></a>: Notifications are sent via <a href="messaging.html">FHIR messaging</a> to the application identified in the URI</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      See below for further discussion of the various channels. Note that sending
      the entire resource creates security concerns that must be managed by the server.
    </p>
    <p>
      Subscriptions are active resources; a server can only accept a subscription
      if it will execute the specified channel for any resources subsequently
      received. The subscription is no longer active once it is deleted from
      the server.
    </p>
  </div>

  <div>
    <a name="bnr"></a>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
    <p>
      As an alternative to subscriptions, the RESTful API describes a
      polling-based subscription method using <a href="bundle.html">bundles</a>
      and the <a href="http.html#history">history operation</a>. This method
      of polling allows for a much tighter relationship between the client and
      the server that doesn't involve missing updates and/or deletes.
    </p>
    <p>
      When using the <code>Subscription</code> resource, the FHIR server combines
      the roles of publisher and information distributer. Other arrangements
      of the publish and subscribe pattern describe separate agents for the two roles.
      Implementers may implement the <code>Subscription</code> resource using an
      architecture with separate agents, or using any other pub/sub architectire
      (e.g. see <a href="http://fhircast.org/">FHIRCast</a>, or, more generally,
      <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/websub/">W3C Pub/Sub</a>).
    </p>
  </div>

</div>
