<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>

<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><b>This is a candidate resource not yet formally proposed (or approved)</b></p>

<p>
The subscription reason is used to define a push based subscription 
from a server to another system. Once a subscription is registered with the server, 
the server checks every resource that is created or updated, and 
if the resource matches the given criteria, it send a message
on the defined "channel" so that another system is able 
to take an appropriate action. The server is able to send 
notifications without any information about the matching
resource, or with the entire resource.
</p>
<p>
Several different types of channels are supported:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><b>rest-hook</b>: A post is made to the URL. If a resource is included, the URL is intepreted as the service base</li>
 <li><b>websocket</b>: An PING message is sent to the designated URI</li>
 <li><b>email/sms</b>: An notification is send to nominated email address or SMS number</li>
 <li><b>message</b>: The resource is sent to the application identified in the URI as a <a href="messaging.html">message</a></li>
</ul>
<p>
See below for further discussion of the various channels. Note that sending
the entire resource creates security concerns that must be managed by the server.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Once a subscription is created, any newly created or updated resources 
that meet the criteria in the resource cause a notification to be sent using the 
provided channel. The criteria is a <a href="search.html">Search</a> string
that has the same interpretation as if it were appended to the base 
URL and submitted using the REST API. Note that the criteria is applied to the new value of the
resource. The consequence of this is that there is no notification 
when a resource is deleted, or when a resource is updated so that 
it no longer meets the criteria. 
</p>
<p>
The RESTful API describes a polling-based subscription method using
<a href="extras.html#bundle">bundles</a> and the <a href="http.html#history">history operation</a>. 
This method of polling allows for a much tighter relationship between
the client and the server, that doesn't involve missing updates and/or 
deletes. 
</p>
<p>
Subscriptions are active resources; a server can only accept a subscription
if it will execute the provided channel for any resources subsequently 
received. The subscription is no longer active once it is deleted from 
the server.
</p>

</div>

</div>
