<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<h2>Notes</h2>
<h3>Perpetual and Episodic Accounts</h3>
<p>
    There may be two types of accounts that are used to track billing activities with medical systems:
</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Episodic Account:</b>
An account that collects the charges for a specific set of services offered over a limited time period.  For example, a hospital account might contain all charges related
to a given admission, including any inpatient appointments, and possibly re-admissions, of the billing for those re-admissions should be grouped with the initial admission
for the purpose of claim submission.<br/>

Episodic Accounts often exist for the duration of a relatively short billing cycle (for example, a month, or possibly a quarter).  One a given billing cycle ends, the
associated Episodic Account would close, and a new account would open for the next billing cycle.  A patient that is admitted for 6 months, where the billing cycle is
monthly, would have 6 episodic accounts each covering one month.<br/>

Episodic Accounts may be communicated using the Account.covers property.
</li>
<li><b>Perpetual Account</b>
A long running account that accumulates charges and payments associated with a specific beneficiary.  This account is often open for as long as the beneficiary has a
relationship with the healthcare organization.  It may be linked to an EpisodeOfCare.  A beneficiary may have different perpetual accounts.  For example, one for charges
related to car crash (i.e., third party liability).  One associated with charges related to a research study the patient is participating in.  And one for their general
personal/family care, which would be covered by their normal insurance.<br/>

Perpetual Accounts may be communicated using the Encounter.account or EpisodeOfCare.account properties.
</li>
</ul>
</div>
