<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
<p><b>Note to Balloters:</b> The key changes made since FHIR 6.0.0-ballot4 include:</p>
<p>Changed the ResearchStudy.studyDesign ValueSet binding to be HL7 Terminology.</p>
<p>Changed the ResearchStudy.associatedParty.role ValueSet binding to be HL7 Terminology and &quot;preferred&quot; binding.</p>
<p>Changed the ResearchStudy.progressStatus.state ValueSet binding to be HL7 Terminology and &quot;preferred&quot; binding.</p>
<p>Added DocumentReference as a possible Resource type to ResearchStudy.result.</p>
<p>Added ResearchStudy.comparisonGroup.name string element.</p>
<p>Changed ResearchStudy.primaryPurposeType 0..1 to ResearchStudy.purposeType 0..* and example binding strength..</p>
<p>Updated the definition of ResearchStudy.progressStatus.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="background-color: lightblue">
	<p><b>Release Notes:</b></p>
	<ul>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53698">FHIR-53698</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53697">FHIR-53697</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53696">FHIR-53696</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53694">FHIR-53694</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53693">FHIR-53693</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53692">FHIR-53692</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-57268">FHIR-57268</a></li>
	</ul>
</blockquote>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<p>This resource is a <a href="workflow.html#definition">
        <em>definition resource</em>
      </a> from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.</p>
    <p>A process where a researcher or organization plans and then executes a series of steps intended to increase the field of healthcare-related knowledge. This includes studies of safety, efficacy, comparative effectiveness and other information about medications, devices, therapies and other interventional and investigative techniques. A ResearchStudy involves the gathering of information about human or animal subjects or stability data about drug products or drug substances.</p>
	<p>For clinical trials -- A research study is a scientific way to improve or develop new methods of health care. Studies are designed to answer specific questions on how to prevent, diagnose, or treat diseases and disorders. The ResearchStudy resource describes essential information about the study, including the purpose, objective, sponsor, investigator, therapy, condition being studied, schedule of activities, and other key items.</p>
    <p>Uses for the ResearchStudy resource include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Registering a clinical trial in trial registry such as clinicaltrials.gov</li>
      <li>Communicating study protocol information between study stakeholders</li>
      <li>Supporting study set up of sites, forms</li>
      <li>Grouping Observation resources by study</li>
      <li>Setting up a Schedule of Activities for the study and its subjects</li>
	  <li>Specifying Study information in support of Genomic, Proteomic and Stability studies</li>
      </ul>

  <h3>Extensions</h3>
  <p>ResearchStudy is aimed at all forms of studies.  For some study types specific extensions have been defined </p>

  <p>
    <b>Extension: SiteRecruitment</b>
  </p>
<p>Some studies need to find sites according to specific criteria - for example site has a freezer capable of very low temperatures and a centrifuge.</p>

  <p>
    <b>Extension: StudyRegistration</b>
  </p>
<p>Used to separate study registration activities from study progress status.</p>

</div>

</div>
