<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
    Insurance offerings will be fully described by the combination of both InsurancePlan (the costs) and InsuranceProduct (the benefits).
    However, some systems may only need to represent the InsurancePlan, so that Coverage resources can describe which plan is associated
    with a given beneficiary.  In that case, there will be some other system that is responsible for tracking the benefits associated with the plan.
</p>
<p>
    An InsurancePlan pairs the health insurance coverage benefits under an InsuranceProduct with the particular cost sharing structure
    offered to a consumer. A given InsuranceProduct may comprise multiple InsurancePlans.
</p>

<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn">
  <p><b>Note to Balloters:</b></p>
  <p>This resource is likely to be removed from the specification and moved to being an <a href="resource.html#additional">Additional Resource</a>
	after this ballot due to concerns around it's readiness, and the thin implementation experience. Ballot comments on this subject are welcome.</p>

</blockquote>  
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
    <a href="insuranceproduct.html">InsuranceProduct</a> describes a list of covered benefits and networks as well as details about who
    administers the product and applicable coverage areas.
</p>
<p>
    InsurancePlan describes the costs to the subscriber or beneficiary associated with benefits, as well as additional information about
    the offering, such as who administers the plan, a coverage area, contact information, etc.  The specific benefits covered by the plan
    are described in the InsuranceProduct referenced in InsurancePlan.product.
</p>
<p>
    A <a href="coverage.html">Coverage</a> resource establishes the link between an InsurancePlan and a beneficiary and optionally a subscriber. 
</p>
</div>

</div>
