<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../../../schema/fhir-single.xsd">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"> </a>
		<h3>Scope and Usage</h3>
		<p>
      This profile sets expectations for use of the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">DataElement</a> resource within the 
      <a href="sdc.html">Structured Data Capture</a> implementation guide.  This includes
      identifying which core elements and extensions must be supported.
    </p>
		<p>
      The focus of this profile is on those characteristics of Data Elements which are necessary to support the
      definition of forms (questionnaires) that can support auto-population or pre-population of content on the basis
      of referenced data elements.
    </p>
		<p>
      For the purposes of this profile, <i>Supported</i> means that clients SHALL be capable of processing the element/extension and use the information to control the display
      and information capture associated with the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">DataElement</a>.  It means that servers SHALL be capable of persisting those 
      elements and returning 
      them in response to requests.
    </p>
	</div>
	<div>
		<a name="boundaries"> </a>
		<h3>Boundaries and Relationships</h3>
		<p>
    This profile relies on the use of a number of other profiles, some required, others available for use &quot;when necessary&quot;:
    </p>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement-11179.html">datalement-11179</a> which defines extensions for ISO-11179-specific concepts, such as ObjectClass and 
          Property</li>
			<li>
				<a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}element-extensions.html">element-extensions</a> which defines extensions describing constraints on the values for data elements.  
          There are used here to constrain the allowed values for questions.</li>
			<li>
				<a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}iso-21090.html">iso-21090</a> provides extensions for strings allowing the conveying of language and translation extensions which may 
          be relevant in some environment</li>
		</ul>
	</div>
	<a name="content"> </a>
	<h3>Content</h3>
	<table class="lines">
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2">
				<b>Profiles</b>: </td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td>
				<a href="sdc-element.html">SDC-Element</a>
			</td>
			<td>Sets expectations for data elements registered or used as part of the structured data capture project</td>
		</tr>
	</table>
	<a name="language"> </a>
	<h3>Language and translations</h3>
	<p>
  In some environments, it may be necessary for a questionnaire to support multiple languages.  The rendering tool would select the appropriate
  language based on a configuration setting, or perhaps would display all available languages and the user would read the one they are familiar with.
  Systems MAY choose to provide support for identifying language and translations.  If they do, they SHALL do so using the generic language and
  translation extensions FHIR defines based on the ISO21090 data type specification:
  </p>
	<ul>
		<li>
			<a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extension-iso21090-st-language.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/iso21090-ST-language</a> allows the language of a 
			particular (or any other data type) to be identified</li>
		<li>
			<a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extension-iso21090-st-translation.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/iso21090-ST-translation</a> allows additional 
			repetitions in alternate languages to be communicated.  (The language for each translation would be communicated using the above #language extension)</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
  These extensions can be used on absolutely any string element on <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>, 
  <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}valueset.html">ValueSet</a> or any other resource.  The base string should be the primary language of the questionnaire.  It is what will be rendered by systems that do
  not support the translation extension or by systems whose language preference is other than one of the languages provided.
  </p>
	<p>
  The ISO 19763 specification permits declaring language on questionnaire titles, descriptions, display names for codes and many other strings.  It also supports
  capturing multiple variants of these strings with distinct languages.  These capabilities can be mirrored using the above extensions.
  </p>
	<a name="issues"> </a>
	<h3>Open Issues</h3>
	<p>
  While DataElement.stringency has been introduced, a formal set of rules defining exactly what level of &quot;tightness&quot; must exist for a stringency code, and
  in particular, what the rules are for data elements intended for use in auto-population/pre-population has not yet been defined.  For example, if a data element
  supports a subset of the answer codes that the question does, is that acceptable?  Must the question text be word-for-word identical?  Is it acceptable if the
  data element length is shorter than the permitted length for the question?  Is it acceptable if units of measure are not an exact match so long as conversion
  factors are known?
  </p>
	<p>
  Opinions on these and related questions of stringency are welcome.
  </p>
	<h3>Example List</h3>
	<table class="list">
		<tbody>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<a href="dataelement-sdc-profile-example.html">C-CDA-Gender</a>
				</td>
				<td>
					<a href="dataelement-sdc-profile-example.xml.html">XML</a>
				</td>
				<td>
					<a href="dataelement-sdc-profile-example.json.html">JSON</a>
				</td>
				<td>FHIR Gender with mapping to C-CDA</td>
			</tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<br/>
	<p>
  Additional examples of this profile can be found as contained resources within the following examples:
  </p>
	<table class="list">
		<tbody>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<a href="questionnaire-sdc-profile-example-ussg-fht.html">SDC-LOINC USSG Family History</a>
				</td>
				<td>
					<a href="questionnaire-sdc-profile-example-ussg-fht.xml.html">XML</a>
				</td>
				<td>
					<a href="questionnaire-sdc-profile-example-ussg-fht.json.html">JSON</a>
				</td>
				<td>LOINC US Surgeon General family history including data elements &amp; value sets.  Note: This example isn't strictly valid against SDC as data elements do not have 
        definitions and don't include mappings to SDC-approved specificaitons for auto-population</td>
			</tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p>
  Usage note: every effort has been made to ensure that the examples are correct and useful, but they are not a normative part of the specification.
  </p>
</div>