<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../../../schema/fhir-single.xsd">
  <p>
    The SDC specification provides an infrastructure to standardize the capture and expanded use of patient-level data collected within an EHR.
  </p>
  <p>
    This includes two components:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Support more sophisticated questionnaire/form use-cases such as those needed for research, oncology, pathology and other clinical domains.</li>
    <li>Support pre-population and auto-population of EHR data into forms/questionnaires for uses outside direct clinical care (patient safety, adverse event reporting, public 
      health reporting, etc.).</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    A third component - defining standards for the sharing of common data element definitions between registries to enable broader and more consistent data element use is 
    addressed in a <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdcde}}/sdcde.html">second companion implementation guide</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    This implementation guide is prepared as a U.S. Realm Specification on behalf of the 
    Structured Data Capture project - an effort under the <a href="http://www.healthit.gov/newsroom/about-onc">U.S. Office of the National Coordinator (ONC)</a>'s Standards and 
    Infrastructure (S &amp; I) Framework.  However, much of the content is likely to be useable in other jurisdictions.  The only portions of this specification that may be 
    problematic for use of this implementation guide in some jurisdictions are the bindings to terminologies such as SNOMED CT and RxNorm.  The workflow, constraints and 
    extensions used should all have broad applicability.
  </p>
  <a name="toc"/>
  <h3>Navigation</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide follows the FHIR pattern of being published as a web-based specification.  This
    allows easy navigation between the SDC-specific portion of the implementation guide and the resources,
    data types, value sets and other specification components leveraged from the FHIR core specification.  This
    approach also allows implementers to easily navigate to the information needed to perform a particular task.
  </p>
  <p>
    A <a href="toc.html">Table of Contents</a> page is provided that lists all of the pages defined as part of this implementation guide.  (Do be aware that some pages 
    have multiple tabs.)  A table of contents is also available for the full <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}toc.html">FHIR specification</a> if you really want to read 
    absolutely everything.  There's also an <a href="artifacts.html">Artifact index</a> that lists all artifacts defined within this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <p>
    Bread-crumb navigation is provided in the gray bar just below the menu at the top of each page, allowing
    easy navigation back to the main SDC page.
  </p>
  <p>This implementation guide has a number of sections:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="#fhir">Understanding FHIR</a> should be read by those who are not familiar with FHIR as a pre-requisite to reading the rest of the implementation guide</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#background">Background</a> provides links to background and implementation information including security guidelines, the SDC wiki and the use-cases driving the 
      implementation guide</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#workflow">Workflow</a> describes the primary workflow associated with the SDC implementation guide</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#capabilitystatement">Capability Statements</a> describes the different roles systems wishing to conform to this implementation guide can take on and summarizes how 
        those roles interact.</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#resources">Resources</a> describes the resources used as part of this implementation guide, including profiles placed on those resources to constrain and 
        extend their capabilities.</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#population">Pre-population Service</a> describes in detail how the pre-population mechanism is intended to work</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#ip">Intellectual Property Considerations</a> provides information about intellectual property referenced by this implementation guide</li>
  </ul>
  <br/>
  <a name="fhir"> </a>
  <h3>Understanding FHIR</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide is based on the HL7 <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}index.html">FHIR</a> standard.  It uses terminology, notations and design principles that are
    specific to FHIR.  Before reading this implementation guide, it's important to be familiar with some of the basic principles of FHIR as well 
    as general guidance on how to read FHIR specifications.  Readers who are unfamiliar with FHIR are encouraged to read (or at least skim) the following 
    prior to reading the rest of this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview.html">FHIR overview</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview-dev.html">Developer's introduction</a>
    </li>
    <li>(or <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview-clinical.html">Clinical introduction</a>)</li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}datatypes.html">FHIR data types</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}terminologies.html">Using codes</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}references.html">References between resources</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}formats.html">How to read resource &amp; profile definitions</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}resource.html">Base resource</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}http.html">RESTful operations</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}search.html">Search</a>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Feel free to explore other aspects of the FHIR specification that you feel may be relevant or of interest.
  </p>
  <a name="background"> </a>
  <h3>Background</h3>
  <p>
    The following links provide additional context for the SDC specification.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-intro.html">Introduction</a> - How this project came to be and what it is trying to achieve</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-security.html">Security</a> - Security and privacy rules and considerations</li>
    <li>
      <a href="http://wiki.siframework.org/Structured+Data+Capture+Initiative">Project wiki containing development materials and discussions (for additional background)</a>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <a name="workflow"> </a>
  <h3>Workflows</h3>
  <p>
    There are two primary workflows that fall within the scope of the SDC implementation guide - form creation/curation and form filling.
  </p>
  <a name="fig1"> </a>
  <img alt="Diagram showing interaction between Form Designer, Form Manager and Data Element Registry" src="sdc-form-curation.png"/>
  <p>
    <b>Figure 1: Form Curation Workflow</b>
  </p>
  <p>
    In form curation, the Form Designer interacts with both the Form Manager and the Data Element Registry to create, edit and update forms,
    including identifying and defining associated terminologies and data elements.  This is an iterative process where an initial version is
    created and then subsequently updated and maintained, eventually changing status to <i>active</i> and later <i>retired</i>.
  </p>
  <p/>
  <p>
    The more significant (and complex) workflow in SDC is to complete (and potentially submit) a completed questionnaire response.
  </p>
  <a name="fig2"> </a>
  <img alt="Generic Workflow" src="sdc-generic-workflow.png"/>
  <p>
    <b>Figure 2: Form Filling Workflow</b>
  </p>
  <p>
    <i>
      <b>Note</b>: The diagram depicts the optional storage of the completed form by the EHR. This can occur when the EHR stores a copy of 
      the form as they send it to the External Data Repository or by the external data repository returning a copy of the form to 
      the sender who can store an internal version of the form.
    </i>
  </p>
  <p>The driver of this workflow is the
    <a href="sdc-form-filler.html">Form Filler</a> system.  It retrieves a form (Questionnaire) from the
    <a href="sdc-form-manager.html">Form Manager</a>.  It may also request that the Form Manager generate an initial QuestionnaireResponse,
    potentially partially populated with information known by the Form Manager or supplied by the Form Filler.  The Form Filler could generate the
    QuestionnaireResponse itself without the assistance of the Form Manager and in either case could partially fill in the response based on information
    known by the form filler.
  </p>
  <p>
    When as much of the questionnaire response as possible has been filled in by automated means, the form is displayed to
    an end-user who reviews and edits the automatically populated content as well as completing those portions of the form that were not populated
    automatically.  In some cases, the form may be stored locally or using a <a href="sdc-form-response-manager.html">Form Response Manager</a> to allow a user to 
    stop and resume editing at a later point.  
  </p>
  <p>
    The Form Filler (possibly with help from the Form Manager) is responsible for verifying that a completed form is actually
    complete and valid against the corresponding Questionnaire.  Once valid, the form filler submits the form to one or more target repositories 
    (<a href="sdc-form-receiver.html">Form Receiver</a> allows the completed form to be subsequently retrieved,
    <a href="sdc-form-archiver.html">Form Archiver</a> does not) and/or stores the completed form itself.  (Note - Form Receivers may perform validation on forms
    prior to consumption, Form Archivers typically will not.)
  </p>
  <p>
    The pre-population process (done by the Form Manager) and the auto-population process (done by the Form Filler itself) can be done by
    a variety of means.  If using data elements referenced directly within the questionnaire or mapped via <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}conceptmap.html">ConceptMap</a>,
    those may need to be retrieved from a <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdcde}}/sdc-de-registry.html"> Data Element Registry</a> in order to look
    up what mappings the data element has to other resources.
  </p>
  <h3>SDC Specification</h3>
  <p>The following sections describe the artifacts that set expectations for systems wishing to be conformant to the FHIR SDC implementation guide.</p>
  <a name="capabilitystatement"> </a>
  <h4>Capability Statements</h4>
  <p>
    FHIR Capability statements define the expectations for particular system "roles" within an SDC environment.  To be considered SDC-conformant, a system 
    must adhere to the requirements defined by at least one of these statements.  Some systems might choose to comply with more than one.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-form-designer.html">SDC Form Designer</a> - System responsible for creating and editing form designs</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-form-filler.html">SDC Form Filler</a> - System responsible for capturing user form input to produce partially or fully completed forms</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-form-manager.html">SDC Form Manager</a> - Repository for form definitions.  May also perform pre-population</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-form-response-manager.html">SDC Form Response Manager</a> - Searchable repository for storage and retrieval of completed and partially completed forms.</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-form-receiver.html">SDC Form Receiver</a> - Write-only destination to which forms are sent for processing</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-form-archiver.html">SDC Form Archiver</a> - Write-only system responsible for archiving completed forms as well as works in progress</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    In addition to the above, there's another relevant role:<br/>
    When looking up data elements, the <i>SDC Form Designer</i> will communicate use of the <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdcde}}/sdc-de-registry">SDC Data Element 
    Registry</a>, which is defined in the <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdcde}}/sdcde.html">SDC Data Element Exchange</a> implementation guide.
  </p>
  <p>
    A summary of how these roles interact can be seen in <a href="#fig1">Figure 1</a> and <a href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> above.
  </p>
  <a name="resources"> </a>
  <h4>Resources</h4>
  <p>
    This implementation guide defines profiles on several resources.  Implementations are expected to be conformant with these profiles in order
    to be conformant with this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>Resource</th>
        <th>SDC Profile</th>
        <th>Purpose</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">DataElement</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdc-dataelement.html">SDC Data Element (DE) Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define data elements that can be referenced in questionnaires and can be used to auto-populate form data</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdc-questionnaire.html">SDC Questionnaire Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define form definitions that may be downloaded for manual and/or automatic population</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdc-questionnaireresponse.html">SDC Questionnaire Response Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to share instance data captured using questionnaire forms</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}valueset.html">ValueSet</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdc-valueset.html">SDC Value Set Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define collections of allowed values for data elements and for questions in questionnaires</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}codesystem.html">CodeSystem</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdc-codesystem.html">SDC Code System Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define allowed values for data elements and for questions in questionnaires</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>
    Additional resources such as <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}patient.html">Patient</a>, <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}practitioner.html">Practitioner</a>, 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}binary.html">Binary</a>, <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}conceptmap.html">ConceptMap</a>, 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}provenance.html">Provenance</a>, <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> and others are also 
    likely to be used in SDC solutions, though no SDC-specific profiles have been created for them.    
    <!-- Todo: decide how explicit the list of relevant sections needs to be -->
  </p>
  <p>
    For the purposes of this implementation guide, "must support" shall be interpreted as follows:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Conformant systems SHALL be capable of sending and receiving the data element</li>
    <li>When a system persists a resource instance, all "must support" elements SHALL be persisted and retrieved with other elements</li>
    <li>Where an element affects the display or validation of a Questionnaire and a system performs either or both of those operations, the behavior established by the value 
      of the element SHALL be performed</li>
  </ul>
  <a name="population"> </a>
  <h4>Pre-population service</h4>
  <p>
    The <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resource defines a set of custom operations to support generation of completed questionnaires,
    possibly automatically filling in some of the answers using existing system information.  This could be information passed to the system on which the operation is 
    invoked (as a CDA document, FHIR bundle or other recognized source) or using data the system already has locally. The three operations are as follows:
  </p>
  <table cellpadding="5">
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>Operation</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire-operations.html#populate">populate</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          This operation supports generating a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> instance based on a specified
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>.  If matching data is available for any of the questions and the server supports 
          the pre-population capability, the answers for those questions will be filled in the QuestionnaireResponse instance.
        </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire-operations.html#populatehtml">populatehtml</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          This operation produces an HTML web page as a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}binary.html">Binary</a> instance.  The HTML page provides an interactive rendering
          of the form, using html-based controls to capture user inputs and scripting languages to support form validation and submission to the server that
          generated the form and/or the recipient(s) designated by the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>.  If matching data is available 
          for any of the questions and the server supports the pre-population capability, the form will initially render with the answers for those questions filled in.
        </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire-operations.html#populatelink">populatelink</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          This operation returns a URL leading to an web page with an interactive rendering of the form that allows a user navigating to the link with a browser to
          complete and submit a response to the questionnaire.  The response will be transmitted to the server generating the link, hosting the form and/or as
          designated as part of the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> itself.  If matching data is available 
          for any of the questions and the server supports the pre-population capability, the form will initially render with the answers for those questions filled in.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>
    For SDC purposes, server systems claiming to support roles that require support for the <code>populate</code>, <code>populatehtml</code> or <code>populatelink</code>
    operations (<a href="sdc-form-manager.html">SDC Form Manager</a>) SHALL, at minimum:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Handle the input parameters <code>identifier</code>, <code>questionnaire</code>, <code>questionnaireRef</code>, <code>subject</code> and <code>content</code>
    </li>
    <li>Support <code>content</code> parameters consisting of a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}http.html#binary">Binary</a> resource containing a C-CDA* document</li>
    <li>Populate the returned <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> instance or rendered form for all questions referencing
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">DataElements</a> that are mapped to C-CDA content</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Similarly, client systems claiming to support the <code>populate</code>, <code>populatehtml</code> and/or <code>populatelink</code> operations
    (<a href="sdc-form-filler.html">SDC Form Filler</a>) SHALL, at a minimum:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Be capable of invoking the operation(s) on a selected questionnaire both directly (<code>Questionnaire/[identifier]/$populate</code>)
      as well as indirectly either by <code>identifier</code> or <code>questionnaire</code>
    </li>
    <li>Support passing a single C-CDA* document as a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}http.html#binary">Binary</a> resource using the <code>content</code> parameter</li>
    <li>Be able to accept an incoming partially-populated <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> and render it as if they had retrieved a saved partially-completed <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a></li>
    <li> It is the responsibility of the <a href="sdc-form-filler.html">SDC Form Filler</a> to ensure the form is valid after a human has reviewed and edited the form.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    * While C-CDA is the focus for compliance with this release of the SDC specification, systems are encouraged to support additional formats.  Candidates
    for mandatory support in future versions of this implementation guide include the
    <a href="http://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public/wg/ca/CDAR2_IG_CDP1_R1_D1_2015MAY%20V10%200%205-11-2015%20clean.pdf">Clinical Documents for Payers - SET 1</a> (CPD1)
    and 
    <a href="http://www.ihe.net/Technical_Framework/upload/IHE_QRPH_Suppl_PRPH_Ca_Rev2-1_2011-09-02.pdf"> Physician Reporting to a Public Health Repository</a>
    specifications.  Passing a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}bundle.html">Bundle</a> of FHIR resources is also an option that has been used by at least some implementers.
  </p>
  <p>
    Systems supporting one or more of the populate operations are encouraged to support using the 
    <code>definition</code> element to trace the linkage from Questionniare question to DataElement or <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}structuredefinition.html">StructureDefinition</a> element to 
    support mapping.  As well, systems may also choose to support the use of the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extension-questionnaire-demap.html">deMap</a> extension to 
    support maintaining of question &lt;-&gt; data element links outside the questionnaire itself.  If using this approach, the 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}conceptmap.html">ConceptMap</a>.<code>sourceUri</code> equal to the full resource id of the Questionnaire and
    a <code>targetUri</code> of the base URL for the DataElement end-point of the server to which data elements will be mapped.  The 
    <code>ConceptMap.element.code</code> and <code>ConceptMap.element.map.code</code> will correspond to the question linkId and the data element
    local id, respectively.  Support for alternative mechanisms including ConceptMaps directly from Questionnaire questions to data sources, Questionnaire
    extensions providing mappings direct to data sources or use of Questionnaire.group.question.concept are all acceptable mechanisms for executing <code>populate</code>
    functionality.  More formal conversion between existing data sources and Questionnaires can be represented using 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}structuremap.html">StructureMap</a> which allows the definition of fully computable mappings between a given source structure and 
    target structure where either (or even both) structures can be a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponses</a>.  The
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extension-questionnaire-sourcestructuremap.html">questionnaire-sourceStructureMap</a> extension allows a Questionnaire to point to a
    StructureMap that can be used to populate it.  The source structure mapped from could be a FHIR structure, but could also be any other data structure, including CDA
    documents.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>IMPORTANT CONSIDERATIONS FOR MAPPING:</b>
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Mapping can be dangerous because it can lead to the sharing of incorrect data or, occasionally, the failure to share correct data.  For this reason, it is essential that
      human users be given the opportunity to review questionnaire responses that have been populated by automated means.
    </li>
    <li>
      Even with this precaution, care should be taken when performing data mappings, including:
      <ul>
        <li>Be aware that the risk of incorrect mapping occurring can be significantly higher when mapping complex questionnaires and/or complex data structures and 
          especially high when mapping both.</li>
        <li>The degree of risk is implementation dependent (type of data, type of questionnaire, type of source, mapping mechanism, type of user, etc.)</li>
        <li>Both mappings and the implementation of those mappings should be carefully verified and in some situations should be subject to certification or external 
          verification</li>
        <li>Mapping to data elements not specifically defined for use in the context of a particular questionnaire or set of questionnaires (i.e. with a defined 
          context) magnifies the risk of erroneous population.  Defining data elements for "general purpose" mapping use carries a significant risk of inappropriate 
          data population, particularly for complex structures.</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>
      Not all <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">DataElements</a> will be appropriate or safe to reference in a Questionnaire.  It is important that the definition
      associated with the data element fully reflects the context of the question in the questionnaire.  For example, "gender" would not be a safe data element
      because it would not be clear whether the gender was that of the patient or a fetus of the patient.  It must be clear from the data element definition
      exactly what piece of information should be extracted from a source system, C-CDA document or other data source.
    </li>
    <li>
      Mapping to C-CDA, where applicable, should be constrained and specific (e.g. for particular demographic sections) rather than making it open and generic.  These mappings 
      should be per ONC's recommendations. Mapping to C-CDA is one of many options, not the only one.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <a name="terminologyops"> </a>
  <h3>Terminology Operations</h3>
  <p>
    In addition to the QuestionnaireResponse population operations, it will be useful for Form Filler and Form Manager systems to support some of FHIR's
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}terminology-service.html">terminology service</a> capabilities - specifically the 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}operation-valueset-expand.html">Valueset Expand</a> and 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}operation-valueset-validate-code.html">Validate code</a>
    operations.
  </p>
  <a name="ip"> </a>
  <h3>Intellectual Property Considerations</h3>
  <p>
    While this implementation guide and the underlying FHIR are licensed as public domain, this guide mandates the use of terminologies including LOINC, SNOMED CT and
    RxNorm which have more restrictive licensing requirements.  Implementers should make themselves familiar with licensing and any other constraints of terminologies,
    questionnaires, data elements and other components used as part of their implementation process.  In some cases, licensing requirements may limit the systems
    that data captured using this implementation guide may be shared with.
  </p>
</div>