<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>
    This provides a list of changes to the SDC specification since its initial release
  </p>
  <p>
      <b>2017-03-20 v2.0 - SDC R2 (STU) Official Publication</b> based on FHIR R3 (STU)
  </p>
  <ul>
      <li>Updated to reflect changes to the Questionnaire, QuestionnaireResponse and ValueSet resources including alignment of data elements and search criteria.  Significant changes include:
      <ul>
            <li>Questionnaire.item.linkId is now mandatory on all elements (including display items)</li>
            <li>Additional metadata elements have been added to Questionnaire and a few elements have been renamed</li>
            <li>The deReference extension has been replaced by Questionnaire.item.definition</li>
            <li>Sort order of elements has shifted in all resources to better align with other definitional resources</li>
         </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Revamped the look &amp; feel of the profiles to make them easier to navigate and place descriptive text "in context" and changed the menu to make it easier to access IG content</li>
      <li>Renamed the sdc-response profile to sdc-questionnaireresponse and sdc-element to sdc-dataelement to be clearer and avoid confusion</li>
      <li>Renamed the conformance resources to no longer start with "conformance-" to avoid unnecessary redundancy</li>
      <li>Clarified and revamped the Form Archiver and Form Receiver to more closely align with the equivalent IHE roles.  Specifically, clarified that archiver is write-only.  Changed receiver from exposing QuestionnaireResponses as read-write to only consuming responses via a new operation - process-response</li>
      <li>Introduced a new capability statement called SDC Form Response Manager that builds on SDC Form Manager to provide read/write support for QuestionnaireResponses.</li>
      <li>Added additional optional populate and terminology operations to the Form Filler and Form Manager</li>
      <li>Changed DataElement.element to 1..* instead of 1..1 to support the use of Questionnaires with complex data types (e.g. addresses)</li>
      <li>Changed DataElement.element.definition from 1..1 to 0..1</li>
      <li>Added a rule that the reference from a Questionnaire to a QuestionnaireResponse must be version-specific</li>
      <li>Various changes to the documentation text to improve clarity and add implementation guidance</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
      <b>2016-08-11 v1.6 - SDC R2 (STU) Ballot Candidate</b> based on FHIR R3 (STU) ballot candidate
  </p>
  <ul>
      <li>Updated to reflect changes to the Questionnaire, QuestionnaireResponse and ValueSet resources including alignment of data elements and search criteria.  Significant changes include:
      <ul>
            <li>Migrated the previous questionnaire-enableWhen, questionnaire-defaultValue (became initialValue), questionnaire-label (became prefix), questionnaire-readOnly, 
          questionnaire-maxLength and questionnaire-category (now 0..*) extensions to be part of the Questionnaire resource's core elements</li>
            <li>Refactored Questionnaire to allow both groups and questions to be treated as "items" and introduced the notion of "text" items.  This allows for a number of Questionnaire
          designs to be simplified, allows new capabilities and altered which extensions were needed. (questionnaire-questionControl -&gt; 
          questionnaire-itemControl, and questionnaire-instruction, -security, -help, -tooltip, -trailing,
          -units, -lowRangeLabel and -highRangeLabel all become items of type "text" with a corresponding questionnaire-itemControl code to differentiate them)</li>
            <li>Added support for additional data types for Questionnaire.item.options</li>
            <li>Questionnaire now has a mandatory "url" to capture the canonical URL for the Questionnaire</li>
         </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Added support for two new "populate" operations - populatehtml and populatelink operations</li>
      <li>Added a profile for the new CodeSystem resource which has now been split out from
      ValueSet.  The new profile reflects the constraints and extensions that have been moved over from the SDC Valueset profile</li>
      <li>In the SDC Questionnaire profile, Item.required and Item.repeats are no longer 1..1, so they can be omitted if their value is the default 
      - false</li>
      <li>Added references to a number of new extensions:
      <ul>
            <li>questionnaire-supportLink - allows linking a questionnaire item to a web page, PDF or other artifact that gives supporting information</li>
            <li>questionnaire-sourceStructureMap - allows linking a questionnaire to a 
          StructureMap that provides a computable mapping between a data source and QuestionnaireResponses for that Questionnaire</li>
            <li>questionnaire-usageMode - allows flagging a questionnaire item to indicate whether it should be
          displayed only when capturing data, when displaying a completed questionnaire or both</li>
            <li>questionnaire-studyProtocolIdentifier - allows linking a Questionnaire to the study protocol it's associated with</li>
            <li>questionnaire-allowedProfile - allows questions of type Reference to identify a FHIR profile that must be satisfied by any referenced resource</li>
            <li>questionnaire-ordinalValue - allows capturing a numeric value associated with a code allowed as the answer to a question</li>
            <li>questionnaire-optionPrefix - allows capturing the label (e.g. "(a)", "(ii)", etc.) for an option in a list of options for a question</li>
            <li>questionnaire-unit - allows capturing the computable units associated with a question whose answer is asimple decimal or integer</li>
            <li>questionnaire-referenceFilter - allows specifying a query to use when looking up allowed answers for a question of type Reference</li>
         </ul>
      </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
      <b>2015-10-24 v1.0 - SDC R2 (DSTU) Official Publication</b> based on FHIR R2 (DSTU) publication
  </p>
  <ul>
      <li>First official release</li>
  </ul>
</div>
