<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	  <a name="language">  </a>
	  <h3 class="self-link-parent">
      <span class="sectioncount">{{site.data.pages[page.path].label}}.1</span> Language and translations <a title="link to here"
         class="self-link"
         href="{{page.path}}#language">
         <img src="assets/images/link.svg"
              class="self-link"
              width="20"
              height="20"/>
      </a>
   </h3>
	  <p>
  In some environments, it may be necessary for a questionnaire to support multiple languages.  The rendering tool would select the appropriate
  language based on a configuration setting, or perhaps would display all available languages and the user would read the one they are familiar with.
  Systems MAY choose to provide support for identifying language and translations.  If they do, they SHALL do so using the generic 
  translation extension FHIR defines: <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extension-translation.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/translation</a>
  </p>
	  <p>
  These extensions can be used on absolutely any string element on <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>, 
  <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}valueset.html">ValueSet</a> or any other resource.  The base string should be the primary language of the questionnaire.  It is what will be rendered by systems that do
  not support the translation extension or by systems whose language preference is other than one of the languages provided.
  </p>
	  <p>
  The ISO 19763 specification permits declaring language on questionnaire titles, descriptions, display names for codes and many other strings.  It also supports
  capturing multiple variants of these strings with distinct languages.  These capabilities can be mirrored using the above extensions.
  </p>
	  <a name="issues">  </a>
	  <h3 class="self-link-parent">
      <span class="sectioncount">{{site.data.pages[page.path].label}}.2</span> Open Issues <a title="link to here" class="self-link" href="{{page.path}}#issues">
         <img src="assets/images/link.svg"
              class="self-link"
              width="20"
              height="20"/>
      </a>
   </h3>
	  <p>
  While DataElement.stringency has been introduced, a formal set of rules defining exactly what level of "tightness" must exist for a stringency code, and
  in particular, what the rules are for data elements intended for use in auto-population/pre-population has not yet been defined.  For example, if a data element
  supports a subset of the answer codes that the question does, is that acceptable?  Must the question text be word-for-word identical?  Is it acceptable if the
  data element length is shorter than the permitted length for the question?  Is it acceptable if units of measure are not an exact match so long as conversion
  factors are known?
  </p>
	  <p>
  Opinions on these and related questions of stringency are welcome.
  </p>
</div>
