<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<p>
The MeasureReport resource represents the results of calculating a measure for a specific subject or group of subjects. The <code>$evaluate</code> operation of the <a href="measure.html">Measure</a> resource is defined to return a MeasureReport. The resource can represent three different levels of report: individual, subject-list, and summary.
</p>

<p>
The resource draws requirements from the HL7 CDA R2 Implementation Guide: Quality Reporting Document Architecture - Category 1 (QRDA I) Release 1 STU5.3 (US Realm) and the HL7 Implementation Guide for CDA Release 2: Quality Reporting Document Architecture - Category III (QRDA III), Release 1 implementation guides.
</p>

<p>An <em>individual</em> MeasureReport contains information about a specific subject and typically includes references to the relevant data used to generate the report. A <em>subject-list</em> MeasureReport reports on a list of subjects and provides a List resource that contains references to individual-level reports for each subject being reported. A <em>summary</em> MeasureReport reports on a group of subjects and contains population counts and the calculated score as defined by the Measure. Finally, <em>data-collection</em> reports are used to communicate the data of interest, so no scoring or other calculated information is expected.</p>

<p>For a detailed discussion of how to use the Measure and MeasureReport resources, refer to the <a href="clinicalreasoning-quality-reporting.html">Quality Reporting</a> topic.</p>

</div>

<a name="stu"></a>


<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>Although the MeasureReport is conceptually an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, there is enough specific information required to support the quality reporting use case to warrant a separate resource.</p>

<p>The resource is differentiated from a general-purpose query result because it communicates specific information related to quality measurement evaluation that would be difficult to convey generally without imposing some other structure on top of the general results.</p>
</div>


<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
