<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
<i>This resource is a draft proposal for use as part of an approach to Clinical Quality within FHIR, and is documented as part of the <a href="cqif/cqif.html">Clinical Quality Framework (CQF) Implementation Guide</a>.</i>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
</p>

<p>
 The _evaluate_ operation of the Measure resource is defined to return a MeasureReport. The resource is capable of representing three different levels of report: patient-level, patient-list, and summary.

The resource is based on the HL7 CDA R2 Implementation Guide: Quality Reporting Document Architecture - Category 1 (QRDA I) DSTU Release 3 (US Realm) and the HL7 Implementation Guide for CDA Release 2: Quality Reporting Document Architecture - Category III (QRDA III), DSTU Release 1 implementation guides.
</p>

<p>Note that this resource is a special case of the more general notion of a query evaluation result. However, because the general case requires the ability to represent arbitrary content, this resource uses a simple indicator structure to describe population sizes for each population type defined in the measure. The intent is to be able to represent the more general case as well, either by generalizing this resource, or by making this structure a profile of a more general resource, and we are actively seeking comments about what approaches might be taken to achieve that aim.</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>Although the MeasureReport is conceptually an <a href="observation">Observation</a>, there is enough specific information required to support the quality reporting use case to warrant a separate resource.</p>

<p>The resource is differentiated from a general purpose query result because it communicates specific information related to quality measurement evaluation that would be difficult to convey generally without imposing some other structure on top of the general results.</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
