<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"></a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p> 
		Appointment resources are used to provide information about 
		a planned meeting that may be in the future or past.  They may be for a single meeting or
		for a series of repeating visits.  Examples include a scheduled surgery, a follow-up for a
		clinical visit, a scheduled conference call between clinicians to discuss a case, the reservation
		of a piece of diagnostic equipment for a particular use, etc.  The visit scheduled by an appointment
		may be in person or remote (by phone, video conference, etc.)  All that matters is that the time and
		usage of one or more individuals, locations and/or pieces of equipment is being fully or partially
		reserved for a designated period of time.
		</p>
		<p>
		This definition takes the concepts of appointments in a clinical setting and also extends
		them to be relevant in the community healthcare space, and also ease exposure to other
		appointment / calendar standards widely used outside of Healthcare.
		</p>
		<a name="basic-workflow"></a>
		<h3>The basic workflow to create an appointment</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<b>Making the Appointment Request</b>
				<p>
					When an appointment is required, a requester creates new Appointment resource with the Appointment.status="proposed".<br/>
					All included participants (optional or mandatory) should have the status="needs-action" to allow filtering and displaying
					appointments to user-participants for accepting or rejecting new and updated requests. Based on internal system business rules,
					certain statuses may be automatically updated, for example: "reject because the requested participant is on vacation" or 
					"this type of user is not allowed to request those specific appointments".
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<b>Replying to the request</b>
				<p>
					The reply process is simply performed by the person/system handling the requests updating
					the participant statuses as needed. If there are multiple systems involved, then these
					will create AppointmentResponse entries with the desired statuses.
				</p>
				<p>
					Once all participants have their participation status created/updated
					(and the main system marking the appointment participant records with the AppointmentResponse
					statuses) then the overall status of the Appointment is updated.
				</p>
				<p>
					To "invalidate" an appointment response it should have the status changed to entered-in-error,
					or simply delete the resource.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>

		<a name="recurring"></a>
		<h3>Recurring Appointments</h3>
		<p>
			When a recurring appointment is requested, the participant may choose to respond to each individual
			occurrence, in which case <code>AppointmentResponse.recurring</code> should be <code>false</code>. If the participant chooses
			to respond the same way for all occurrences, they may instead use a single AppointmentResponse with
			recurring set to <code>true</code>. These may be combined as the participant chooses. For example, they may
			accept all occurrences of a series (recurring = true), but then send a decline for a specific 
			occurrence (recurring = false).<br/>
			For more general information on recurring appointments, refer to the <a href="appointment.html#recurring">appointment page</a>.
		</p>
	</div>
</div>
