<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

    <h2>Notes:</h2>
    <ul>
        <li>Timezones and Recurring Appointments</li>
        <p>Recurring appointments need to have the timezone in which the values were entered in defined.
				Knowing that the start time was at 9:00:00Z+10 does not mean that the same time in 2 weeks is actually the same. 
        </p>
			<p>
				As if this was a time in Brisbane Australia, this time will be the same (in respect to its offset from UTC),
				however if this was for Melbourne Australia, during the daylight savings period of time Melbourne becomes +11.
				So without the additional information as to which timezone it was created in, scheduling a 9am appoitment every
				Wednesday would not be possible.
			</p>
			<li>Placer/Filler (HL7 v2)</li>
			<p>
				The appointment information is effectively the same between the filler and placer, and given the nature of the
				fhir resource, there is only a single resource for both purposes. The Placer is the actor that performs the
				PUT or POST operation on the resource, and the filler is the actor that receives these resource messages and
				processes the information and makes a decision if the appointment can be used.
				<em>Brian: Does this seem right that the filler and placer are applied in this way?</em>
			</p>
			<li>Interaction with other Standards</li>
			<p>
				The strong desire is that implementers of this resource should consider providing this resource
				in the iCalendar format as an alternative representation. Many 3rd party applications and component providers 
				have parsers and user interface controls to display this information.
				This may lower the entry point to integrate outside the health-care specific applications, and into the 
				consumer space. This would permit the easier creation of a mobile application that creates appointments
				in the devices native calendar.<br/>
				The iCalendar specification can be found at <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2445.txt">http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2445.txt</a>.
			</p>
    </ul>
</div>
