<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Lists the current status or changes to an inventory.
The current status of inventory is presented as the quantity of items, grouped in listings, where a listing can be the items in a location, or with a given status. This is a 'snapshot' of the current inventory.
<br/>
The changes to an inventory are represented as the additions (incoming) or substractions (consumptions or outgoing) of items to an inventory listing. This is often used when there is a need to determine the increment/decrement in stock, and there is a need to only transmit the difference, without the need to update the entire snapshot.
<br/>
The inventory status can be available as a response to a request, or can be done ad-hoc (e.g. report a consumption for consignment stock) or scheduled (e.g. recount the stock every 6 months).


<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
</p>
</div>


<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The InventoryReport resource is associated with consumable items - typically resources like Medication, Devices.
Inventory management is related to SupplyRequest and SupplyDelivery, which may be associated with an increase or decrease of inventory.
</p>

<p>
xxDispense: The InventoryReport resource can also be used to indicate consumption of an item. When a Dispense event occurs, there is a depletion in stock. 
InventoryReport does not overlap with Dispense: Dispense carries the 'clinical' meaning that a product has been assigned to a patient. The InventoryReport captures the logistic aspect.
For example (see examples)
<ul>
<li>when a Medication is dispensed to a patient, the use of a InventoryReport is not needed</li>
<li>when a Medication is dropped and afterwards disposed of, and therefore not used by any patient, the InventoryReport can captures this and inform the inventory management system about the subtraction of that item. </li>
<li>when there is a need to inform, for inventory reasons, the items that have been taken from stock, this can be done with an InventoryReport.</li>
</ul>


</p>
</div>


<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
