<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<a name="search_parameters"> </a>
	<h4>Search Parameters</h4>
<p>
The supported search parameters on the DAF List profiles are can be accessed at <a href="conformance-daf-query-requestor.html">DAF Requestor conformance expectations</a> and <a href="conformance-daf-query-responder.html">DAF Responder conformance expectations</a>.
</p>

	<a name="example_usage_scenarios"> </a>
	<h4>Example Usage Scenarios</h4>

<p>
The following are example usage scenarios for the DAF List profile:
</p>
<ul>
	<li>Query for current problem list, medication list or allergy list for a patient</li>
</ul>

	<a name="profiles_specific_implementation_guidance"> </a>
	<h4>Profile specific implementation guidance</h4>

<p>
Implementers need to be mindful of the following during their implementation
</p>
<ul>
	<p><b>Querying Lists vs Clinical Resources:</b> DAF profiles of the List resource should be used by DAF Requestors to query for data that is curated as a list by the DAF Responder.
	 The following are the curated lists that will be used in the context of DAF:</p>
	 <ul>
	    <li>Active Medications List</li>
		<li>Active Problems List</li>
		<li>Active Allergies List</li>
		<li>List of relevant Laboratory Result values</li>
		<li>List of Immunizations</li>
		<li>List of Encounters</li>
	 </ul>
	 <p>DAF Requestors are expected to query the actual Clinical Resources such as Condition, Medication, AllergyIntolerance when they would like to get back a set of resources meeting a specific search criteria.(For example, query for all problems documented for a patient). In contrast, queries on List resources are supposed to be used only when the DAF Requestor expects a curated list to be returned by the DAF Responder. In all cases the List returned is packaged as part of a <a href="bundle.html">Bundle</a> similar to other search results.</p>
	 
	 <p>See<a href="daf.html"> DAF FHIR IG</a> for implementation guidance common to all profiles.</p>
</ul>

</div>