<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

[%stu-note dstu%]
This resource can represent different stages of supply delivery. After a request to create two separate resources to address dispatch vs. reception, current discussion concluded that one resource with multiple, extensible stages provided a better approach to support the variety of needs to document the different steps.
HL7 seeks specific feedback on the implementability of one resource type with multiple stages (likely represented in a future IG with specific profiles to determine specific attributes/value sets applicable to each stage - see <a href="valueset-supplydelivery-stage.html">valueset-supplydelivery-stage</a>), or whether two (or more) resource types would be more adequate.
[%end-note%]


<p><strong>This resource is an <em>event</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.   It is the intent of the Orders and Observation Workgroup to align this resource with  the workflow pattern for <a href="workflow.html#event"><em>event</em> resources</a>.</strong></p>
<p>
The SupplyDelivery is used to document the dispatch (e.g., time of dispatch, content) and/or receipt (e.g., time or receipt, content) of, e.g., supplies, people, devices, patients, biologically derived products.
This includes delivery of supplies within or across institution such as transport a set of supplies from materials management to a service unit, e.g., nurse station, or biologically derived products from the supplier to the hospital.
This resource does not include the provisioning of transportation services.  The SupplyDelivery does not imply that this supply has already been dispensed to the that patient or person, while it could be reserved for that patient or person. 
Those associations are done in dedicated resources such as the MedicationDispense and DeviceDispense.
</p>
<p>Sample use cases include:</p> 
<ul>
<li>Movement of bulk supplies between locations</li>
<li>Receipt of bulk supplies</li> 
<li>Rejection of a delivery due to item condition</li>
<li>Noting the loss of a delivery due to transportation failure</li>
</ul>
<p>The SupplyDelivery enables the documentation of the one or more relevant stages, such as dispatch of and reception of a shipment.  One may opt to document multiple stages given a particular use case, e.g., shipments of biologically derived products in a tightly controlled process, or only use a singular stage to summarize the shipment.  Examples would include the dispatch and reception stages that in certain use cases need to be documented separately using two or more instances.</p>

</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The <a href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/oo-incubator/StructureDefinition-DeviceDispense.html">DeviceDispense</a> and <a href="medicationdispense.html">MedicationDispense</a> resources are used to associate the device or medication with the specific patient for their use, while <a href="supplydelivery.html">SupplyDelivery</a> is solely focused on location and movement 
where the targeted patient or other person (e.g., devices used by a clinician), if included, are for delivery context only.</p>

<p>
To determine the purchase date, a search of <a href="devicerequest.html">DeviceRequest</a>, <a href="supplyrequest.html">SupplyRequest</a>, DeviceDispense, or SupplyDelivery as defined in an implementation guide can be done, as the context of the use case actually determines which date of either resource is considered the purchase date.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="transport.html">Transport</a> resource documents the movement of the supplies, people, patients, etc. between dispatch and receipt including, e.g., time of movement, transporter, average temperature during transport.
</p>
</div>

</div>
