<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>

<a name="dstu"></a>
<blockquote class="stu-note">
    <p>
        <b>STU Note:</b> The Public Health work group wants to draw the attention of reviewers and implementers to the following issues for feedback:
	</p>
    <ol>
        <li>ImmunizationRecommendation.recommendation is allowed to repeat, meaning that multiple recommendations for a given patient can be contained in a single resouce. This ensures that if the recommendations are interrelated, they are available in the same resource (for example, multiple doses of the same vaccine are recommended at different points in the future). Is the preference to allow repetitions of the recommendation backbone element or should the core resource constrain the cardinality to 1..1?</li>
		<li>The ImmunizationRecommendation resource can be thought of as a specialization of a generic recommendation (for a medication or a procedure, etc). Is it better to have a single generic recommendation resource that is then profiled for use in specific domains (immunization recommendation, imaging recommendation, etc) or individual, specific resources for each domain which require less profiling and may be easier for domain implementers to understand?</li>
		<li>Should the ImmunizationEvaluation resource be harmonized with the CDS Hooks project?</li>
		</ol>
</blockquote>

<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The ImmunizationRecommendation resource is intended to cover communication of a specified patient's immunization recommendations and status across all healthcare disciplines in all care settings and all regions. The set of customized (for the patient) recommendations is based on the comparison of the patient's immunization history with a set of published recommendations (protocols).
</p>
<p>
Additionally, the ImmunizationRecommendation resource is expected to cover key concepts related to the querying of a patient's immunization recommendations and status. This resource - through consultation with the Public Health work group - is believed to meet key use cases and information requirements as defined in the existing <a href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186">HL7 v3</a> POIZ domain and Immunization Domain Analysis Model.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource references the following resources:
</p>
<ul>
    <li>Patient</li>
    <li>Organization</li>
    <li>Immunization</li>
    <li>ImmunizationEvaluation</li>
</ul>
</div>

</div>
