<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Processing Order Details</h2>

<p>
Each request includes one or more <i>detail</i> elements that specify what is being ordered.
The following kinds of orders have been defined:
</p>
<table class="grid">
  <tr>
    <th>Description</th>
	<th>Order Resource</th>
	<th>Response Resources</th>
	<th>Notes</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Request for Diagnostic Investigation</td>
	<td><a href="diagnosticorder.html">DiagnosticOrder</a></td>
	<td>0..* <a href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a></td>
	<td>Local work flow arrangements will determine whether the laboratory handles a request by waiting for a specimen, or for the patient, or by visiting the patient directly to obtain the specimen (i.e. phlebotomy ward round)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Order to supply a prescription</td>
	<td><a href="medicationprescription.html">MedicationPrescription</a></td>
	<td>0..* <a href="medicationadministration.html">MedicationAdministration</a> or <a href="medicationdispense.html">MedicationDispense</a></td>
	<td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Transfer of care from one practitioner to another</td>
	<td>Referral (Resource not yet developed)</td>
	<td>n/a</td>
	<td></td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
Note that a resource may only be used for the order details if the definition
for the resource used in the detail explicitly defines how it is known to be something 
requested, as opposed to (for instance) something that has happened. For some 
resources, such as a prescription, this is defined to be always true - it is always an
instruction/request for something to be done, while other resources may have 
some kind of status element for this purpose. If the definition of the resource does 
not explicitly make it clear this, then it cannot be the target of an order (e.g.
you cannot order a diagnostic report, for example - you have to order a diagnostic 
order instead).
</p>


<a name="dstu"> </a>
<blockquote>
<p>
DSTU note: This list is only a start - the full list of what can be ordered much longer, and yet to be described. 
Implementers should expect this list to grow in subsequent versions, and feedback is welcome from implementers 
who use the Order resource for other kinds of orders.
</p>
</blockquote>

</div>
