<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<h3>Implementation Notes</h3>
<ul>
 <li>Instances can be images, but they can also be DICOM structured documents or other DICOM classes</li>
 <li>This resource follows DICOM practice in using OIDs for elements such as instance type rather than codes.</li>  
 <li>Each instance has an Attachment. Multiple Attachments can represent the same information, but using different 
   approaches. The ImagingStudy.content.url could be a reference to a WADO-RS service that makes the instance available. The ImagingStudy.content.url 
   could be a reference to a FHIR resource (<a href="media.html">Media</a>, <a href="composition.html">Composition</a>, etc).</li>
 <li>The use of ImagingStudy.content.data is discouraged with preference of url.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Use Case</h3>
<p>
Joe Angina complains of shortness of breath and occasional chest pain to his primary care physician, Dr. Pat Down at Local MultiClinic, who orders a stress echocardiogram; the order is created as a FHIR Order resource to manage the workflow, with a link to a DiagnosticOrder resource with the details of the request.   The order is scheduled and assigned to cardiologist Dr. Art Skann, also at Local MultiClinic.   
</p>
<p>
On the scheduled day of the exam, Joe arrives at the echo lab to meet with Dr. Skann and have the study done.  Dr. Skann’s workstation shows the daily list of Orders, and he follows the link to retrieve the DiagnosticOrder. (He may follow the links through the referenced Patient resource to access Joe’s electronic medical record, but that is not the concern of this storyboard.)  
</p>
<p>
The Order/DiagnosticOrder has been transcoded to a DICOM Modality Worklist Scheduled Procedure Step, and in the echo lab the equipment has downloaded the Modality Worklist.  The study is performed, and the acquired images and sonographer’s preliminary measurements are stored in the Local MultiClinic Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS).  The PACS creates an ImagingStudy resource for each study it manages.
</p>
<p>
Dr. Skann interprets the study on a PACS workstation, and he selects two key image frames to be included in the diagnostic report; this selection is stored back to the PACS as a DICOM Key Object Selection with the title “For Report Attachment”, and the PACS makes it available (transcodes it) as a FHIR ImagingObjectSelection resource.  Dr. Skann dictates the report using a structured data entry report writing program, including a recommendation for a cardiac catheterization procedure, and signs it.  The report writing program formats the report as a CDA document, retrieves the ImagingObjectSelection resource, and inserts the referenced key images into the report.
</p>
<p>
Dr. Down meets again with Joe, and they review the results of the stress test.  Joe has a question about the findings that the key images in the report do not show, so Dr. Down uses the Local MultiClinic EMR to query the PACS for the full ImagingStudy resource, and uses the references there to open an image display for the full study.  Joe agrees to proceed to catheterization, and Dr. Down sends a referral to the Ginormous University Hospital cath department, and triggers the PACS to share the echo study through the Metropolitan Health Information Exchange.  
</p>
<p>
The PACS creates a manifest of the study as an ImagingObjectSelection resource, which includes all the images but excludes the sonographer’s preliminary measurements (which as a matter of policy are not shared outside the Local MultiClinic). The manifest is published to the Metro HIE. (In accordance with IHE XDS-I, the images themselves are not directly published to the HIE, but available for on-demand retrieval from the PACS.)
</p>
<p>
At Ginormous Hospital, Dr. Cora Plummer receives the cath referral, and looks up the study in the Metro HIE registry.  She retrieves the study manifest ImagingObjectSelection, and uses it to access the shared images, which she uses to prepare for the cath procedure.
</p>


<!-- old use-case replaced August 2015, CP #7679
<p>
The following storyboard illustrates the primary use case for 
this resource:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
An oncologist, Karen, is seeing patients in her clinic, and would like
background on the patients she is seeing today. Her first patient of the
day, Alex. has arrived. She launches her Electronic Medical Record (EMR)
software, and makes a Patient query on Alex using his last name. The EMR
software makes a FHIR query on the Patient resource, to provide background
demographic information for cover page rendering. The EMR software makes a
subsequent FHIR query on the Condition resource, and reports that Alex is
suspected to have prostate cancer. With this information, Karen decides to
check for two further tests - the results of a Prostate-Specific Antigen
(PSA) laboratory test, and of a CT exam performed at the local diagnostic
facility. First, a FHIR query is made against the Observation resource to
query for the most recent value of PSA (the EMR also queries previous 
values of PSA for trending). For the CT exam, the EMR software queries on
the ImagingStudy resource to retrieve a list of available images with other 
relevant constraints (such as modality, body region etc.). This returns 
back the studies available, with relevant meta-data about each study,
its series and images. This information will help Karen to select which 
study would like to review. Using the WADO-RS references provided, the 
artifacts Karen would like to review can be downloaded and viewed using 
capable DICOM viewing software.
</p>
</blockquote>
-->
</div>
