<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<h3>Implementation Notes</h3>
<ul>
 <li>Instances can be images, but they can also be dicom structured documents or other dicom classes</li>
 <li>Each instance may have a url and an attachment. Both represent the same information, but using different 
   approaches. The URL is a reference to a WADO-RS service that makes the instance available, while the attachment 
   is a reference to a FHIR resource (<a href="media.html">Media</a>, <a href="composition.html">Composition</a>, etc).</li>
 <li>This resource follows DICOM practice in using OIDs for elements such as instance type rather than codes.</li>  
</ul>

<h3>Use Case</h3>

<p>
The following storyboard illustrates the primary use case for 
this resource:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
An oncologist, Karen, is seeing patients in her clinic, and would like
background on the patients she is seeing today. Her first patient of the
day, Alex. has arrived. She launches her Electronic Medical Record (EMR)
software, and makes a Patient query on Alex using his last name. The EMR
software makes a FHIR query on the Patient resource, to provide background
demographic information for cover page rendering. The EMR software makes a
subsequent FHIR query on the Condition resource, and reports that Alex is
suspected to have prostate cancer. With this information, Karen decides to
check for two further tests - the results of a Prostate-Specific Antigen
(PSA) laboratory test, and of a CT exam performed at the local diagnostic
facility. First, a FHIR query is made against the Observation resource to
query for the most recent value of PSA (the EMR also queries previous 
values of PSA for trending). For the CT exam, the EMR software queries on
the ImagingStudy resource to retrieve a list of available images with other 
relevant constraints (such as modality, body region etc.). This returns 
back the studies available, with relevant meta-data about each study,
its series and images. This information will help Karen to select which 
study would like to review. Using the WADO-RS references provided, the 
artifacts Karen would like to review can be downloaded and viewed using 
capable DICOM viewing software.
</p>
</blockquote>

</div>
