<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
	The ImagingStudy resource provides information on available imaging data.
</p>
<p>
An ImagingStudy provides information on a single DICOM imaging study, and the series and imaging objects in 
that study. It also provides information on how to retrieve that information (in a native DICOM 
format, or in a rendered format, such as JPEG).
</p>
<p>
This resource provides mappings of its elements to DICOM attributes.  DICOM attributes are identified 
by a 32-bit tag, presented in canonical form as two four-digit hexadecimal values within parentheses 
and separated by a comma, e.g., (0008,103E).  The name and value representation (data type) of 
each attribute can be found 
in <a href="http://medical.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/html/part06.html">DICOM Part 6 Data Dictionary</a>.  
The use of the attributes in the context of information objects, including detailed description of use, can be found 
in <a href="http://medical.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/html/part03.html">DICOM Part 3 Information Object Definitions </a>.  
Attributes used in the DICOM query information models, such as "Number of Instances in Study", can be found 
in <a href="http://medical.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/html/part04.html#chapter_C">DICOM Part 4 Annex C</a>.
</p>
<p>
ImagingStudy provides access to significant DICOM information but will only eliminate the need for DICOM 
query (e.g., a DICOMweb search transaction) in the simplest cases. The DICOM instances are not stored in the ImagingStudy 
resource; use of a DICOM service is needed (e.g., a DICOMweb retrieve transaction).
</p>
<p> 
One ImagingStudy SHALL reference one DICOM Study.
</p>
<p>This resource can change as additional information is added to the related DICOM Study.</p>
<p>See notes for guidance on <a href="imagingstudy.html#source">how imaging study element values can be populated</a> and <a href="imagingstudy.html#workflow">when imaging studies are typically created and updated</a>.</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
    The <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource is used to store details of an entire DICOM Study and its relationships to other resources, such as <a href="patient.html">Patient</a>, <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a>, and <a href="encounter.html">Encounter</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
		The <a href="imagingselection.html">ImagingSelection</a> resource is used to reference to a subset of a study. Instances of this resource are created for specific clinical purposes and are unlikely to change once created.
		</p>
		<p>
		An <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> typically relates to a set of images in the following ways.
		</p>
		<ul>
		  <li><a href="observation.html">Observation.partOf</a> references an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a></li>
		  <li><a href="observation.html">Observation.derivedFrom</a> references an <a href="imagingselection.html">ImagingSelection</a> when it directly relates to an identified subset of a study</li>
		  <li><a href="observation.html">Observation.derivedFrom</a> references an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> when it does not relate to an identified subset of a study.</li>
		  <li><a href="observation.html">Observation.derivedFrom</a> references an <a href="imagingselection.html">ImagingSelection</a> when it is a measurement of an identified subset of a study described by the <a href="imagingselection.html">ImagingSelection</a></li>
		</ul>
	

	<p>The <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> resource is used to store non-DICOM images, video, or audio with relevant metadata. The <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> resource might be appropriate for including a rendered DICOM image in cases where only the image is needed and not the full image context.</p>


</div>
</div>
