<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="notes"></a>
<h3>Implementation Notes</h3>
<p>
A referenced DICOM SOP instance could be:
<ul>
<li>A single- or multi-frame, still or video image captured by a variety of imaging modalities, such as X-ray, MR, and ultrasound;</li>
<li>A set of various presentation parameters, including annotation and markup;</li>
<li>A set of measurements or a report, including radiation dose report and CAD analysis;</li>
<li>An encapsulated PDF or CDA document;</li>
<li>A list of instances, such as key “of interest” images, or instances to be “deleted”; or </li>
<li>Other DICOM content. </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
DICOM Series Instance UID and SOP Instance UID use the <code>id</code> datatype, and are encoded directly. For example, an image with SOP Instance UID of <code>2.16.124.113543.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430045.1.1</code> is encoded in <code>ImagingStudy.series.instance.uid</code> as <code>“2.16.124.113543.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430045.1.1”</code>.
</p>
<p>
The ImagingStudy’s DICOM Study Instance UID is encoded in the <code>ImagingStudy.identifier</code> element, which is of the <code>Identifier</code> datatype. When encoding a DICOM UID in an <code>Identifier</code> datatype, use the Identifier system of <code>“urn:dicom:uid”</code>, and prefix the UID value with <code>“urn:oid:”</code>. Therefore, an ImagingStudy with DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>2.16.124.113543.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430046</code> is encoded as:
<pre class="json">

	"identifier":{
		"system":"urn:dicom:uid",
		"value":"urn:oid:2.16.124.113543.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430046"
	} 

</pre>
</p>
<p>
The study accession number can also be encoded as an <code>Reference.Identifier</code> using the ServiceRequest Reference type and the <code>“ACSN”</code> identifier type, as follows:
<pre class="json">

"basedOn": [
    "reference": {
        "type": "ServiceRequest",
        "identifier":{
            "type" : {
                "coding" : [
                    {
                        "system" : "http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/v2-0203",
                        "code" : "ACSN"
                    }
                ]
            },
            "system":"http://ginormoushospital.org/accession",
            "value":"GH334103"
        }
    }
]

</pre>
</p>
<p>
The ImagingStudy.endpoint elements and ImagingStudy.series.endpoint elements indicate network 
services that can be used to access the studies, series, or instances; for example, a DICOM WADO-RS server. An 
ImagingStudy.series.endpoint of a particular Endpoint.connectionType provides that service for that 
series, and all contained instances. An ImagingStudy.endpoint of a particular connection type provides 
that service for all series in that study that do not have a specified Endpoint of that type, and their 
contained instances. That is, an ImagingStudy.series.endpoint overrides an ImagingStudy.endpoint 
of the same connection type. 
Systems can determine if a particular study, series, or instance is available or offline by interacting with the endpoint.
Since each study, or individual series of a study can be stored on different imaging 
archive servers, per-series endpoints are required. For the identified services and use cases, all instances within 
a series would be stored together, and thus instance-level endpoints are not defined.
</p>
<p>
Different Endpoint connection types may have different capabilities, protocols or requirements; and the specified 
<code>Endpoint.address</code> may require manipulation. See below for the details on use of imaging-related Endpoint connection types.
</p>
<a name="wado-rs"></a>
<h4>WADO-RS</h4>
<p>
An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-rs</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-RS service. The <code>Endpoint.address</code> identifies the HTTP(S) service base url. 
That is, only the scheme, authority and path are included. Sub-services, such as <code>study</code>, shall not be specified. 
The path shall not contain a trailing slash.
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-RS (Web Access to DICOM Objects, RESTful mode) service uses a RESTful approach to instance retrieval.
This service allows for retrieval of native DICOM SOP instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including
JPEG and MPEG. The media type of a response is specified by the request Accept header (preferred); or, by the <code>accept</code>
query parameters. Supported media types depend on the  capabilities of the WADO-RS server and the classification of the instance 
as “single frame,” “multi-frame,” “video,” “text,” or “other.” The WADO-RS service also allows retrieval of study
or series level information.
</p>
<p>
The path to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate sub-resource paths to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingStudy resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-RS service base url of <code>“https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs”</code> found in an <code>ImagingStudy.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>“1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code> found in an <code>ImagingStudy.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>“urn:dicom:uid”</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Series Instance UID of <code>“1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789”</code> found in <code>ImagingStudy.series.uid</code>, and</li>
<li>the DICOM SOP Instance UID of <code>“1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2”</code> found in <code>ImagingStudy.series.instance.uid</code></li>
</ul>
we can construct the WADO-RS URL to issue an HTTP GET for a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file (if consistent with the Accept header):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2

</pre>
<p>
Query parameters on the "rendered" sub-resource can control other aspects of the rendering including: the rendered dimensions, the
quality (compression ratio), the region of interest to render, the brightness/contrast (window center/width)
adjustments, and whether to “burn” patient or study demographics into the rendered result. Specific frames
of a multi-frame instance may be retrieved using the frames sub-resource.
</p>
<p>
For example, provided the Accept header indicates a preference for image/jpeg, the example above can be
extended with parameters that cause a JPEG (rendered to a size of 400 columns by 400 rows) of a region extending from
the top-left corner of the original image to 1000 pixels across and 3000 pixels right, to be retrieved (additional
sub-resource and parameters emphasized):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2<b>/rendered?viewport=400,400,0,0,1000,3000</b>

</pre>
<p>
If the WADO-RS service supports the DICOMweb thumbnail resource, a representative image can be requested, for example, to display alongside the study. The URL would look as follows:
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/thumbnail

</pre>
<p>
For further details on DICOM WADO-RS capabilities including additional rendering parameters,
see <a href="http://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/PS3.18.html">DICOM PS 3.18</a>.
</p>
<a name="wado-uri"></a>
<h4>WADO-URI</h4>
<p>An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-uri</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-URI service. The <code>Endpoint.address</code> identifies the HTTP(S) service base url. 
That is, only the scheme, authority and path are included. Neither a question mark (“?”) nor any query parameters shall be included.
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-URI (Web Access to DICOM Objects, URI mode) service uses HTTP query parameter syntax. This service allows
for retrieval of native DICOM instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including JPEG and MPEG. The media
type of a response is specified by the request Accept header (preferred); or, by the contentType query parameter.
Supported media types depend on the classification of the instance as “single frame,” “multi-frame,” “video,” “text,” or “other.”
</p>
<p>
The query to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate query parameters to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingStudy resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-URI service base url of <code>“https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri”</code> found in an <code>ImagingStudy.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code> found in an <code>ImagingStudy.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>“urn:dicom:uid”</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Series Instance UID of <code>“1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789”</code> found in <code>ImagingStudy.series.uid</code>, and</li>
<li>the DICOM SOP Instance UID of <code>“1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2”</code> found in <code>ImagingStudy.series.instance.uid</code></li>
</ul>
we can construct the WADO-URI URL to issue an HTTP GET for a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file (if consistent with the Accept header):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2

</pre>
<p>
Additional query parameters can control other aspects of the rendering including rendered dimensions, quality (compression
ratio), the region of interest within the image to render, brightness/contrast (window center/width) adjustments, whether
to “burn” patient or study demographics into the rendered result, and which frame of a multi-frame instance to retrieve.
</p>
<p>
For example, provided the Accept header indicates a preference for image/jpeg, the example above can be extended with
parameters that cause a JPEG thumbnail (100 columns by 100 rows) of the left half of the image to be retrieved (additional
parameters emphasized):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2&amp;<b>rows=100&amp;columns=100&amp;region=0,0,0.5,1 </b>

</pre>
<p>
For further details on DICOM WADO-URI capabilities including additional rendering parameters,
see <a href="http://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/PS3.18.html">DICOM PS 3.18</a>.
</p>
<a name="iid"></a>
<h4>IID</h4>
<p>An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>ihe-iid</code>, system <code>http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies an IHE <b>Invoke Image Display (IID)</b> service. The <code>Endpoint.address</code> identifies the HTTP(S) service base url. 
That is, only the scheme, authority and path are included. Neither a question mark (“?”) nor any query parameters shall be included.
</p>
<p>
The IHE <b>Invoke Image Display (IID)</b> service provides a standardized mechanism to launch a viewer in a particular study 
context. (IID also supports invoking a particular patient context, but that is not profiled here.) An IID-type Endpoint should 
be used only at the study level. As well as invoking the viewer on a particular study, query parameters can request particular 
viewer capabilities, image quality, and more.
</p>
<p>
To launch a viewer, append the appropriate query parameters to <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, using the following information in a fictional ImagingStudy resource:
<ul>
<li>the WADO-URI service base url of <code>“https://pacs.hospital.org/IHEInvokeImageDisplay”</code> found in an <code>ImagingStudy.endpoint.address</code>,</li>
<li>the DICOM Study Instance UID of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code> found in an <code>ImagingStudy.identifier</code> having <code>Identifier.system</code> of <code>“urn:dicom:uid”</code>,</li>
</ul>
we can construct the IID URL to invoke a diagnostic quality viewer on the indicated study:
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/IHEInvokeImageDisplay?requestType=STUDY&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;diagnosticQuality=true

</pre>
<p>
For further details on IHE Invoke Image Display capabilities including additional parameters, see
the <a href="http://www.ihe.net/Technical_Frameworks/#radiology">IHE Technical Frameworks</a>, 
or the introduction on the <a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php/Invoke_Image_Display">IHE IID Profile Wiki</a>.
</p>


<a name="additional-dicom-attributes"></a>
<h4>Additional DICOM attributes</h4>
<p>
Some imaging uses may require information beyond what is present in an ImagingStudy resource. Many of the DICOM patient and study level attributes are found in the FHIR Patient, Procedure, or other resources which are referenced from an ImagingStudy instance. Other DICOM content may be transformed into other FHIR resources, such as DiagnosticReports or Observations, which are not directly referenced, but may be easily found.
</p><p>
Although many ImagingStudy consumers are expected to need only the DICOM information contained in FHIR resources, some may need additional DICOM attributes. For these cases, which by their nature involve more imaging-aware consumers, the most flexible solution is to leverage the DICOM WADO-RS metadata-only endpoint to retrieve an XML or JSON representation of the DICOM study, series, instance, or frame information.
</p><p>
A benefit of using the metadata endpoint in this way is that the ImagingStudy creator does not need to know each of the attributes that each of the (current or future) ImagingStudy consumers is (or will be) interested in.
</p>
<h5>Example Metadata Retrieval</h5>
<p>
A client retrieves the following ImagingStudy:
</p>
<pre>
{
  "resourceType": "ImagingStudy",
  "id": "example-xr",
  "identifier": [
    {
      "use": "official",
      "system": "urn:dicom:uid",
      "value": "urn:oid:2.16.124.113543.6003.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430046"
    }
  ],
  ...
  "series": [
    {
      "uid": "2.16.124.113543.6003.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430045.1",
      ...
      "endpoint": [
        {
          "reference": "Endpoint/example-wadors"
        }
      ]
      ...
    }
    ...
  ]
}
</pre>
<p>
(See <a href="imagingstudy-example-xr.json.html">Example XR</a> for full example)
</p><p>
The client retrieves the referenced Endpoint (see <a href="endpoint-example-wadors.json.html">Example WADO-RS</a>) and extracts the WADO-RS URL: <pre>https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs</pre>.
</p><p>
The client uses the WADO-RS URL, the identifier.value and the series.uid to construct a WADO-RS metadata request:
</p>
<pre>
GET https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/2.16.124.113543.6003.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430046/series/2.16.124.113543.6003.1154777499.30246.19789.3503430045.1/metadata HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/dicom+json
</pre>
<p>
The WADO-RS server then returns the complete DICOM metadata for the requested series.
</p>

<a name="use-case"></a>
<h3>Use Case</h3>
<a name="ehr-usecase"></a>
<h4>EHR access to imaging studies</h4>
<p>
Amy, a family physician, would like to see a list of available studies for her patient, 
Alex, filtered by ImagingStudy.status=available to exclude studies without images. 
Her EHR
client makes a FHIR call for all <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> objects available for Alex.
In the response, she is able to see the study date, procedure, modality, and accession number, for each
study returned. There is enough information provided in the response to obtain a thumbnail via a WADO-RS
call, or to launch a viewer using an <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE Radiology - Invoke Image Display (IID)</a>
profile call using the url elements found in the <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>.
</p>
<a name="scheduled"></a>
<h4>Comprehensive Imaging Scheduled Workflow</h4>
<p>
Joe Angina complains of shortness of breath and occasional chest pain to his primary care physician, Dr. Pat Down at
Local MultiClinic, who orders a stress echocardiogram; the order is created as a FHIR <a href="task.html">Task</a>
resource to manage the workflow, with a link to a <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a> resource with
the details of the request.   The order is scheduled and assigned to cardiologist Dr. Art Skann, also at Local MultiClinic.
</p>
<p>
On the scheduled day of the exam, Joe arrives at the echo lab to meet with Dr. Skann and have the study done.
Dr. Skann’s workstation shows the daily list of <a href="task.html">Task</a>, and he follows the link to retrieve the
<a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a>. (He may follow the links through the
referenced <a href="patient.html">Patient</a> resource to access Joe’s electronic 
medical record, but that is not the concern of this storyboard.)
</p>
<p>
The <a href="task.html">Task</a> and <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a> has been transcoded to a DICOM Modality Worklist
Scheduled Procedure Step, and in the echo lab the equipment has downloaded the Modality Worklist.  The
study is performed, and the acquired images and sonographer’s preliminary measurements are stored in the
Local MultiClinic Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS).  The PACS creates
an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource for each study it manages.
</p>
<p>
Dr. Skann interprets the study on a PACS workstation, and he selects two key image frames to be included
in the diagnostic report; this selection is stored back to the PACS as a DICOM Key Object Selection with
the title "For Report Attachment", and the PACS makes it available (transcodes it) as a
FHIR <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource.  Dr. Skann dictates the
report using a structured data entry report writing program, including a recommendation for a cardiac
catheterization procedure, and signs it.  The report writing program formats the report
as a <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> document,
retrieves the <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource, and inserts the
referenced key images into the report.
</p>
<p>
Dr. Down meets again with Joe, and they review the results of the stress test.  Joe has a question about
the findings that the key images in the report do not show, so Dr. Down uses the Local MultiClinic EMR
to query the PACS for the full <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource and uses the references there to open an image
display for the full study.  Joe agrees to proceed to catheterization, and Dr. Down sends a referral to
the Ginormous University Hospital cath department and triggers the PACS to share the echo study
through the Metropolitan Health Information Exchange.
</p>
<p>
The PACS creates an imaging study as an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>
resource, which includes all the
images but excludes the sonographer’s preliminary measurements (which as a matter of policy are
not shared outside the Local MultiClinic). The imaging study is published to the Metro HIE. (In
accordance with <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE XDS-I</a>, the images themselves are not directly
published to the HIE, but available for on-demand retrieval from the PACS.)
</p>
<p>
At Ginormous Hospital, Dr. Cora Plummer receives the cath referral, and looks up the study in the
Metro HIE registry.  She retrieves the study <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>,
and uses it to access the shared images, which she uses to prepare for the cath procedure.
</p>


<!-- old use-case replaced August 2015, CP #7679
<p>
The following storyboard illustrates the primary use case for
this resource:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
An oncologist, Karen, is seeing patients in her clinic, and would like
background on the patients she is seeing today. Her first patient of the
day, Alex. has arrived. She launches her Electronic Medical Record (EMR)
software, and makes a Patient query on Alex using his last name. The EMR
software makes a FHIR query on the Patient resource, to provide background
demographic information for cover page rendering. The EMR software makes a
subsequent FHIR query on the Condition resource, and reports that Alex is
suspected to have prostate cancer. With this information, Karen decides to
check for two further tests - the results of a Prostate-Specific Antigen
(PSA) laboratory test, and of a CT exam performed at the local diagnostic
facility. First, a FHIR query is made against the Observation resource to
query for the most recent value of PSA (the EMR also queries previous
values of PSA for trending). For the CT exam, the EMR software queries on
the ImagingStudy resource to retrieve a list of available images with other
relevant constraints (such as modality, body region etc.). This returns
back the studies available, with relevant meta-data about each study,
its series and images. This information will help Karen to select which
study would like to review. Using the WADO-RS references provided, the
artifacts Karen would like to review can be downloaded and viewed using
capable DICOM viewing software.
</p>
</blockquote>
-->

<a name="size"></a>
<h3>Size Considerations</h3>
<p>
Depending on the modality and procedure type, a DICOM study can range from having one or two instances instance (as in many X-ray procedures) to several thousand instances (for some CT exams). The number of series within a study has far less variability, and is usually under twenty, although post-processing, computer-aided detection, and AI applications may cause modest increases. An ImagingStudy resource describing a large DICOM study would itself be of significant size.
</p><p>
Issuing narrowly-tailored queries can help a client avoid search results containing many ImagingStudy resources. The _summary=true query parameter will omit several resource elements, including all instance-level elements; this can be used to examine search results before retrieving the full instances. If a server limits the byte size of search bundle, this may impact the number of ImagingStudy resources returned per search result page; a client can use the _count query parameter to influence the number of resources per search result page.
</p><p>
When populating an ImagingStudy resource, storing an update for each DICOM instance in the study could result in sending previously sent information repeatedly--an issue that grows as the study size increases. It might also result in a server maintaining thousands of versions of the resource. Repeated, rapid updates of an ImagingStudy may lead to resource contention.
</p><p>
Although not reflected in the ImagingStudy resource, the size of an individual referenced instance may be anywhere from a few kilobytes (a compressed 256x256 pixel MR or 640x480 pixel ultrasound image) to a gigabyte or more (for digital breast tomography imaging). When retrieving the referenced content of an ImagingStudy, consider whether all DICOM instances are needed, whether DICOM instances are used concurrently or sequentially, and what rendering or Transfer Syntax is appropriate for the use case.
</p>
</div>
