<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
  <a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p><strong>This resource is a request resource from a FHIR workflow perspective</strong> - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.</p>
<p><em>ProcedureRequest</em> is a record of a request for a procedure to be planned, proposed, or performed, as distinguished by the <code>ProcedureRequest.status</code> field value, with or on a patient.  Examples of procedures include diagnostic tests/studies, endoscopic procedures, counseling, biopsies, therapies (e.g., physio-, social-, psychological-), (exploratory) surgeries or procedures, exercises, and other clinical interventions.  Procedures may be performed by a healthcare professional, a friend or relative or in some cases by the patient themselves.  The procedure will lead to either a <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> or <a href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a>, that in turn may reference one or more observations, that summarizes the performance of the procedures and associated documentation such as observations, images, findings that are relevant to the treatment/management of the subject.</p>
<p>The principal intention of <em>ProcedureRequest</em> is to support ordering procedures for on patients (which includes non-human patients in veterinary medicine). However, in many contexts, healthcare related processes include performing diagnostic investigations on groups of subjects, devices involved in the provision of healthcare, and even environmental locations such as ducts, bodies of water, etc. <em>ProcedureRequest</em> supports all these usages.  The procedure request may represent an order that is entered by a practitioner in a CPOE system as well as a proposal made by a clinical decision support (CDS) system based on a patient&#39;s clinical record and context of care. Planned procedures referenced by a <a href="careplan.html">CarePlan</a> may also be represented by this resource. </p>
<p>The general work flow that this resource facilitates is that a clinical system creates a procedure request. The procedure request is then accessed by or exchanged with a system, perhaps via intermediaries, that represents an organization (e.g., diagnostic or imaging service, surgical team, physical therapy department) that can perform the procedure. The organization receiving the procedure request will, after it accepts the request, update the request as the work is performed, and then finally issue a report that references the requests that it fulfilled.</p>
<p>The <em>ProcedureRequest</em> resource allows requesting only a single procedure. If a workflow requires requesting multiple procedures simultaneously, this is done using multiple instances of this resource. These instances can be linked in different ways, depending on the needs of the workflow. For guidance, refer to the <a href="request.html">Request pattern</a></p>
</div>
<div>
 <a name="bnr"> </a>

		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

      <p><em>ProcedureRequest</em>, <a href="referralrequest.html">ReferralRequest</a>, and <a href="communicationrequest.html">CommunicationRequest</a> are closely related. In fact, for some services, it may be appropriate to use any one of these resources to request that the procedure be performed. Which one is used may be driven by organization practice and by context. When it is unclear which to use, the following principles may be helpful:</p>
      <ul>
      <li><em>ProcedureRequest</em> is typically used when the requesting clinician has and wishes to exercise the authority (and expertise) to decide exactly what action will be done.</li>
      <li>A ReferralRequest is used when the requesting practitioner is seeking another practitioner or organization to use their own expertise and/or authority to determine the specific action to take.</li>
      <li>A CommunicationRequest is a request to merely disclose information whereas a <em>ProcedureRequest</em> is used when an action is considered to be training or counseling - i.e. when the process will involve verification of the patient's comprehension or an attempt to change the patient's mental state.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Irrespective of this guidance, systems should be prepared for some degree of overlap between these resources and be prepared to execute searches against multiple resources in cases where differentiation cannot be guaranteed. In some workflows more than one type of resource might exist.  For example, upon receiving a ReferralRequest a practitioner might initiate a <em>ProcedureRequest</em>.</p>
</div>
</div>
