<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
<p>
A <i>Procedure Request</i> is a record of a request for a procedure to be performed. 
It can be used to represent a procedure that is planned, that is proposed, or that is ordered.
</p>
<p>
A procedure is an activity 
that is performed with or on a patient as part of the provision of care. Examples include surgical 
procedures, diagnostic procedures, endoscopic procedures, biopsies, counselling, physiotherapy, exercise, etc.
Procedures may be performed by a healthcare professional, a friend or relative or in some cases by the patient
themselves.
</p>
<p>
The procedure request may represent an order that is entered by a practitioner in a CPOE 
system as well as a proposal made by a clinical decision support (CDS) system based 
on a patient's clinical record and context of care. Planned procedures referenced by a
<a href="careplan.html">CarePlan</a> may also be represented by this resource.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
ProcedureRequest is closely related to other types of "request" resources, particularly <a href="diagnosticorder.html">DiagnosticOrder</a>
and <a href="referralrequest.html">ReferralRequest</a>.  In fact, for some services, it may be appropriate to use any one of these
resources to request that the procedure be performed.  Which one is used may be driven by organization practice and by context.  When
it is unclear which to use, the following principles may be helpful:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
ProcedureRequest or DiagnosticOrder are typically used when the requesting clinician has and wishes to exercise the authority 
(and expertise) to decide exactly what action will be done.
</li>
<li>
A ReferralRequest is used when the requesting practitioner is seeking another practitioner or organization to use their own expertise
and/or authority to determine the specific action to take.
</li>
<li>
Whether an activity is deemed to be a procedure or only a diagnostic order is typically driven by how invasive the diagnostic process
is.  More invasive processes are typically represented as procedures, though the dividing line may vary by organization.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Irrespective of the guidance above, systems should be prepared for some degree of overlap between these resources and be
prepared to execute searches against multiple resources in cases where differentiation cannot be guaranteed.  As well, in some workflows
more than one type of resource or even all three might exist.  E.g. Upon receiving a ReferralRequest a practitioner might initiate a 
DiagnosticOrder.  The diagnostic service might then initiate a ProcedureRequest.
</p>
<p>
The notion of ProcedureRequest and <a href="communicationrequest.html">CommunicationRequest</a> are also closely related.  
The boundary between determining whether an action is
considered to be training or counselling (and thus a ProcedureRequest) as opposed to a CommunicationRequest is based on whether
there's a specific intent to change the mind-set of the patient.  A request to merely disclose information would be considered
a CommunicationRequest.  Invocation of a process that will involve verification of the patient's comprehension or an attempt to
change the patient's mental state would be a ProcedureRequest.
</p>
</div>

</div>
