<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Why not custom resources?</h2>
<p>
Technically, nothing prevents implementers from going off and defining their own resources containing
whatever data elements they wish.  However, doing so causes several issues:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Custom resources don't have a discoverability mechanism in the same way custom codes and extensions
  do using the <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a> and <a href="profile.html">Profile</a> resources.  As a 
  result, any implementer that receives a custom resource would have no way of looking up what the meaning 
  of the resource or its elements were.  While they could get some sense of meaning from XML or JSON tag names, this often 
  isn't sufficient for safe healthcare interoperability.</li>
  <li>Custom resource names would not be present in the FHIR schemas as allowed elements within the FHIR
  ATOM schema and would also not be present in the enumeration of resources in the Reference type.  
  Nor would they be supported by any of the auto-generated reference implementations and software interfaces
  This would cause issues for any receiving system making use of the schemas directly or via code-generation.</li>
  <li>There is no means of preventing two implementers from independently coming up with the same name for
  a resource but defining it differently in terms of meaning as well as allowed elements.  This would also cause
  interoperability issues.</li>
</ul>
<p>
All of these concerns are mitigated when there's an assumption that the custom resource will only be used
within a narrow constrained environment where all participants will be aware of the semantics, will be using
the same custom schemas and there's no chance of collisions.  However, HL7's experience is that closed
implementation environments rarely remain that way over the long term.  Eventually data will need to be
shared with others outside the closed environment and all of the above issues will again come into play.
</p>
<p>
Therefore, use of 'custom' resources is <b>NOT</b> considered to be conformant with FHIR.  While the use of
extensions may make the Basic resource slightly more complex and less visually appealing, it is the only safe
and approved mechanism for sharing resource concepts not representable using standard HL7-defined resources.
</p>
<p>
It is expected that future versions of the interface tooling will be able to generate object interfaces on the
basis of profiles.  Where this occurs, the complexity of custom resource elements being expressed as extensions
should be transparant to the internal code of systems that support that particular variant of the Basic resource.
This should further reduce the cost of using 'Basic' as opposed to custom resources.
</p>
<p>
NOTE: This position is subject to change based on implementation experience.  Alternative mechanisms for
handling custom resource requirements in a safe manner may be explored.  Ideas around alternative technical 
strategies for managing this issue are welcome.
</p>

<h2>Documents and narrative-only resources</h2>
<p>
Documents are constructed of sections, where a key part of each section is the narrative.  The narratives
are stitched together to form the overall text of the document.  Many documentsections will correspond neatly to
resources that are already defined - <a href="list.html">List</a>, <a href="diagnosticreport">DiagnosticReport</a>,
<a href="familyhistory.html">FamilyHistory</a>, etc.  However, oddly enough, alignment with FHIR resources isn't
always top of mind when clinicians and others design documents and some sections won't neatly align with the
boundaries of resources.  Sometimes there's simply a need for a place where a document author can say "stuff"
without any particular constraints on what they may choose to talk about.  Basic is intended to provide a
mechanism to handle those circumstances.
</p>
<p>
Where-ever possible, the "standard" FHIR resources should be used, even for narrative-only content.  That's because
subsequent revisions of the narrative-only content might choose to encode pieces or even all of the narrative content.
Encoding can occur with "Basic" as well.  Extensions can point to other resources (contained or stand-alone) that
fully encode pieces of the free-form narrative found in the Basic resource.  If no appropriate other resource exists
for the meaning of the content, extensions can also be used.
</p>

<h2>Best practices for using 'Basic'</h2>
<p>
There are several good practices to follow when making use of the Basic resource:
</p>
<ol>
  <li>Before using Basic, post a description of the desired resource type on HL7's FHIR list-server or on
  <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/hl7_fhir">Stack Overflow</a> to see whether the
  use-case can be met by an existing resource.  (Sometimes the intended scope of an existing resource won't 
  be clear, even if the intent is to cover your space.)  Using an existing resource is usually preferable
  to using Basic as it significantly increases the likelihood of interoperability.</li>
  
  <li>If an existing resource would normally be a good fit for your use-case but can't be used due to
  overly prescriptive constraints your implementation is unable to meet, again raise the problem on
  <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/hl7_fhir">Stack Overflow</a> so the problem with the
  specification can be addressed</li>
  
  <li>If it is necessary to make use of the Basic resource, try to use one of the HL7-defined codes for
  resource type or submit your requirement for a new type for inclusion in the HL7 vocabulary, as this will
  increase the likelihood of interoperability.  Alternate code systems are conformant, but are less likely to
  be recognized or re-used across the healthcare implementation space.</li>
  
  <li>Architect your interface in a way that will make it less painful to swap your use of Basic with an
  'official' resource in the event that a future release of FHIR formally defines a resource that encompasses
  your use-case.</li>
  
  <li>Use a <a href="profile.html">Profile</a> to define the extensions relevant to each type of other resource used.
  Profile can also be used to define additional search criteria appropriate for the resource.</li>
</ol>

<h2>Referencing Basic resources</h2>
<p>
None of the standard resources will have direct references to Basic, aside from those that allow linking to
"Any" resource.  As a result, most references to "Basic" will need to be performed using extensions.
</p>

</div>
