<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"></a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p style="border:2px; border-style:solid; border-color:#999999; padding: 1em; border-radius: 4px 4px 4px 4px;"><b><i>For an overview of this resource and others in the Medication Definition domain, also see the <a href="medication-definition-module.html">module page</a></i></b></p>
		<p>
			A medicinal product may consist of several items, which need to be combined or processed before administration to the patient. 
			
			This resource covers the ready-for-use administrable product - the components of which are 
			<a href="manufactureditemdefinition.html">ManufacturedItemDefinition</a> resources. 
			Note that in some cases the administrable product needs no processing or transformation from the manufactured item. 
		</p>
		<p>
			This resource represents the final form of the product; hence it details properties such as the route, that only apply to the final product. 
			It is a definitional resource, representing the properties of a product, but not the actual instance given to someone.
			When necessary to record that, a <a href="medication.html">Medication</a> resource is used. 
		</p>
		
		<p>
			<i>
			This resource corresponds to the Pharmaceutical Product as defined by the ISO IDMP set of standards, 
			namely ISO 11615. To better align with the HL7 guidelines for supporting different product concepts and to avoid possible confusion 
			with the resources defined in the <a href="medication.html">Medications module</a> of HL7 FHIR, the concept "Administrable Product" has been adopted for the name, 
			whereas the terms and definitions of other core resources in the <a href="medication-definition-module.html">Medication Definition module</a> do correspond 
			directly to the ISO IDMP terms. 
			See also the <a href="administrableproductdefinition-mappings.html">mapping table</a> for a detailed mapping of this resource to the IDMP Pharmaceutical Product definition.
			</i>
		</p>
	</div>
</div>
