<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The FHIR terminology specification is based on two key concepts, originally defined in <a href="http://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public/standards/V3/core_principles/infrastructure/coreprinciples/v3modelcoreprinciples.html">HL7 v3 Core Principles</a>:
</p>
<ul>
<li> <code><a href="codesystem.html">CodeSystem</a></code> - defines a set of codes with meanings (also known as enumeration, terminology, classification, and/or ontology) - e.g. define which codes (symbols and/or expressions) exist, and how they are understood</li>
<li> <code>ValueSet</code> - selects a set of codes from those defined by one or more code systems to specify which codes can be used in a particular context</li>
</ul>
<p>
Value sets have 2 aspects:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><code>.compose</code>: A definition of which codes are intended to be in the value set ("intension")</li>
 <li><code>.expansion</code>: The list of codes that are actually in the value set under a given set of conditions ("extension")</li>
</ul>
<p>
The <code>ValueSet</code> resource can carry either the <code>.compose</code> or the <code>.expansion</code>,
or both. There is a <a href="valueset-operations.html#expand">"$expand" operation</a> which can be used to ask a server to generate
an expansion given the composition rules. 
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="relationships"> </a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<ul>
 <li>Value sets use <a href="codesystem.html">CodeSystem</a> resources by referring to them via their canonical URLs</li>
 <li>Value sets are used in <a href="elementdefinition.html">ElementDefinition</a> and <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resources to specify the allowable contents for coded elements</li>
 <li><a href="conceptmap.html">Concept Maps</a> describe mappings between value sets</li>
 <li>The ValueSet resource design is based on the functionality described in the <a href="http://www.omg.org/spec/CTS2/1.0/">OMG CTS 2</a> specification, along 
 with metadata in the HL7 Value Set Definition specification. Value set resources can be converted to CTS2 
 value set and code system resources.</li>
 <li>The value set resource is aligned with the <a href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Value_Set_Definition_Standard_Project">Value Set Definition</a> (VSD) project. 
 Not all of the elements defined by the VSD are part of the base resource - some are defined as part of the <a href="valueset-extensions.html">ValueSet Extensions</a>.
 In the ValueSet resource, the <code>compose</code> element is the VSD "Content Logical definition".</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<a name="context"> </a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>

<p>
When using value sets, proper differentiation between a code system and a value set is important. 
This is one very common area where significant clinical safety risks occur in practice. Implementers
should be familiar with the content in <a href="terminologies.html">Using Codes in resources</a>.
</p>

<h3>ValueSet Identification</h3>
<p>
A value set has 3 identifiers:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><code>ValueSet.id</code>: the <a href="resource.html#id">logical id</a> on the system that holds the value set - this changes as it moves from server to server (this id, with the server address prepended, is called the 'literal identity' of the resource)</li>
 <li><code>ValueSet.url</code>: the canonical URL that never changes for this value set - it is the same in every copy. Ideally, the URL should also be the location of the master version of the value set, though this is not always possible</li>
 <li><code>ValueSet.identifier</code>: A system/value pair that is used to identify the value set in other contexts (such as an OID in an <a href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186">HL7 v3</a> specification)</li>
</ul>
<p>
For further information regarding resource identification, see <a href="resource.html#id">Resource Identity</a>.
</p>

<p>
This means that each value set has 2 different URLs that can be used to reference it - 
its canonical <code>url</code>, and its local location from which it may be retrieved. 
Because it is common practice to copy (cache) value sets locally, most references to 
value sets use the canonical URL. 
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
For example, the value sets published as part of FHIR all have a canonical URL
which is also a location by which they may be accessed in the FHIR specification
itself. Note, though, that while a new version of the FHIR Specification is being prepared,
value sets that are published in the drafts will not be found in the published FHIR
specification at their canonical URL. 
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>
Alternatively, the <code>identifier</code> and <code>version</code> elements may be used to reference this value set in a 
design, a profile, a <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> template 
or <a href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186">HL7 v3</a> message (in the CD data 
type valueSet and valueSetVersion properties). These different contexts may make additional restrictions on the 
possible values of these elements.  The <code>identifier</code> is generally not needed when using value sets in
a FHIR context, where the canonical URL is always the focus.
</p>

</div>

</div>

