<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Identifier and Version</h2>
<p>
The <i>identifier</i> and <i>version</i> elements may be used to reference this value set in a design, a profile, a 
CDA template or V3 message (valueSet and valueSetVersion). These different contexts may make additional restrictions 
on the possible values of these elements.  These elements are generally not needed when using value sets with FHIR
implementations as they can make use of the innate identifier and versioning mechanism associated with the resource
</p>

<h2>Value Sets that define codes</h2>

<p>
A value set that defines codes automatically includes all the codes it defines. 
This kind of value set is useful for simple sets of codes that are highly 
specific and context-dependent. The value set and the code system are both 
given URI identifiers by which they may be identified from elsewhere 
(ValueSet.identifier and ValueSet.define.system). These identifiers must 
be different.
</p>
<ul>
 <li><i>ValueSet.define.system</i> is the URI that identifies these codes 
   when used in a <a href="datatypes.htm#Coding">Coding</a></li>
 <li>The usability of the codes is closely linked to the quality of the definitions. 
   Although a definition is not required for each concept, a good definition SHOULD be provided</li>
 <li>If concepts contain other concepts, then the contained concepts are "subsumed" by 
   the containing concept (there is an "is-a" relationship between the codes).</li>
  <li>An abstract concept must have contained concepts</li>
</ul>

<h2>Value Sets that include codes defined elsewhere</h2>

<p>
Value sets that include codes defined in some other code system are most useful when 
dealing with large general code systems such as SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm or various IETF code sets 
including human language. The value set can be a simple list of included codes or it can be some 
kind of general selection criteria using the facilities provided by the code system. 
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Within an include or exclude criterion, multiple filters and concept selections are intersected. All the 
   conditions specified must be true.</li>
 <li>The value set always includes any codes it defines itself. A typical use for this
    is when including a set of codes from elsewhere, and adding a few additional codes to cover
    cases not catered to by the included codes</li>
 <li>An include statement includes any enumerated codes and any codes that meet the filter criteria</li>
 <li>If the system reference is not version specific and filters are present, then the contents of the value set are open and change 
    over time as the underlying code systems are updated</li>
 <li>The content of the value set is constructed by unioning of all the import and include statements and then 
  eliminating any of the 'excluded' codes.</li>
 <li>A value set needs to do something.  It can't simply include an existing value set without 
   also including additional content or excluding content</li>
<!--
 <li>The point of declaring that this value set restricts another is that this value set can then replace the other in a profile 
without changing the meaning. Declaring this explicitly allows profile tools to reason about the relationship without having 
to compute the relationship, which might not be possible for a profile tool</li>
-->
 <li>Using the property filters is only possible where the underlying code system defines 
  appropriate properties. Note that in some cases, the underlying code system defines the 
  logical concepts but not the syntax for exercising them. In such cases, the literal 
  definitions may be provided by a third party. See below for notes about its use against common code systems</li>
</ul>

<h3>Code systems Note</h3>
<p>
How filters are used with various code systems:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr><th>System</th>    <th>Property</th> <th>Expression</th> <th>Value</th>        <th>Definition</th></tr>
 <tr><td>SNOMED CT</td> <td>"concept"</td><td>is-a</td>       <td>[concept]</td>    <td>Includes all codes that have a transitive is-a relationship with the concept Id provided as the value</td> </tr>
 <tr><td></td>          <td>"expression"</td><td>=</td>       <td>[expression]</td> <td>The result of the filter is the result of executing the given snomed expression 
 (see <a href="http://www.ihtsdo.org/fileadmin/user_upload/Docs_01/News/SNOMED_CT_Query_Specification_-__v0.08_-_20121213.doc"> SNOMED CT Query Language</a>)</td> </tr>
 <tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr>
 <tr><td>Loinc</td> <td>SCALE_TYP</td><td>=</td>       <td>[concept]</td>    <td>Includes all codes where the named property has the given value</td> </tr>
 <tr><td></td>      <td>Type</td>        <td>=</td>       <td>Method</td>       <td>All the LOINC codes for particular methods defined in LOINC</td> </tr>
 <tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr>
 <tr><td>V3 Code systems</td> <td>"concept"</td><td>is-a</td>       <td>[code]</td>    <td>Includes all codes that have a transitive is-a relationship with the concept identified by the value</td> </tr>
</table>

<a name="expansion"> </a>
<h2>Value Set Expansion</h2>
<p>
A value set can be "expanded", where the definition of the value set is 
used to create a simple collection of codes suitable for use for data 
entry or validation. This is most useful when a value set includes 
all the children of a code or a set of codes by filter.
</p>
<p>
The standard way to produce a value set expansion is to perform a 
<a href="query.htm">query</a> on the value set with _query=expand:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [service-url]/valueset/?_query=expand&amp;id=...
</pre>
<p>
This is a request to produce a value set expansion for the value set
with the provided id. The value set can be identified by other means,
such as identifier and version. There is an additional parameter 
flat=true|false, which the client can use to specify whether a 
hierarchical value set expansion is acceptable or not.
</p>
<p>
The value set expansion returned by this query should be treated 
as a transient result that will change over time (whether it does or
not depends on how the value set is specified), so applications 
should repeat the query each time the value set is used.
</p>
<p>
A resource that represents a value set expansion includes the same
identification details as the definition of the value set, and MAY
include the definition of the value set (<i>define</i> and <i>compose</i>
elements). In addition it has a <i>expansion</i> element which contains
the list of codes that constitute the value set expansion. If the 
expansion is heirachical (codes contain other concepts), there 
is no implication about the logical relationship between them; this 
is guidance for helping human user navigate the choice of codes that 
may or may not relate to the logical definitions of the codes or concepts.
</p>


</div>
