<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The FHIR terminology specification is based two key concepts, originally defined in <a href="http://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public/standards/V3/core_principles/infrastructure/coreprinciples/v3modelcoreprinciples.html">HL7 v3 Core Principles</a>:
</p>
<ul>
<li> <b>code system</b> - defines a set of codes with meanings (also known as enumeration, terminology, classification, and/or ontology)</li>
<li> <b>value set</b> - selects a set of codes from those defined by one or more code systems</li>
</ul>
<p>
Code systems define which codes (symbols and/or expressions) exist, and how they are understood. Value Sets specify 
which codes can be used in a particular context.
</p>
<p>
Value sets may be constructed in one of two ways:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A value set can <i>define</i> its own codes (e.g. an in-line simple code system definition), and/or</li>
 <li>A value set can be <i>composed</i> of codes defined in other code systems, either by listing the codes or by providing a set of selection criteria</li>
</ul>
<p>
A value set can also be "expanded", where the value set is turned into a simple collection of enumerated codes.
This operation is performed to produce a collection of codes that are ready to use for data entry or 
validation. An expanded value set may also contain the original definition as well. 
</p>
<p>
Value sets that define their own codes are effectlvely providing inline code system definitions.
These are intended for small, simple code systems that are found throughout the implementation
context (e.g. lists of wards, status codes, enumerations). The inline code system definition is 
not intended to represent large publically defined terminologies such as LOINC etc - these have
their own distributions formats .
</p>
</div>
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<ul>
 <li>Value sets are used in <a href="structuredefinition.html">StructureDefinitions</a>, and <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaires</a> to specify the allowable contents for coded elements</li>
 <li>In addition, a specific <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a> can reference the value set it was picked from</li>
 <li><a href="conceptmap.html">Concept Maps</a> describe mappings between value sets</li>
 <li>The ValueSet resource design is based on the functionality described in the <a href="http://www.omg.org/spec/CTS2/1.0/">OMG CTS 2</a> specification, along 
 with metadata in the HL7 Value Set Definition specification. Value set resources can be converted to CTS2 
 value set and code system resources</li>
 <li>The value set resource is aligned with the <a href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Value_Set_Definition_Standard_Project">Value Set Definition</a> (VSD) project. 
 Not all the elements defined by the VSD are part of the base resource - some are defined as part of the <a href="valueset-extensions.html">ValueSet Extensions</a>.
 In the ValueSet resource, the <code>lockedDate</code>, <code>compose</code> and <code>define</code> elements make up the VSD Content Logical definition</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>

<p>
When using value sets, proper differentiation between a code system and a value set is important. 
This is one very common area where significant clinical safety risks occur in practice. Implementers
should be familiar with the content in <a href="terminologies.html">Using Codes in resources</a>.
</p>
<p>
Each value set has 2 different URLs that can be used to reference it, its logical identifier, and 
its location. 
</p>
<p>
The location of the value set is a URL by which it may be retrieved, usually from a FHIR 
server, and is often a relative reference to a value set on the same server. 
The logical identifier is in the value set itself, in 
<a href="valueset-definitions.html#ValueSet.identifier">ValueSet.identifier</a>. This 
is the logical identity (sometimes called the canonical URL) that refers to this 
value set across all systems. Ideally, the URL should also be the location of the 
master version of the value set, though this is not always possible. 
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
For example, the value sets published as part of FHIR all have a logical URL
which is also a location by which they may be accessed in the FHIR specification
itself. However, while a new version of the FHIR Specification is being prepared,
value sets that are published in the drafts will not be found in the current FHIR
specification. 
</p>
<p>
Because it is common practice to copy (cache) value sets locally, most 
references to value sets can either be logical or literal URL. 
</p>

</blockquote>

<h3>ValueSet Identification</h3>
<p>
A value set has 3 identifiers:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>ValueSet.id: the local identifier on the system that holds it - this changes as it moves from server to server (this, the the server address prepended, is called the 'literal identity' of the resource)</li>
 <li>ValueSet.url: the master identifier that never changes for this value set - the same in every copy (this is called the 'logical identity' of the resource)</li>
 <li>ValueSet.identifier: A system/value pair that is used to identify the value set in other contexts (such as an OID in an HL7 V3 specification)</li>
</ul>
<p>
For further information, see <a href="resource.html#id">Resource Identity</a>.
</p>
</div>

</div>

