<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
The <i>identifier</i> and <i>version</i> elements may be used to reference this value set in a design, a profile, a 
 CDA template or V3 message (valueSet and valueSetVersion). These different contexts may make additional restrictions 
 on the possible values of these elements.
</p>

<h2>
Notes for "Code System" kind:
</h2>
<ul>
 <li>The "system" value for the defined codes is the <i>ValueSet.definition.system</i>. If that has no value, then 
   it's the <i>ValueSet.identifier</i>, which must be a proper URI in this case. If that has no value, it's the URL of the resource itself</li>
 <li>The usability of the codes is closely linked to the quality of the definitions. Although a definition is not required for each concept, 
   providing a good definition is highly encouraged</li>
</ul>

<h2>
Notes for "Composition" kind:
</h2>
<ul>
<li>The content of the value set is a union of all the import and include statements and then with any excluded codes eliminated</li>
<li>A value set needs to do something.  It can't simply include an existing value set without also including additional content or excluding content</li>
<li>The point of declaring that this value set restricts another is that this value set can then replace the other in a profile 
without changing the meaning. Declaring this explicitly allows profile tools to reason about the relationship without having 
to compute the relationship, which might not be possible for a profile tool</li>
<li>Using the property filters is only possible where the underlying code system defines appropriate properties. 
  Note that in some cases, the underlying code system defines the logical concepts but not the literal codes for 
  the concepts. In such cases, the literal definitions may be provided by a third party</li>
<li>Within an include or exclude criterion, multiple filters and concept selections are intersected.  In other words, all the conditions specified must be true.</li>
</ul>

<h2>
Notes for "Expansion" kind:
</h2>
<ul>
 <li>When the codes are in a hierarchy, they </li>
 <li></li>
</ul>



</div>
