<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Identifier and Version</h2>
<p>
The <i>identifier</i> and <i>version</i> elements may be used to reference this value set in a design, a profile, a 
CDA template or V3 message (valueSet and valueSetVersion). These different contexts may make additional restrictions 
on the possible values of these elements.  These elements are generally not needed when using value sets with FHIR
implementations as they can make use of the innate identifier and versioning mechanism associated with the resource
</p>

<h2>Value Sets that define codes</h2>

<p>
Value sets can define their own codes. A value set that defines codes automatically includes all 
the codes it defines, and is useful for simple sets of codes that are highly 
specific and context-dependent. The value set and the code system are both 
given URI identifiers by which they may be identified from elsewhere 
(ValueSet.identifier and ValueSet.define.system). These identifiers SHALL 
be different.
</p>
<ul>
 <li><i>ValueSet.define.system</i> is the URI that identifies these codes 
   when used in a <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a></li>
 <li>The usability of the codes is closely linked to the quality of the definitions. 
   Although a definition is not required for each concept, a good definition SHOULD be provided. In the absence of any definition, there is no formal meaning associated with the concept</li>
 <li>If concepts contain other concepts, then the contained concepts are "subsumed" by 
   the containing concept (there is an "is-a" relationship between the codes).</li>
  <li>An abstract concept SHALL have contained concepts</li>
  <li>The set of codes defined SHALL NOT contain duplicate codes</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note: Value sets only define their own codes when they are not defined elsewhere,
such as codes defined in SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm etc. To specify a value set that
is made up of codes from other code systems, see "compose" below. 
</p>

<a name="versioning"> </a>
<h3>Versioning Code Systems</h3>
<p>
Most code systems evolve over time, due to corrections, clarifications, and changes to approach or underlying knowledge or reality.
If these changes lead to the meanings of existing codes changing significantly, then the interpretation of the code system becomes
version dependent. This significantly complicates implementation based on the code system, to the point where it is not clear that
safety can be assured, so SHOULD be avoided whenever possible. It is preferable to assign a new identifier to a code system 
when any concepts in it have a significant change in meaning (for example, the German diagnostic classification code system 
ICD10GM2009 has a different <i>system</i> to ICD10GM2008), but this also can have substantial impact on implementation, so 
is often not practical - for instance, <a href="snomedct.html">SNOMED CT</a> has a complex version release framework, which
may lead to variations in meaning of concepts, but there is only one identifier for LOINC. 
</p>
<p>
For this reason, a code system MAY provide a version identifer in <i>ValueSet.define.version</i>. The version specific identifier SHOULD be 
provided whenever there are potentially significant changes in meaning across multiple releases of a code system.
There is no particular format requirement for the version identifier, though HL7 recommends a date based approach. 
</p>
<p>
When the value set definition of a code system includes a version identifier, the version identifier SHOULD be 
used in <a href="datatypes.html#coding">Coding</a> instances that refer to the code system. 
</p>
<p>
Where the terminology does not clearly define what string should be used to identify code system versions, the recommendation is to use the date (expressed in FHIR date format) on which that version was officially published as the version date.
</p>



<h2>Value Sets that include codes defined elsewhere</h2>

<p>
Value sets that include codes defined in some other code system are most useful when 
dealing with large general code systems such as SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm or various IETF code sets 
including human language. The value set can be a simple list of included codes or it can be some 
kind of general selection criteria using the facilities provided by the code system. 
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Within an include or exclude criterion, multiple filters and concept selections are intersected. All the 
   conditions specified SHALL be true.</li>
 <li>The value set always includes any codes it defines itself. A typical use for this
    is when including a set of codes from elsewhere, and adding a few additional codes to cover
    cases not catered to by the included codes</li>
 <li>An include statement consists of any enumerated codes and any codes that meet the filter criteria</li>
 <li>If the system reference is not version specific and filters are present, then the contents of the value set are open and change 
    over time as the underlying code systems are updated</li>
 <li>The content of the value set is constructed by unioning of all the import and include statements and then 
  eliminating any of the 'excluded' codes.</li>
 <li>A value set needs to do something.  It can't simply include an existing value set without 
   also including additional content or excluding content</li>
<!--
 <li>The point of declaring that this value set restricts another is that this value set can then replace the other in a profile 
without changing the meaning. Declaring this explicitly allows profile tools to reason about the relationship without having 
to compute the relationship, which might not be possible for a profile tool</li>
-->
 <li>Using the property filters is only possible where the underlying code system defines 
  appropriate properties. Note that in some cases, the underlying code system defines the 
  logical concepts but not the syntax for exercising them. In such cases, the literal 
  definitions may be provided by a third party. See below for notes about its use against common code systems</li>
 <li>Value sets may include abstract codes - that is, codes designated by the underlying code system as 
   not for use as a real concept. These abstract codes are typically used as a grouping/searching mechanism,
   and can be included either by enumerating them, or by using a filter</li>
</ul>
<p>
When a value set enumerates codes, it is also able to define an alternative display for 
the code that is to be used where ever the value set is expanded and used in a UI. This 
facility is provided to cover the following circumstances:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>The system that defines the code or expression doesn't provide a display for this code (or any codes)</li>
 <li>The system that defines the code or expression defines multiple choices for display</li>
 <li>The system provides a very long display name that is unnecessary or inappropriate in the context of this value set (e.g. a display name of "Glucose [Mass/volume] in Serum or Plasma --10 PM specimen" for LOINC code 48991-4, when the value set only includes Glucose mass/vol in serum/plasma codes). As the display names get longer, this becomes more important</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note that care must be taken in order to avoid "changing the meaning" of the concept by
implying that it means something other than the explicit definition of the concept in the
underlying system (e.g. in the case above, using a display "Glucose Concentration at 10pm"). 
For this reason, some contexts of use do not allow a display to be associated with a specific code.
</p>
<p>
The display name for the code in the value set is only used in the UI. The display in a 
a <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a> must be taken from the underlying system, 
even if a value set is referenced explicitly in the Coding. The alternative display 
specified in the value set would go in <a href="datatypes.html#CodeableConcept">CodeableConcept</a>.text.
</p>
 
<h3>Code systems Note</h3>
<p>
How filters are used with various code systems:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="loinc.html">Using LOINC with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="snomedct.html">Using SNOMED CT with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="rxnorm.html">Using RxNorm with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="ucum.html">Using UCUM with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="ncimeta.html">Using NCI Metathesaurus with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="cpt.html">Using CPT with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="ndfrt.html">Using NDF-RT with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="unii.html">Using UNII with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="ndc.html">Using NDC with FHIR</a></li>
 <li><a href="cvx.html">Using CVX with FHIR</a></li>
</ul>

<table class="grid">
 <tr>
   <th>System</th>    
   <th>Property Name</th> 
   <th>Operation</th> 
   <th>Value</th>        
   <th>Definition</th>
   <th>Example</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td>V3 Code systems</td> 
   <td>concept</td>
   <td>is-a</td>       
   <td>[code]</td>    
   <td>Includes all codes that have a transitive is-a relationship with the concept identified by the value</td> 
   <td><a href="valueset-relatedperson-relationshiptype.html">Relationship Type</a></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td>V2 Tables</td> 
   <td></td>
   <td></td>       
   <td></td>    
   <td>(no filters defined)</td> 
   <td></td>
 </tr>
</table>

<a name="expansion"> </a>
<h2>Value Set Expansion</h2>
<p>
A value set can be "expanded", where the definition of the value set is 
used to create a simple collection of codes suitable for use for data 
entry or validation. This is most useful when a value set includes 
all the codes in a code system, or a set of codes by filter. 
</p>
<p>
A resource that represents a value set expansion includes the same
identification details as the definition of the value set, and MAY
include the definition of the value set (<i>define</i> and <i>compose</i>
elements). In addition it has a <i>expansion</i> element which contains
the list of codes that constitute the value set expansion. 
If the expansion has nested <code>contains</code> elements, there is 
no implication about the logical relationship between them, and the 
structure cannot be used for logical inferencing. The structure 
exists to provide navigational assistance for helping human users to 
locate codes in the expansion.
</p>
<p>
When a request for an expansion is received (e.g. for the <a href="valueset-operations.html#expand">$expand</a> operation,
the following process should be followed:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>If the value set already has an expansion (e.g. a stored expansion), simply take the existing expansion as it is. If not, then:</li>
 <li>for each <i>compose.import</i>, find the referenced value set by ValueSet.url, expand that (e.g. using the <a href="valueset-operations.html#expand">$expand</a> operation: GET [base]/ValueSet/$expand$identifier=[compose.import]), and add it to the result set. This means that expansion across imports is a recursive process</li>
 <li>for each <i>compose.include</i>, identify the correct version of the code system, and then:
  <ul>
   <li>if there are no codes or filters, add every code in the code system to the result set</li>
   <li>if codes are listed, add them to the result set</li>
   <li>if any filters are present, process them in order (as explained above), and add the intersection of their results to the result set</li>
  </ul>
 </li>
 <li>for each <i>compose.exclude</i>, follow the same process as for <i>compose.include</i>, but remove any codes from the result set, instead of adding them</li>
 <li>add any codes in the <i>define</i> to the result set</li>
</ul>
<p>
The "result set" is then represented in <i>expansion</i>. Note that the expansion structure is inherently ordered, and 
also provides support for a hierarchical tree of items. This specification does not fix the meaning of use of either
of these, and the conceptual approach described should not be understood to prohibit any implementation approach in
these regards. There is a <a href="valueset-operations.html">defined operation</a> to ask a server to perform this expansion.
</p>
<p>
An expansion may include entries in the expansion that only serve an arbitrary grouping purpose, to make it easier
for a human to use the list. These entries have no system or code, and must be marked as abstract. Note that the 
value set define and compose offer no support for defining these, but this does not exclude servers from using
extensions or other knowledge to introduce such groups as an implementation feature. 
</p>
<p>
Whether to store expanded value sets, or simply to store their definitions, and expand on the fly is 
a matter for system deployment. Some servers, including public value sets servers, only store expansions. 
However any system that stores an expansion must be concerned with how to determine whether the expansion 
is still current, and this requires deep knowledge of how the expansion was created. 
</p>
<p>
A system with a dedicated terminology server that returns expansions on demand avoids this problem, but 
leaves open the question of how to audit the specific expansion that was used for a particular case. 
One solution to this is to use a dedicated terminology server, and have the clients ask for 
expansions on demand based on the value set definitions, and for the server to store (and reuse as 
appropriate) the returned expansion (when it reuses the expansion, ValueSet.expansion.identifier will
be the same).
</p>

<a name="detailed-metadata"/>
<h3>Code systems with detailed metadata</h3>
<p>
Sometimes code systems may be used to represent more complex information than just 
code, display name and code system.  For example, a code system of drug information
which contains information about the content of the medication (e.g. RxNorm), or a set of  
observation types, that contain methods, units, etc (e.g. LOINC).  
In FHIR, these are handled by splitting the concept into two distinct parts - the 
<b>ValueSet</b> resource is used to manage the codes, display names and relationships.  
A separate "detail" resource (e.g. <a href="medication.html">Medication</a> for 
drugs, <a href="dataelement.html">DataElement</a> for observation types, 
<a href="location.html">Location</a> for location, etc.) is used to convey detailed 
information (dose form &amp; strength, allowed data type or permitted values, address &amp;
hours of operation, etc.)  One "detail" resource instance is created for each code.
</p>
<p>
This division accomplishes several things:
</p>
<ul>
<li>It allows generic systems that support terminology management to perform standard 
terminology operations on code systems dealing with complex structures - code lookup, 
validation, subsumption testing, mapping and translation.</li>
<li>It allows information to be exchanged about individual medications, data elements 
and locations.  Codes can't be retrieved individually in FHIR - it is necessary to 
retrieve the entire resource.  By packaging the detailed information in separate 
resources, independent retrieval and update is possible.</li>
<li>It supports use-cases for sharing medication, location, observation type and 
similar information in circumstances where the code may be unknown, unavailable or 
occasionally non-existent (e.g. custom compounds, non-registered locations).  Having 
a distinct resource supports these capabilties which would not be possible using 
<b>ValueSet</b>.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note that this division in FHIR does not imply that a similar division is required in 
the internal representation used by systems exposing a FHIR interface.  Similarly, some 
systems may choose to only expose or maintain one aspect of such information types (i.e. 
only the discrete resource instances or only the value set.)
</p>
<p>
The linkage between the "detail" resource and the <b>ValueSet</b> is accomplished via the 
<code>code</code> element (or equivalent) on the detail resource.  As well, the "name" or 
"title" on the detail resource generally corresponds with the display name on the matching 
code.  Most detail resources will also have an "identifier" element.  This <i>can</i> be
set to the same value and namespace as the code, but if the only identifier a resource has
is its defining code, it may be better to omit the identifier entirely.
</p>

</div>
