<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Identifier and Version</h2>
<p>
The <i>identifier</i> and <i>version</i> elements may be used to reference this value set in a design, a profile, a 
CDA template or V3 message (valueSet and valueSetVersion). These different contexts may make additional restrictions 
on the possible values of these elements.  These elements are generally not needed when using value sets with FHIR
implementations as they can make use of the innate identifier and versioning mechanism associated with the resource
</p>

<h2>Value Sets that define codes</h2>

<p>
Valuesets can define their own codes. A value set that defines codes automatically includes all 
the codes it defines, and is useful for simple sets of codes that are highly 
specific and context-dependent. The value set and the code system are both 
given URI identifiers by which they may be identified from elsewhere 
(ValueSet.identifier and ValueSet.define.system). These identifiers SHALL 
be different.
</p>
<ul>
 <li><i>ValueSet.define.system</i> is the URI that identifies these codes 
   when used in a <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a></li>
 <li>The usability of the codes is closely linked to the quality of the definitions. 
   Although a definition is not required for each concept, a good definition SHOULD be provided. In the absence of any definition, there is no formal meaning associated with the concept</li>
 <li>If concepts contain other concepts, then the contained concepts are "subsumed" by 
   the containing concept (there is an "is-a" relationship between the codes).</li>
  <li>An abstract concept SHALL have contained concepts</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note: Value sets only define their own codes when they are not defined elsewhere,
such as codes defined in SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm etc. To specify a value set that
is made up of codes from other code systems, see "compose" below. 
</p>

<a name="versioning"> </a>
<h3>Versioning Code Systems</h3>
<p>
Most code systems evolve over time, due to corrections, clarifications, and changes to approach or underlying knowledge or reality.
If these changes lead to the meanings of existing codes changing significantly, then the interpretation of the code system becomes
version dependent. This significantly complicates implementation based on the code system, to the point where it is not clear that
safety can be assured, so SHOULD be avoided whenever possible. It is preferable to assign a new identifier to a code system 
when any concepts in it have a significant change in meaning (for example, the German diagnostic classification code system 
ICD10GM2009 has a different <i>system</i> to ICD10GM2008), but this also can have substantial impact on implementation, so 
is often not practical - for instance, <a href="http://loinc.org">LOINC</a> has re-defined the meaning of codes in the past,
but there is only one identifier for LOINC. 
</p>
<p>
For this reason, a code system MAY provide a version identifer in <i>ValueSet.define.version</i>. The version specific identifier SHOULD be 
provided whenever there are potentially significant changes in meaning across multiple releases of a code system.
There is no particular format requirement for the version identifier, though HL7 recommends a date based approach. 
</p>
<p>
When the value set definition of a code system includes a version identifier, the version identifier SHOULD be 
used in <a href="datatypes.html#coding">Coding</a> instances that refer to the code system. 
</p>


<h2>Value Sets that include codes defined elsewhere</h2>

<p>
Value sets that include codes defined in some other code system are most useful when 
dealing with large general code systems such as SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm or various IETF code sets 
including human language. The value set can be a simple list of included codes or it can be some 
kind of general selection criteria using the facilities provided by the code system. 
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Within an include or exclude criterion, multiple filters and concept selections are intersected. All the 
   conditions specified SHALL be true.</li>
 <li>The value set always includes any codes it defines itself. A typical use for this
    is when including a set of codes from elsewhere, and adding a few additional codes to cover
    cases not catered to by the included codes</li>
 <li>An include statement consists of any enumerated codes and any codes that meet the filter criteria</li>
 <li>If the system reference is not version specific and filters are present, then the contents of the value set are open and change 
    over time as the underlying code systems are updated</li>
 <li>The content of the value set is constructed by unioning of all the import and include statements and then 
  eliminating any of the 'excluded' codes.</li>
 <li>A value set needs to do something.  It can't simply include an existing value set without 
   also including additional content or excluding content</li>
<!--
 <li>The point of declaring that this value set restricts another is that this value set can then replace the other in a profile 
without changing the meaning. Declaring this explicitly allows profile tools to reason about the relationship without having 
to compute the relationship, which might not be possible for a profile tool</li>
-->
 <li>Using the property filters is only possible where the underlying code system defines 
  appropriate properties. Note that in some cases, the underlying code system defines the 
  logical concepts but not the syntax for exercising them. In such cases, the literal 
  definitions may be provided by a third party. See below for notes about its use against common code systems</li>
</ul>

<h3>Code systems Note</h3>
<p>
How filters are used with various code systems:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr>
   <th>System</th>    
   <th>Property Name</th> 
   <th>Operation</th> 
   <th>Value</th>        
   <th>Definition</th>
   <th>Example</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td>SNOMED CT</td>          
   <td>expression</td>
   <td>=</td>       
   <td>[expression]</td> 
   <td>The result of the filter is the result of executing the given SNOMED CT expression 
    (see the draft <a href="http://www.ihtsdo.org/fileadmin/user_upload/Docs_01/News/SNOMED_CT_Query_Specification_-__v0.08_-_20121213.doc"> SNOMED CT Query Language</a>)</td> 
   <td>(no example yet)</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td></td> 
   <td>concept</td>
   <td>is-a</td>       
   <td>[concept]</td>    
   <td>Includes all concept ids that have a transitive is-a relationship with the concept Id provided as the value <br/>The SNOMED CT Query Language expression for this is DescendentsAndSelf([concept])</td> 
   <td><a href="valueset-administration-method-codes.html">Administation Methods</a></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td></td> 
   <td>concept</td>
   <td>in</td>       
   <td>[concept]</td>    
   <td>Includes all concept ids that are in the reference set identified by the concept Id provided as the value <br/>The SNOMED CT Query Language expression for this is MembersOf([concept])</td> 
   <td><a href="valueset-administration-method-codes.html">Administation Methods</a></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td colspan="4"><hr/></td>
 </tr>
 
 <tr>
   <td>LOINC</td> 
   <td>[property]</td>
   <td>= / regex</td>       
   <td>[value]</td>    
   <td>Includes all codes where the named property has the given value. Valid Property Names are all the names listed in the 
     "Field Name" column in LOINC Database Structure (Appendix A of the LOINC manual). 
     Of these, the 6 properties COMPONENT, PROPERTY, TIME_ASPCT, SYSTEM, SCALE_TYP, and METHOD_TYP are most likely to be useful. 
     In addition, the following 5 property names are defined in the Document Ontology: Document.Kind, Document.TypeOfService, Document.Setting, Document.Role, and Document.SubjectMatterDomain.
   </td> 
   <td><a href="valueset-doc-codes.html">Document Codes</a></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td></td>      
   <td>Type</td>        
   <td>=</td>       
   <td>Method</td>       
   <td>All the LOINC codes for particular methods defined in LOINC</td> 
   <td><a href="valueset-observation-methods.html">Observation Methods</a></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
   <td colspan="4"><hr/></td>
 </tr>
 
 <tr>
   <td>V3 Code systems</td> 
   <td>concept</td>
   <td>is-a</td>       
   <td>[code]</td>    
   <td>Includes all codes that have a transitive is-a relationship with the concept identified by the value</td> 
   <td><a href="valueset-relatedperson-relationshiptype.html">Relationship Type</a></td>
 </tr>
 
</table>

<a name="expansion"> </a>
<h2>Value Set Expansion</h2>
<p>
A value set can be "expanded", where the definition of the value set is 
used to create a simple collection of codes suitable for use for data 
entry or validation. This is most useful when a value set includes 
all the children of a code or a set of codes by filter.
</p>
<p>
A resource that represents a value set expansion includes the same
identification details as the definition of the value set, and MAY
include the definition of the value set (<i>define</i> and <i>compose</i>
elements). In addition it has a <i>expansion</i> element which contains
the list of codes that constitute the value set expansion. If the 
expansion is heirarchical (codes contain other concepts), there 
is no implication about the logical relationship between them; this 
is guidance for helping human user navigate the choice of codes that 
may or may not relate to the logical definitions of the codes or concepts.
</p>
<p>
In general, the following process should be followed when 
expanding a value set:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>for each <i>compose.import</i>, find the referenced value set, expand that, and add it to the result set</li>
 <li>for each <i>compose.include</i>, identify the correct version of the code system, and then:
  <ul>
   <li>if there is no codes or filters, add every code in the code system to the result set</li>
   <li>if codes are listed, add them to the result set</li>
   <li>if any filters are present, process them in order (as explained above), and add the intersection of their results to the result set</li>
  </ul>
 </li>
 <li>for each <i>compose.exclude</i>, follow the same process as for <i>compose.include</i>, but remove any codes from the result set, instead of adding them</li>
 <li>add any codes in the <i>define</i> to the result set</li>
</ul>
<p>
The "result set" is then represented in <i>expansion</i>. Note that the expansion structure is inherently ordered, and 
also provides support for a hierarchical tree of codes. This specification does not fix the meaning of use of either
of these, and the conceptual approach described should not be understood to prohibit any implementation approach in
these regards.
</p>
<p>
An application MAY offer to expand value sets for other applications. In this 
case, the standard way to produce a value set expansion is to perform a 
<a href="search.html">query</a> on the value set with _query=expand:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [service-url]/ValueSet/?_query=expand&amp;id=:valueSet&amp;...
</pre>
<p>
This is a request to produce a value set expansion for the value set
with the provided id which is either a logical id, or an absolute reference to a value set. 
The value set can be identified by other means, such as identifier and version. 
Servers can define their own additional parameters that influence the expansion 
process, such in relation to order and hierarchy.
</p>
<p>
The value set expansion returned by this query should be treated 
as a transient result that will change over time (whether it does or
not depends on how the value set is specified), so applications 
should repeat the query each time the value set is used.
</p>
<h2>Value Set Validation</h2>
<p>
An application may offer to provide code validation services for other 
applications. In this case, the standard way for an application to 
ask for validation is to perform a 
<a href="search.html">query</a> on the value set with _query=validate:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [service-url]/ValueSet/?_query=validate&amp;id=:valueSet&amp;system=:system&amp;version=:version&amp;code=:code&amp;...
</pre>
<p>
The values for system, version, and code are those from the <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a> data type.
Version is optional, and code and system are mandatory. Additionally, the parameter "coding" or "codeableconcept" 
can be used - the value of these parameters is a URL encoded XML or JSON representation of the two data types
respectively. An additional boolean parameter "extensible" can be provided to specify whether the
applicable binding is extensible or not.
</p>
<p>
The result of this query is an <a href="operationoutcome.html">Operation Outcome</a>.
If there are no errors in the outcome (OperationOutcome.issue.severity), then the code is considered
to be valid.
</p>


</div>
