<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
			Appointment resources are used to provide information about
			a planned meeting that may be in the future or past.  The resource only describes a single meeting,
			a series of repeating visits would require multiple appointment resources be created for each instance.
			Examples include a scheduled surgery, a follow-up for a
			clinical visit, a scheduled conference call between clinicians to discuss a case, the reservation
			of a piece of diagnostic equipment for a particular use, etc.
			The visit scheduled by an appointment
			may be in person or remote (by phone, video conference, etc.)  All that matters is that the time and
			usage of one or more individuals, locations and/or pieces of equipment is being fully or partially
			reserved for a designated period of time.
		</p>
		<p>
			This definition takes the concepts of appointments in a clinical setting and also extends
			them to be relevant in the community healthcare space, and also ease exposure to other
			appointment / calendar standards widely used outside of healthcare.
		</p>

    <h3>The basic workflow to create an appointment</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<b>Discovery/Addressing</b>
				<p>
					Before an appointment can be made the address of the resource that we want to schedule
					an appointment with must be determined. This is often based on the healthcare Service Type,
					any formatting information which indicates how to make the request.
					This is typically handled via the Schedule resource.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<b>Checking Availability on the Schedule(optional)</b>
				<p>
					This optional step permits the checking of any existing available times 
					(<a href="slot.html">slot</a> resources associated with a selected <a href="schedule.html">schedule</a>) that can be booked against.
					Just because a time is indicated it is available doesn't guarantee that an appointment can be made.
					The booking system that is going to process the request may make other qualifying decisions to
					determine if the appointment can be made, such as permissions, assessments, availability of other
					resources etc.
				</p>
				<p>
					This step is optional as the creation of the appointment is never a guaranteed action.
					But by performing this availability check, you can increase the chances of making a successful
					booking.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<b>Making the Appointment Request</b>
				<p>
					The request is performed by posting an Appointment to the address found during discovery.
					This will have a needs-action status for each of the participants.
					(The system that receives the request may modify the status of any posted appointment based
					on internal business rules, such as certain users do not have permission to request certain
					appointments)
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<b>Replying to the request</b>
				<p>
					The reply process is simply performed by the person/system handing the requests updating
					the Participant Statuses as needed. If there are multiple systems involved, then these
					will create AppointmentResponse entries with the desired statuses.
				</p>
				<p>
					Once all participants have their participation status created/updated
					(and the main system marking the appointment participant records with the AppointmentResponse
					statuses) then the overall status of the appointment is updated.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<b>Checking the overall status (Requester)</b>
				<p>
					The Requester (organizer) of the appointment checks for the overall status of the appointment
					(and appointmentresponses where applicable) using fhir pub-sub techniques.
				</p>
				<p>
					Where the participant statuses indicate that a re-scheduling is required, then the process may
					start again, with other systems replying to a new set of times.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>

		<h3>There are 2 typical workflows that occur with appointments</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<b>Outlook Style - Community</b>
				<p>
					These types of requests are typically handled by selecting a specific time from a list of available slots.
					Then making the request for that timeslot.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<b>Hospital Scheduling - Clinical</b>
				<p>
					Clinical scheduling is often far more complex in its requirements and processing.
					Often this involves checking multiple availabilities across multiple systems and
					timing with other internal systems, not just those exposed by the Slot resources.
				</p>
				<p>
					Consideration should be given to situations where scheduling needs to be handled
					in more of a queue-like process.
				</p>
				<p>
					Note: This type of clinical appointment scheduling has not been specifically covered
					with this definition of the appointment (and the related resources), however if you
					would like to contribute to the modification of this resource to cover these use cases,
					please contact the HL7 Patient Administration work-group.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</div>
  <div>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

    <h3>Appointment Statuses and Encounters</h3>
    <p>
      Appointments can be considered as Administrative only, and the Encounter is expected to have
      Clinical implications.
    </p>
    <p>
      In general it is expected that appointments will result in the creation of an Encounter.
      The encounter is typically created when the service starts, not when the patient arrives.
      When the patient arrives, an appointment can be marked with a status of Arrived.
    </p>
    <p>
      In an Emergency Room context, this appointment resource is probably not appropriate to be used.
      In these cases an encounter should be created.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Appointment request pattern used is different to the order-response pattern used elsewhere in FHIR.<br/>
      This is due to the close relationship to the iCAL standard. Many non-clinical systems use generic
      non health appointment systems which implement this standard, and the desire to integrate
      with the consumer who has no access to health based software is highly desirable.<br/>
      The mappings to the iCAL standard has been provided to guide implementation of gateways between
      FHIR servers and iCAL systems.
    </p>
		<h3>Appointment Locations and Participation</h3>
		<p>
			The Location of the appointment is to be defined by using a participant that references a location
			or HealthcareService.<br/>
			This permits the location to also have its availability checked via a schedule and any
			conflicts more easily managed.
		</p>
  </div>
</div>
