<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<a name="notes"></a>
<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul> 
 <li>The author and the attester are often the same person, but this might not be the case in some clinical workflows.</li>
 <li>The attester attests contents of the document resource, the subject resource and the resources referred to 
   in the Composition.section.content references. Because documents are often derived Compositions and the attestation
   from the composition is held to apply to the document, the method for <a href="documents.html#presentation">presenting a document</a>
   should be used when/if attesters review the content of the composition.
   </li>
 <li>The custodian is responsible for the maintenance of the composition and any documents derived from it. With regard to the documents, they are 
   responsible for the policy regarding persistence of the documents. Although they need not actually retain a copy of the document, they SHOULD do so.
 </li>
 <li>It is acceptable for a Composition to contain only narrative (<code>Composition.section.text</code>) and no entries (<code>Composition.section.entry</code>)</li>
</ul>  

<a name="mixed"></a>
<h2>
Compositions about multiple entities
</h2>
<p>
Typically, a composition is made about the subject - e.g. a patient, or group of patients, location, or device - and the 
distinction between the subject and the composition describes the subject. Some kinds of documents contain data about other 
parties or entities that are relevant to the subject of the document. Some examples:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A neonatal discharge summary that contains information about the mother</li>
 <li>A family history document that contains multiple sections for different family members</li>
 <li>A social health evaluation document that contains information about the patient's family members</li>
 <li>A procedure report that contains details about a device implanted in the patient</li>
</ul>
<p>
In all these cases, the subject of the document is a single patient, but some of the details are actually
related to other persons or entities. When this happens, these other entities are detailed in the <code>Composition.section.focus</code> element.
In the absence of a <code>focus</code>, it is assumed that the <code>subject</code> of the composition is the focus. 
</p>
<p>
If a <code>focus</code> is specified, then the resources referred to from the section SHALL 
either:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>specify that their <code>subject</code> (however named e.g. <code>patient</code>) or <code>focus</code> element (if present) is the focus indicated</li>
 <li>not have a <code>subject</code> element</li>
</ul>
<p>
A few compositions genuinely cover multiple subjects - different sections are about different subjects. In such
case, <code>Composition.subject</code> is omitted, and the extension <a href="[%extensions-location%]StructureDefinition-composition-section-subject.html">section-subject</a>
is used on each section to indicate the subject.
</p>

[%stu-note dstu%]
Feedback is welcome on two issues related to Composition:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>For many compositions, the title is the same as the text or a display name of Composition.type (e.g., a "consultation" or "progress note"). Note that <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> does not make title mandatory, but there are no known cases where it is useful for title to be omitted, so it is mandatory here during the trial use period.</li>
 <li>A client can ask a server to generate a fully bundled document from a Composition resource using the $document operation. This operation definition does not resolve the question how document signatures are created. This is an open issue during the period of trial use, and feedback is requested regarding this question.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Feedback <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir-issues">here</a>.
[%end-note%]

</div>
