<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p> 
A Composition is also the basic structure from which <a href="documents.html">FHIR Documents</a> - 
immutable bundles with attested narrative - are built. A single logical composition may be 
associated with a series of derived documents, each of which is a frozen copy of the 
composition.
</p>

<p>
Note: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EN_13606">EN 13606</a> uses the term "Composition" 
to refer to a single commit to an EHR system, and offers some common examples: a consultation 
note, a progress note, a report or a letter, an investigation report, a prescription form 
and a set of bedside nursing observations. These logical examples are all valid uses of a 
Composition resource, but it is not required that all the resources are updated in 
a single commit.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<a name="status"> </a>
<h3>Composition Status Codes</h3>
<p>
Every composition has a status, which describes the status of the content of the composition, taken from this list of codes:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr> <td><b>Code</b></td> <td><b>Definition</b></td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>preliminary</td> <td>This is a preliminary composition (also known as initial or interim). The content may be incomplete or unverified.</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>final</td> <td>The composition is complete and verified by an appropriate person and no further work is planned</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>appended</td> <td>The composition has been modified subsequent to being marked and/or released as "final" and is complete and verified by an authorized person. The modifications added new information to the composition, but did not revise existing content</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>amended</td> <td>The composition content or the referenced resources have been modified subsequent to being released as "final" and the composition is complete and verified by an authorized person</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>retracted</td> <td>The composition was originally created/issued in error and this is an amendment that marks that the entire composition and any past versions or copies should not be considered as valid</td> </tr>
</table>
<p>
Composition status generally only moves down through this list - it moves from preliminary to final and then it may progress to either appended or amended. 
Note that in many workflows, only final compositions are made available and the preliminary status is not used. 
</p>
<p>
A very few compositions are created entirely in error in the workflow - usually the composition concerns the wrong patient or is written by the wrong author,
and the error is only detected after the composition has been used or documents have been derived from it. To support resolution of this case, 
the composition is updated to be marked as "retracted" and a new derived document can be created. This means that the entire series of derived 
documents is now considered to be created in error and systems receiving derived documents based on retracted compositions
SHOULD remove data taken from earlier documents from routine use and/or take other appropriate actions. Systems are not required to 
provide this workflow or support documents derived from retracted compositions, but they SHALL not ignore a status of retracted. 
Note that systems that handle compositions or derived documents and don't support the retracted status need to define 
some other way of handling compositions that are created in error; while this is not a common occurrence, some clinical systems 
have no provision for removing erroneous information from a patient's record and there is no way for a user to know that it is not fit for use -
this is not safe. 
</p>
<p>
Note: for RIM-centric readers, see the <a href="composition-status.html">v3 mapping for the codes</a> and the <a href="composition-mappings.html#http://hl7.org/v3">RIM mapping for the element</a>.
</p>
</div>

</div>
