<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<blockquote class="stu-note">
<p><b>Note to Implementers:</b> For an overview of this resource and others in the Nutrition domain, also see the <a href="nutrition-module.html">module page</a>.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>This resource is an <em>event</em> resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a>.  It is the intent of the Orders and Observation Workgroup to align this resource with  the workflow  pattern for <a href="workflow.html"><em>event</em> resources</a>.</strong></p>
<p>
The NutritionIntake resource, in conjunction with the <a href="nutritionproduct.html">NutritionProduct</a> resource, is utilized to capture details about the consumption of foods (i.e., solid and/or liquid), supplements, enteral nutrition, and infant formula. Dietitians and other practitioners use the data to calculate how much nutrition a patient has taken in. NutritionIntake represents the event of consuming food (i.e. solid and/or liquid), etc. and NutritionProduct represents the actual food and formula items.
</p>
<p>
NutritionIntake can also be used to record a person’s intake through the use of food tracking apps (e.g.MyFitnessPal), inpatient hospital consumption or administration, or a student’s meal consumption in a school district.</p>
<p>
NutritionIntake can be utilized in many environments where food is served or consumed: hospitals/acute care, meal tracking systems, enteral or supplement in a home setting, outpatient settings, long-term care, etc. NutritionIntake should be general enough to capture intake regardless of country or region.
</p>
<p>
Parenteral nutrition is out of scope as this ordering is handled through MedicationRequest, thus administration of parenteral nutrition should also be captured through MedicationAdministration.
</p>
</div>


<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<ul>
	<li>Intake of food (i.e. solid and/or liquid), oral nutritional supplements, enteral nutrition, or infant formula should be recorded using the NutritionIntake resource.</li>
	<li>Supplements, such as vitamins, minerals, and herbals, should be recorded using the medication resources</li>
	<li>Parenteral nutrition should be recorded using the medication resources</li>
</ul>
</div>


<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
As a dietitian, it is important to be able to know what a person is consuming and/or administered to assess the adequacy of the patient’s intake. Capturing a patient’s intake is important to establish a baseline, determine care, track trends, and see improvement in that patient. Dietitians might use intake data to see patterns, such as when a diabetic patient’s blood glucose is consistently high given the distribution of carbohydrates.  Other practitioners have the need to monitor intake as well; for example, a nurse might need to know intake for administering insulin prior to meals, a speech therapist needs this information for ensuring safe administration of food, or a physician may need to ensure a patient fluid restriction is consistent with recommendations.
</p>
<p>
Having intake documented within its own resource allows for consistency in documentation across multiple disciplines and settings. In some instances, the Observation resource has been extended to capture intake; while this allows for a quick way to document intake, the Observation resource does not provide all the detail necessary, such as capturing energy and nutrients (including vitamins, minerals, carbohydrates, etc.). Previous implementation attempts of using the Observation resource have noted this is cumbersome and has required too many extensions without being able to document all the necessary details tied to ingredients in food (i.e., solid and/or liquid) products.
</p>
<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn">
<p><b>Note to Balloters:</b>
The <a href="valueset-nutritionintake-status-reason.html">nutritionintake-status-reason</a> code system used in NutritionIntake.statusReason is currently defined in the FHIR specification, but is expected to be moved to <a href="http://terminology.hl7.org">HL7 Terminology</a> (THO).
</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
