<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->

<h2>Notes</h2>
  <h3>Representing the Sequence</h3>
  <p>
  This resource supports three patterns for representing a sequence of interest:
  <ul>
    <li>By providing a “literal” string of IUPAC codes representing nucleotides or amino acids.</li>
    <li>By linking to a “formatted” file or link containing the sequence information (e.g. FASTA file or GA4GH sequence repository).</li>
    <li>By providing a list of “edits” from a starting sequence.</li>
  </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
  The MolecularSequence resource is designed to represent a single sequence in an instance. Each sequence might have multiple representations, but implementers SHALL ensure all representations are for the same sequence.
  </p>
  <h4>Sequence as a literal string</h4>
  <p>
    <code>MolecularSequence.literal</code>: This string element can be used to hold the sequence as a string of characters.
  </p>
  <h4>Sequence as a file or URL</h4>
  <p>
    <code>MolecularSequence.formatted</code>: This Attachment is used to refer to the sequence as embedded file content or via a URL reference.
  </p>
  <p>
    This method can be used to refer to sequence data from an an external source. If the sequence is referring to a GA4GH repository, the <code>MolecularSequence.formatted.url</code> should refer to a GA4GH compliant endpoint that conforms to GA4GH data models.
  </p>
  <h4>Sequence as a series of edits from a known sequence</h4>
  <p>
    <code>MolecularSequence.relative</code>: This complex element is used for encoding sequence. When the information of starting sequence and edits are provided, the observed sequence will be derived. Here is a picture below:
  </p>
  <img src="genomics-image34.jpg" alt="" style="width:624px;height:468px" />

  <h5>Composing multiple relative sequences into one new sequence</h5>
  <p>
    <code>MolecularSequence.relative.ordinalPosition</code>: Indicates the order in which the sequence should be considered when putting multiple <code>relative</code> together.
  </p>
  <p>
    <code>sequenceRange</code>: Indicates the nucleotide range in the composed sequence when multiple <code>relative</code> are used together
  </p>
  <p>
    These attributes help to clarify what sequence is being representing with less computation/inference on the recipient side. Implementers SHOULD use <code>sequenceRange</code> first to determine order as the most reliable. If <code>sequenceRange</code> is not present then <code>ordinalPosition</code> SHOULD be used. Finally, if both <code>sequenceRange</code> and <code>ordinalPosition</code> are absent, then the order of the <code>relative</code> data elements SHOULD be used to calculate a composition. It is the responsibility of the data sender to ensure the message can be consistently understood. Additionally, gaps in <code>sequenceRange</code> are considered intentional (i.e. the composed sequence contains a sequence of N's, the placeholder nucleotide, for the gap range.
  </p>
  <p>
    In a FGFR2:MET Fusion use case, where the fusion was uncovered through RNA sequencing, a partial representation can be found <a href="sequence-example-ordinal.html">here</a>.
  </p>
  <h5>Representing the Starting Sequence</h5>
  <p>
    <code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence</code>: There are four optional ways to represent a starting sequence in MolecularSequence resource:
    <ol>
      <li><code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.sequenceCodeableConcept</code>: Starting sequence id in public database;</li>
      <li><code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.sequenceString</code>: Starting sequence string; </li>
      <li><code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.sequenceReference</code>: Reference to starting sequence stored in another sequence entity; </li>
      <li><code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.genomeAssembly</code>, <code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.chromosome</code>: The combination of genome assembly and chromosome. </li>
    </ol>
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.windowStart</code> and <code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.windowEnd</code>defines a range from the starting sequence that is used to define a subsequence used as the starting sequence.
  </p>
  <h5>Coordinate System</h5>
  <p>
    When saving the sequence information, the nucleic acid will be numbered with order. Some representations use a 0-based system (e.g. GA4GH API, BAM files) while some use a 1-based system (e.g. VCF file format). The element coordinateSystem contains this information.
  </p>
  <p>
    <code>MolecularSequence.relative.coordinateSystem</code> binds to a LOINC answer list, please review those answers <a href="https://loinc.org/LL5323-2/">here</a> as well as the detailed description found <a href="https://loinc.org/92822-6/">here</a>.
  </p>
  <p> 
    Here are two examples:
    <ul>
      <li>0-based example: <a href="coord-0base-example.html">here</a></li>
      <li>1-based example: <a href="coord-1base-example.html">here</a></li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <h5>Choice of Strand</h5>
  <p>
    There are lots of definition concerning with the directionality of DNA or RNA. Here we are using <code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.orientation</code> and <code>MolecularSequence.relative.startingSequence.strand</code>. <b>Orientation</b> represents the sense of the sequence, which has different meanings depending on the <code>MolecularSequence.type</code>. <b>Strand</b> represents the sequence writing order. Watson strand refers to 5' to 3' top strand (5' -&gt; 3'), whereas Crick strand refers to 5' to 3' bottom strand (3' &lt;- 5').
  </p>
  <p>
    Only two possible values can be made by strand, watson and crick. Since the directionality of the sequence string might be represented in different word in different omics scenario, below are simple example of how to map other expressions into its correlated value:
  </p>
  <table style="width:100%">
    <tr>
      <th>Watson</th>
      <th>Crick</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5′-to-3′ direction</td>
      <td>3′-to-5′ direction</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>+1</td>
      <td>-1</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sense</td>
      <td>Antisense</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Positive</td>
      <td>Negative</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
<h3>Character usage for sequence as strings</h3>
<p>
  There are attributes where the sequence is represented as a string of characters.
    <ul>
      <li><code>relative.startingSequence.sequenceString</code></li>
      <li><code>relative.edit.replacementSequence</code></li>
      <li><code>relative.edit.replacedSequence</code></li>
      <li><code>literal</code></li>
    </ul>
</p>
<p>
  The characters used in these string representations of a sequence should be constrained to the IUPAC codes found here <a href="https://www.bioinformatics.org/sms2/iupac.html">https://www.bioinformatics.org/sms2/iupac.html</a>.
</p>

</div>