<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"></a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
			This is not the right relationship for short-term, highly transient relationships. Marriage, for example, is
			usually a longer term relationship, so this resource is appropriate.<br/>
			Such as:
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Represent relationship between two members</li>
			<li>Represent the certainty of the relationship</li>
			<li>Represent the temporal nature of the relationship<br/>
				(e.g., father/daughter is mostly persistent, but resident
				in household is very transient).</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
			A short term relationship such as "sat next to in a meeting" is not appropriate for this resource.<br />
			This is not the right resource for living arrangements. That may be group instead?<br />
			This is not for tracking relationship between care team and the patient. For example, the social worker
			would be a Practitioner on your Care Team.<br />
			This is not for tracking caregivers that are performing actions. For example, the lady taking you to church
			would be a RelatedPerson. But if that lady is your neighbor, then the neighbor relationship may be
			represented in this resource, though not used in tracking care.<br />
			PersonalRelationship is not to be used to represent the relationship of "provides care for". That should be
			in CareTeam.<br/>
			This is not the right resource to represent the role of the person within a group (e.g., the head of the household is the decision maker),
			that would be recorded in the Group.member.involvement element.
		</p>
		<h3>Potential use cases:</h3>
		<ul>
			<li>Public Health</li>
			<ul>
				<li>Isolation</li>
				<li>Contact tracing</li>
				<li>WIC programs</li>
				<li>Congregate housing</li>
				<li>2/15/2024 - Public Health WG has indicated they are interested, and wants to be kept up to date.</li>
			</ul>
			<li>Social Care</li>
			<ul>
				<li>Gravity </li>
				<li>Administration for Children and Families (ACF)</li>
			</ul>
			<li>Occupational Health</li>
			<li>Shared exposures or environments</li>
			<ul>
				<li>Military Health (for representing units)</li>
				<li>First responders</li>
			</ul>
			<li>Research</li>
		</ul>	
	</div>

	<div>
		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
		<p>
			<b>Boundaries between this and RelatedPerson</b><br/>
			The RelatedPerson resource specifically represents a person, along with their relationship to the patient.<br/>
			It contains the details of both the individual, and the relationship.
			In contrast to this PersonalRelationship resource which purely represents the relationship between two individuals.
		</p>
		<p>
			<b>Boundaries between this and <a href="familymemberhistory.html">FamilyMemberHistory</a></b><br/>
			Although there is a relationship within the family member history, it is not the same as the relationship.
			It intends to provide the details of the family member's health history that could be relevant to the patient, not the relationship itself.
		</p>
		<p>
			<b>Boundaries between this and <a href="careteam.html">CareTeam</a></b><br/>
			PersonalRelationship is not to be used to represent the relationship of "provides care for".  That should be in CareTeam.
		</p>
		<p>
			<b>Boundaries between this and Group</b><br/>
			A group contains all the members and the involvement property indicates the member's relationship to the group, not to the other individuals withing the group.
		</p>
	</div>
</div>