<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This profile defines extensions defining additional constraints on data elements.
</p>
<p>
Data elements can be defined in several places.  The extensions defined within this profile may apply
to most or all of these:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="dataelement.html">DataElement</a> - defining the characteristics that must hold for an element to be an instance of a particular Data Element</li>
  <li><a href="profile.html">Profile</a>.structure.element.definition - defining the characteristics of the data element when used according to the profile</li>
  <li><a href="profile.html">Profile</a>.extensionDefn.definition - defining the characteristics of the extension, regardless of where it is used</li>
  <li><a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>.group.question - defining the characteristics of permitted answers</li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>Note:</b> Implementations are not required to reject invalid data.  However, transmitting data that violates one of these extensions would be considered invalid against
the resource that declared the extension.
</p>

<div>
<h3>Length extensions</h3>
<p>
These extensions govern the length of most of the simple data types.  Some data types are excluded because their lengths are already fixed and cannot be
further constrained.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a name="minLength"> </a><b>minLength</b> - (0..1) Establishes a lower bound for the character length for the element</li>
<li><a name="maxLength"> </a><b>minLength</b> - (0..1) Establishes an upper bound for the character length for the element</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<h3>Format extensions</h3>
<p>
These extensions govern the appearance of string and string-like simple data types.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a name="regex"> </a><b>regex</b> - (0..1) Expresses a "regular expression" that computably defines the permitted syntax for a string</li>
<li><a name="entryFormat"> </a><b>entryFormat</b> - (0..1) Provides human-readable guidance for the desired syntax for a string</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<h3>Numeric and range extensions</h3>
<p>
These extensions govern the allowed range of numeric and date or time data types.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a name="minValue"> </a><b>minValue</b> - (0..1) Identifies the lowest value allowed for a numeric or date element</li>
<li><a name="maxValue"> </a><b>maxValue</b> - (0..1) Identifies the highest value allowed for a numeric or date element</li>
<li><a name="maxDecimalPlaces"> </a><b>maxDecimalPlaces</b> - (0..1) Identifies the number of decimal places allowed for decimal elements</li>
</ul>
</div>

</div>

</div>
