<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This profile defines extensions governing how data elements should be rendered when presented to a user, printed, etc.
</p>
<h3>XHTML-based extensions</h3>
<p>
These extensions make use of XHTML capabilities to influence the rendering of data elements.  In theory, systems displaying data using a technology
other than xhtml could parse the information in the style string and attempt to map it to their own internal display syntax.  However, it is likely that 
not all of the markup instructions would map well.  Support for these extensions by software using mechanisms other than XHTML for rendering is therefore
unlikely.
</p>
<p>
When generating narrative that includes elements with one of these extensions, the narrative covering these elements SHOULD apply the guidance provided
by these extensions to how the element appers in the narrative.
</p>
<p>
<b>Note:</b> Implementers should be cautious around the use of sophisticated formatting capabilities.  Not all browsers and other xhtml rendering tools
support all styles and xhtml capabilities, or at least don't support them well.  This is particularly true for mobile solutions.  Limiting to simple
capabilities increases the likelihood of interoperability and consistent rendering across devices.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a name="style"><b>style</b></a> - (0..1) A string expressing one or more <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/WD-css-style-attr-20020515">xhtml style</a>
  values.  This extension can be used on any element (including, in theory, 
  complex elements containing sub-elements).  It declares one or more xhtml styles that should be declared
  for the node that is responsible for rendering that element.  These might influence font, color, background, etc.</li>
<li><a name="markup"><b>markup</b></a> - (0..1) A string containing excaped xhtml to use to render the specified string with more complex formatting of some or 
  all of the content.  This may include tags for text rendering, embedded styles, or even tables or list structures.  The textual content must be the
  same as that included in the base value of the string.</li>
</ul>
</div>

</div>
