<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
OrganizationRole describes the role an organization plays at an organization, including the services they provide,
the location(s) where they provide services, and their availability, electronic endpoints, and other relevant information.
</p>
OrganizationRole addresses the need to define a non-hierarchical relationship between two or more organizations. For example:
•One organization may provide services to another organization
•Two or more organizations may form a partnership or joint venture
•An organization may be a member of another organization, but not owned by it (e.g. a hospital is a member the American Hospital Association, a hospital is a member of a health information exchange network)

OrganizationRole is similar in form and function to practitionerRole. Instead of references to practitioner and organization (as in practitionerRole), organizationRole includes references to a participatingOrg and a primaryOrg. The participating organization provides “services” to the primary organization (much like a practitioner provides services to an organization). Using the three examples above:
•The participating organization provides services to the primary organization
•The joint venture is considered the primary organization, and partners within the joint venture are considered participating organizations
•An association is the primary organization, and its members are participating organizations.

As with practitionerRole, organizationRole provides the link between an organization and a health insurance provider network.

<p>
The role, specialty, Location telecom and HealthcareService properties can be repeated if required in other instances
of the PractitionerRole. Some systems record a collection of service values for a single location, others record the 
single service and the list of locations it is available. Both are acceptable options for representing this data.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
	Qualifications (from the Practitioner resource) do not imply a Role, but might be considered when an Organization 
  allocates practitioners to roles within their organization, and could provide useful information (such as expiry information)
  which could need to be tracked in some situations to ensure they continue to be eligible for a specific role.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Practitioner performs different roles within the same or even different organizations. Depending on jurisdiction and custom, 
it may be necessary to maintain a specific Practitioner Resource for each such role or have a single Practitioner with multiple roles.
The role can be limited to a specific period, after which authorization for this role ends. Note that the represented organization
need not necessarily be the (direct) employer of a Practitioner.
</p>
</div>

</div>
