<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The Provenance resource tracks information about the activity that created a version of a resource, including the entities, and agents involved in producing a resource.
This information can be used to form assessments about its quality, reliability or trustworthiness, or to provide pointers for where to go to further investigate the origins of the resource and the information in it. 
</p>
<p>
<a href="provenance.html">Provenance resources</a> are a record-keeping assertion that gathers information about the context in which the information in a resource was obtained. 
Provenance resources are prepared by the application that initiates the create/update etc. of the resource.
An <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> resource contains overlapping information, but is created as events occur, to track and audit the events. 
AuditEvent resources are often (though not exclusively) created by the application responding to the read/query/create/update, etc., event. 
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"> </a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<a name="overlap"> </a>
<p>
Many other FHIR resources contain some elements that represent information
about how the resource was obtained, and therefore they overlap with the 
functionality of the Provenance resource. These properties in other resources
should always be used in preference to the Provenance resource, and the 
Provenance resource should be used where additional information is required,
though overlap can occur. 
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
The Provenance resource is based on the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/NOTE-prov-overview-20130430/">W3C Provenance specification</a>, 
and mappings are provided. The Provenance resource is tailored to fit the FHIR use-cases for provenance more directly. 
In terms of <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/">W3C Provenance</a> the FHIR <a href="provenance.html">Provenance resources</a> covers "Generation" of "Entity" with 
respect to FHIR defined resources for creation or updating; 
whereas <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> covers "Usage" of "Entity" and all other "Activity" as defined in W3C Provenance.
</p>
<p>
The W3C Provenance Specification has the following fundamental model:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Key concepts" src="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-primer/images/key-concepts.png" width="280" height="173" style="float: none; clear: both"/>
</p>
<p>
Where:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Target - An entity that is a FHIR resource instance that is created, updated or deleted.</li>
<li>Entity - An entity is a physical, digital, conceptual or other kind of thing with some fixed aspects; entities may be real or imaginary.</li>
<li>Agent - An agent is something that bears some form of responsibility for an activity taking place, for the existence of an entity, or for another agent's activity.</li>
<li>Activity - An activity is something that occurs over a period of time and acts upon or with entities; it may include consuming, processing, transforming, modifying, relocating, using, or generating entities.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The Provenance resource actually corresponds to a single activity that identifies a set of resources (<i>target</i>) generated by the activity.
The activity also references other entities (<i>entity</i>) that were used and the agents (<i>agent</i>) that were associated with the activity. 
To record multiple activities that resulted in one (<i>target</i>), record each (<i>activity</i>) in independent Provenance records all pointing at that (<i>target</i>).
</p>
<p>
The Provenance resource depends upon having References to all of the resources, entities, and agents involved in the 
activity. These References need not be resolvable. The references must provide a unique and ambiguous identification. 
If a resource, entity, or agent can have different versions that must be identified, then the Reference must have 
versioning information included.
</p><p>
Versioning and unique identification are not mandated for all systems that provide Resources, entities, and agents. 
But, inclusion of Provenance requirements may introduce requirements for versioning and unique identification on those systems
</p>
<a name="TODO"> </a>
<h3>Open Issues and Request for Comments</h3>
<p>
At this juncture, Provenance has several areas of concern for the Security WG. The first concern is whether the current HL7 
ProvenanceEvent value set is sufficient for conveying the states 
to which a trigger event can cause an activity to transition the FHIR Resource target of the Provenance Resource from a previous state.  
The current value set was will be updated post DSTU2.
</p>
<p>
While the intended FHIR ProvenanceEvent value set has sub-value sets from multiple sources such as W3C and HL7, there are 
some duplicate and colliding definitions, the upside is that there are more provenance event related actions than in the 
HL7 ProvenanceEvent value set.  The Security, Community Based Collaborative Care, and the EHR Work Groups are in 
the process of refining and de-duplicating this value set in hopes of replacing the current one in DSTU 2.1 if the 
Provenance Resource is permitted to be re-published.  In any case, feedback from business and implementer communities 
would be very much appreciated.
</p>
<p>
Another area of concern is whether the Provenance.entity.role element is necessary at all if there is a sufficient 
activity value set, and if it is useful, whether W3C codes indicating that the entity is the target of 
provenance, e.g., derivation or revision, make sense where the entity is an input into a target resource which may 
be a revision or derivation of that entity.
</p>
<p>
Note that the binding of the ProvenanceEvent and Purpose of Use value sets are currently set to extensible rather 
than example.  Concerns have been raised about constraining vocabulary choices during DSTU especially for other 
jurisdictions.  For example, outside of the US, ISO 13606 Purpose of Use codes are more likely used.  
Security WG would also appreciate feedback on whether these bindings should be example or extensible.
</p>

</div>

</div>
