<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The provenance resource tracks information about activity that created a version of a resource, including the entities, and agents involved in producing a resource.
This information can be used to form assessments about its quality, reliability or trustworthiness, or to provide pointers for where to go to further investigate the origins of the resource and the information in it. 
</p>
<p>
<a href="provenance.html">Provenance resources</a> are a record-keeping assertion that gathers information about the context in which the information in a resource was obtained. 
Provenance resources are prepared by the application that initiates the create/update etc. of the resource.
A <a href="auditevent.html">Audit Event</a> resource contains overlapping information, but is created as events occur, to track and audit the events. 
Audit Event resources are often (though not exclusively) created by the application responding to the read/query/create/update etc. event. 
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Many other FHIR resources contain some elements that represent information
about how the resource was obtained, and therefore they overlap with the 
functionality of the Provenance resource. These properties in other resources
should always be used in preference to the provenance resource, and the 
provenance resource should be used where additional information is required,
though overlap can occur. 
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
The provenance resource is based on the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/NOTE-prov-overview-20130430/">W3C Provenance specification</a>, 
and mappings are provided. The Provenance resource is tailored to fit the FHIR use-cases for provenance more directly. 
In terms of <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/">W3C Provenance</a> the FHIR <a href="provenance.html">Provenance resources</a> covers "Generation" of "Entity" with 
respect to FHIR defined Resources for creation or updating; 
where as <a href="auditevent.html">Audit Event</a> covers "Usage" of "Entity" and all other "Activity" as defined in W3C Provenance.
</p>
<p>
The W3C Provenance Specification has the following fundamental model:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Key concepts" src="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-primer/images/key-concepts.png" width="280" height="173" style="float: none; clear: both"/>
</p>
<p>
The <i>Provenance</i> resource actually corresponds to a single activity that identifies a set of resources (<i>target</i>) generated by the activity.
The activity also references other entities (<i>entity</i>) that were used and the agents (<i>agent</i>) that were associated with the activity. 
</p>
</div>

</div>
