<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="using"> </a>
<h3>Using the Provenance Resource</h3>

<p>
The Provenance resource identifies information about another resource (the <i>target</i> element). 
The Provenance resource may be used in several different ways:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>As part of a <a href="bundle.html">Bundle</a> where it identifies the provenance of part or all of the resources in the Bundle (e.g. <a href="documents.html">Documents</a>)</li>
 <li>On a <a href="http.html">RESTful system</a> where it keeps track of provenance information relating to resources</li>
</ul>
<p>
The resources found in a <a href="bundle.html#bundle-unique">Bundle are often the latest version and don't have a version identified</a>, yet Provenance resources in the Bundle may have references (e.g. .target) to version specific resources. When de-referencing resource references that may have a version identified one should look for the non-version resource found in the Bundle.
</p>
<p>
On a RESTful system, the target resource reference should be version specific, but this
requires special care: For new resources that need to have a corresponding Provenance resource, the version-specific
reference is often not knowable until after the target resource has been updated. This can create an 
integrity problem for the system - what if the Provenance resource cannot be created after the target 
resource has been updated? To avoid any such integrity problems, the target resource and the Provenance resources should be submitted 
as a pair using a <a href="http.html#transaction">transaction</a>. 
The <a href="provenance.html#header">Provenance http header</a> may be used if supported. 
</p>
<p>
The <i>Provenance.target</i> may point at a specific element within the targetted resource using the <a href="extension-targetelement.html">target element extension</a> or <a href="extension-targetpath.html">target path extension</a>. For example when updating a Patient resource with a new official name, such as shown in <a href="provenance-example1.html">example 1</a>, where the Provenance is indicating that the official name was provided by the Patient themselves.
</p>
<a name="header"> </a>
<h4>HTTP Header</h4>

<p>
The custom header X-Provenance to provide a provenance resource when performing PUT or POST operations
using the <a href="http.html">RESTful interface</a>:
</p>
<pre>
POST [base]/Observation
Content-Type: application/fhir+?
X-Provenance: { "resourceType": "Provenance", "location": { "reference": "Location/1" }," agent" ... }

[body]
</pre>
<p>
The intent is that the server picks up the provenance, fills out the  <code>target</code>,
and then stores the provenance information as it normally would.
Notes:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Irrespective of the Content-Type or Accept headers, the Provenance resource is in the <a href="json.html">JSON format</a></li>
 <li>The provenance SHALL not have a specified <code>Provenance.target</code>. The server will fill the <code>target</code> in as it processes 
     the contents of the POST/PUT and determines the ids of the resource(s) to which the interaction applies</li>
 <li>Servers MAY ignore the header, but SHOULD process it if they support provenance</li>
 <li>Some server frameworks impose a length limit on individual HTTP headers, or on the the headers as a whole. Servers MAY reject a request if the X-Provenance header is too long</li>
 <li>The use of the header is not documented for other HTTP methods (GET etc)</li>
 <li>When recording an AuditEvent, one AuditEvent may be used to record the create of the resource and provenance</li>
</ul>


<a name="signature"> </a>
<h3>Signatures</h3>

<p>
The Provenance resource includes a <i>signature</i> element (digital signature) which can be used for 
standards based integrity verification and non-repudiation purposes. The <a href="datatypes.html#Signature">Signature</a>  datatype
provides details on use of the <i>signature</i> element. The Signature.type coded value of "Source" should be used
when the signature is for simply proving that the resource content is the same as it was when the resource
was updated or created.
</p>

<a name="removal"> </a>
<h3>Provenance of Removal</h3>
<p>
A Provenance record can be recorded to indicate who deleted a Resource. If versioning is supported, 
the version that was deleted is referenced in Provenance.target; if versioning is not supported then 
Provenance.target contains the non-version reference. Provenance.entity is not used unless there is 
a business requirement to do so.
</p>
<a name="import"></a>
<h3>Use of Provenance to record Import and Transform</h3>
<p>
Provenance can be used to record activities of an automaton that transforms input. Such as middleware 
that extracts information from a HL7 v2 message and creates FHIR resources, or middleware that extracts 
information from an HL7 CDA document and creates FHIR resources, etc. The Provenance in these cases is 
recording the activity of the middleware.
</p><p>
The middleware in this case would, in addition to creating the target resources, create a <code>Provenance</code> 
resource that indicates all the target resources (using <code>Provenance.target</code>). The middleware is 
identified as one of the <code>Provenance.agent</code> elements, with the <code>Provenance.agent.type</code> of <i>assembler</i>.
</p><p>
The middleware may record the source as another <code>Provenance.agent</code> element.
</p><p>
The original content is optionally saved. This might be as a DocumentReference, or Binary. The 
<code>Provenance.entity</code> would then point at this original content.
</p><p>
The original source might include some form of 'provenance' to cover the history of the original 
content prior to the import transformation. This original source 'provenance' should be converted 
into FHIR Provenance records as appropriate.
</p>
<p>
Examples of this activity with Provenance profile can be found in the <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE</a> Implementation Guides for
<ul>
<li>Query for Existing Data for Mobile - <a href="https://wiki.ihe.net/index.php/Query_for_Existing_Data_for_Mobile">QEDm</a></li>
<li>Reconciliation of Clinical Content and Care Providers - <a href="https://wiki.ihe.net/index.php/Reconciliation_of_Clinical_Content_and_Care_Providers">RECON</a> </li>
</ul>
</p>
<a name="patients"></a>
<h3>Muiltiple Patients Affected</h3>
<p>
Where a provenance activity impacts more than one Patient/Subject; multiple Provenance resources should be recorded, one for each Patient/Subject. This best enables segmentation of the Provenance details so as to limit the Privacy impact. The use of multiple Provenance is a best-practice and should be driven by a Policy. There will be cases where the use of multiple Provenance resources is not necessary, such as public health reporting.
</p>
</div>
