<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Devices include durable (reusable) medical equipment, implantable devices, as well as disposable equipment used for diagnostic, treatment, and research for healthcare and public health, as well as devices such as a machine, cellphone, computer, software, application, etc.  The DeviceDefinition resource is used to describe the common characteristics and capabilities of a device of a certain type or kind, e.g., a certain model or class of a device such as a x-ray model or personal wearable device model, whereas a Device resource documents an actual instance of a device such as the actual x-ray machine that is installed or the personal wearable device being worn.
</p>

<p>Devices can also be subdivded as follows:</p>
<p><b>Implantable device</b></p>
<ul>
<li>
a device that is intended to be placed in a surgically or naturally formed cavity of the human body…for a continuous period of 30 days or more <a href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/home-health-and-consumer-devices/home-use-devices">US Food and Drug Administration Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Home Use Devices.</a> Accessed 13 March 2020.
</li>
<li>
any active medical device which is intended to be totally or partially introduced, surgically or medically, into the human body or by medical intervention into a natural orifice, and which is intended to remain after the procedure <a href="https://www.bsigroup.com/en-US/medical-devices/Technologies/Active-Implantable-Medical-Devices/">BSI Group. Active implantable medical devices.</a> Accessed 13 March 2020.
</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Patient-use device</b></p>
<ul>
<li>Patient-use, or home use devices, intended for users in any environment outside of a professional healthcare facility. This includes devices intended for use in both professional healthcare facilities and homes <a href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/home-health-and-consumer-devices/home-use-devices">US Food and Drug Administration Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Home Use Devices.</a> Accessed 13 March 2020.
</li>
</ul>

</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The DeviceDefinition resource contains the "catalog" definition of a device - whether that definition is authored by the manufacturer or a regulatory entity and allows defining valid hierarchical device configurations (devices as part of other devices).
</p>
<p>
Device vs deviceDefinition: The Device resource is meant to refer to a physical instance of a device - hence having attributes like lot number, patient, location, operational status which the DeviceDefinition resource does not have.

</p>




</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>


</div>
 
</div>
