<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
			Need to describe Searching for "Schedule's" that belong to a HealthcareService using Categories, or 
			where using pracitioners or locations as the actor, then the "type" field is expected to be used to store the
			service categories.
			Advice to use as an actor.
		</p>
		<p>
			Also consider 
		</p>
	</div>
    <div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
			Availability resources provide a container for time-slots that can be booked using an appointment,
			It provides the window of time (period) that slots are defined for and what type of appointments can be booked.
			They do not provide any information about actual appointments.
		</p>
		<p>
			In HL7 v2.7 (and the RIM) this resource is defined as a schedule (which in fhir is a simple recurrence):
		</p>
	<blockquote>
		<p>
			A schedule controls the dates and times available for the performance of a service
			and/or the use of a resource.  One schedule applies to one service or resource, since
			each service or resource can be reserved independently of the others.  
			(If two or more services, people, locations, or things cannot be reserved independently
			of one another, they are considered to be one activity or resource.)  A schedule consists
			of slots of time during which the controlled service or resource is potentially available
			for performance or use.  Slots are categorized as open, booked, or blocked.  An open slot
			on a schedule indicates that the service or resource is available for performance or use
			during that period of time.  A booked slot indicates that the service or resource is not
			available during the time period, because an appointment has been scheduled.  A blocked
			slot indicates that a service or resource is unavailable for reasons other than a scheduled
			appointment.
		</p>
		<p>
		The real-world, non-automated analog of the schedule described above is a standard
		appointment book.  These books are generally organized with rows of time slots, during
		which a service or resource is available.
		</p>
		<p>
			A slot is one unit on a schedule.  A slot represents the smallest unit of time or quantity
			that a service or resource may be booked.  Depending on the nature of the service or
			resource, there may be more than one defined slot at a given instant of time.  
			For example, if a service is an open group therapy session with twelve available seats,
			then there are twelve slots for the given block of time.
		</p>
	</blockquote>
	<p>
		It is expected that servers could expose this information as an alternate representation
		using the iCalendar free/busy format, joining the information in slot resources that reference
		this availability resource.
	</p>
</div>
</div>
	