<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
A security claim is some kind of information that may be provided about a <a href="securityprincipal.html">Security Principal</a>.
These claims can be used to make access control decisions when the security principal performs some kind of operation.
Claims may be made directly against principals, or made about <a href="securitygroup.html">groups</a> to which the principal is assigned.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
FHIR defines a number of security related resources:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr> <td><a href="securityevent.html">SecurityEvent</a></td> <td>A record of an event made for purposes of maintaining a security log</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td><a href="securityprincipal.html">SecurityPrincipal</a></td> <td>Tracks a human or software device that uses the system</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td><a href="securitygroup.html">SecurityGroup</a></td> <td>A group of rights for security principals</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td><a href="securityclaim.html">SecurityClaim</a></td> <td>A definition of a claim that can be made about a user</td> </tr>
</table>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Security Claims</h2>
<p>
Many specifications define claims that may be made in regard to security principals:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><b>http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/ws/2009/09/identity/claims/...</b>: A claim type defined by <a href="http://www.ws-i.org/">WS-I</a></li>
 <li><b>http://openid.net/connect/[x]</b>: A claim type defined in the OpenID Connect specification. [x] is the name of the claim, and the value will be an escaped JSON representation of the claim</li>
</ul>
<p>
In addition, this specification defines two claim types of it's own:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><b>http://hl7.org/fhir/tag/security</b>: a reference to a <a href="securitylabel.html">security label</a> - this means that the real world entity has the label applied to it</li>
 <li><b>http://hl7.org/fhir/security-role</b>: a reference to a security role defined by FHIR. See below for details.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Finally, implementation guides or implementing systems can define their own security claims
using the SecurityClaim resource.
</p>

</div>

</div>
