<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../../../schema/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="SDC"> </a>
  <h2>Structured Data Capture (SDC) - Data Element Exchange Implementation Guide</h2>
  <p>
    This implementation guide is a supplement to the base <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdc}}sdc.html">Structured Data Capture</a> (SDC) implementation guide.  It defines 
    expectations for <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">Data Element</a> registries, as well as those systems that are responsible for the creation and 
    maintenance of data elements within those registries.  This capability is documented as a distinct implementation guide because the expectations for systems creating and 
    maintaining data elements are higher than for those systems that are merely responsible for referencing data elements when creating forms or configuring their
    systems to support pre-population or auto-population.
  </p>
  <p>
    The set of expectations described within this implementation guide reflects the consensus view of those stakeholders involved in the
    Structured Data Capture public consultation group, which included representatives from several large organizations responsible for data element
    registries, including:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>The US Federal Drug Administration (FDA)</li>
    <li>The US National Cancer Institute (NCI)</li>
    <li>The US National Library of Medicine (NLM)</li>
    <li>The College of American Pathologists (CAP)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    This implementation guide is intended to be conformant with the 
    <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c050340_ISO_IEC_11179-3_2013.zip">ISO/IEC 11179-3</a> standard, though it only defines (and requires 
    support for) only a subset of the properties defined in that specification.
  </p>
  <p>
    This implementation guide was prepared as a U.S. Realm Specification on behalf of the Structured Data Capture project - an effort under the 
    <a href="http://www.healthit.gov/newsroom/about-onc">U.S. Office of the National Coordinator (ONC)</a>'s Standards and Infrastructure (S &amp; I) Framework
    However, much of the content is likely to be useable in other jurisdictions. The only portions of this specification that may be problematic for use of this implementation 
    guide in some jurisdictions are the bindings to terminologies such as SNOMED CT and RxNorm.  The constraints and extensions used should all have broad applicability.
  </p>
  <a name="toc"/>
  <h3>Navigation</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide follows the FHIR pattern of being published as a web-based specification.  This
    allows easy navigation between the SDC-specific portion of the implementation guide and the resources,
    data types, value sets and other specification components leveraged from the FHIR core specification.  This
    approach also allows implementers to easily navigate to the information needed to perform a particular task.
  </p>
  <p>
    A <a href="toc.html">Table of Contents</a> and <a href="artifacts.html">Artifact Index</a> are provided to help navigate the content within this guide.
    (Do be aware that some pages have multiple tabs.)  A
    table of contents is also available for the full <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}toc.html">FHIR specification</a> if
    you really want to read absolutely everything.  Tooling may provide support for a PDF or other document-approach
    representation of this implementation guide in a future release.
  </p>
  <p>
    Bread-crumb navigation is provided in the gray bar just below the menu at the top of each page, allowing
    easy navigation back to the main SDC page.
  </p>
  <p>This implementation guide has a number of sections:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="#fhir">Understanding FHIR</a> should be read by those who are not familiar with FHIR as a pre-requisite to reading the rest of the implementation guide</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#background">Background</a> provides links to background and implementation information including security guidelines and the SDC wiki</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#capabilitystatement">Capability Statements</a> describes the different roles systems wishing to conform to this implementation guide can take on and summarizes how 
        those roles interact.</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#resources">Resources</a> describes the resources used as part of this implementation guide, including profiles placed on those resources to constrain and extend 
        their capabilities.</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#iso11179">ISO 11179 relationship</a> provides an overview of how the resource profile maps to the ISO 11179 specification</li>
    <li>
      <a href="#ip">Intellectual Property Considerations</a> provides information about intellectual property referenced by this implementation guide</li>
  </ul>
  <br/>
  <a name="fhir"> </a>
  <h3>Understanding FHIR</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide is based on the HL7 <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}index.html">FHIR</a> standard.  It uses terminology, notations and design principles that are
    specific to FHIR.  Before reading this implementation guide, it's important to be familiar with some of the basic principles of FHIR as well 
    as general guidance on how to read FHIR specifications.  Readers who are unfamiliar with FHIR are encouraged to read (or at least skim) the following 
    prior to reading the rest of this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview.html">FHIR overview</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview-dev.html">Developer's introduction</a>
    </li>
    <li>(or <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview-clinical.html">Clinical introduction</a>)</li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}datatypes.html">FHIR data types</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}terminologies.html">Using codes</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}references.html">References between resources</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}formats.html">How to read resource &amp; profile definitions</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}resource.html">Base resource</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}http.html">RESTful operations</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}search.html">Search</a>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Feel free to explore other aspects of the FHIR specification that you feel may be relevant or of interest.
  </p>
  <a name="background"> </a>
  <h3>Background</h3>
  <p>
    DataElement instances do not convey patient-specific information.  However, because the mappings associated with data elements can influence the
    data that might be automatically populated into forms and could also influence the security controls around data associated with the DataElement,
    security precautions should be taken to ensure that data elements are not created or revised by someone without the proper authority.  
    <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdc}}sdc-security.html">Security practices</a> for systems complying with this implementation guide are the same as those for the primary
    SDC implementation guide.
  </p>
  <p>
    Additional information about the Structured Data Capture project can be found on the 
    <a href="http://wiki.siframework.org/Structured+Data+Capture+Initiative">project's wiki</a>.
  </p>
  <h3>Specification</h3>
  <p>The following sections describe the artifacts that set expectations for systems wishing to be conformant to the FHIR SDC implementation guide.</p>
  <a name="capabilitystatement"> </a>
  <h4>Capability Statements</h4>
  <p>
    FHIR Capability statements define the expectations for particular system "roles" within an SDC environment.  To be considered SDC-conformant, a system 
    must adhere to the requirements defined by at least one of these statements.  Some systems might choose to comply with more than one.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-de-registry.html">SDC Data Element Registry</a> - Repository for data elements</li>
    <li>
      <a href="sdc-de-curator.html">SDC Data Element Curator</a> - System responsible for creating and updating data elements</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Systems supporting the <i>SDC Data Element Registry</i> role SHALL be capable of accepting, persisting and returning all DataElement properties marked as
    "must support" in the SDC Data Element Exchange profile.  Systems supporting the <i>SDC Data Element Curator</i> role SHALL be capable of providing and
    updating those same properties.
  </p>
  <a name="resources"> </a>
  <h4>Resources</h4>
  <p>
    This implementation guide defines profiles on several resources.  Implementations are expected to be conformant with these profiles in order
    to be conformant with this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>Resource</th>
        <th>SDC Profile</th>
        <th>Purpose</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}dataelement.html">DataElement</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdcde-dataelement.html">SDC Data Element Exchange Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define data elements for exchange and maintenance within data element registries</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}valueset.html">ValueSet</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdcde-valueset.html">SDC Data Element Exchange Value Set Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define permitted values and meanings for data elements</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}valueset.html">ValueSet</a>
        </td>
        <td>
          <a href="sdcde-codesystem.html">SDC Data Element Exchange Code System Profile</a>
        </td>
        <td>Used to define the concepts used as permitted values and meanings for data elements</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>
    Additional resources such as  
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}conceptmap.html">ConceptMap</a>, <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}provenance.html">Provenance</a>, 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> and others are also 
    likely to be used in SDC solutions, though no SDC-specific profiles have been created for them.    
    <!-- Todo: decide how explicit the list of relevant sections needs to be -->
  </p>
  <a name="iso11179"> </a>
  <h3>ISO 11179 Relationship</h3>
  <p>
    ISO 11179 is one of the principle authorities on the notion of "Data Element".  For a complete view of the alignment between the SDC FHIR specification and ISO 11179, the 
    FHIR profile on DataElement includes <a href="sdcde-dataelement-mappings.html#iso11179">mappings</a> to the ISO 11179 specification for each of the core elements and 
    extensions of the resource.  As a summary, the FHIR DataElement resource can express most (all, if additional extensions are introduced) of the notions present in 11179, 
    however the approach differs in a few ways:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>FHIR does not define separate resources for the Data Element vs. the Data Element Concept.  Both notions can be represented using the same structure and both conceptual 
      and conceptual domain and value domain aspects can be represented within a single instance.</li>
    <li>FHIR uses <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}valueset.html">ValueSet</a>s to represent both permissible values and value meanings (and allows the sets to be defined by
      expression rather than only by enumeration)</li>
    <li>The notions of Object_Class and Property are considered to be just one possible model for defining the meaning of a given element</li>
  </ul>
  <a name="ip"> </a>
  <h3>Intellectual Property Considerations</h3>
  <p>
    While this implementation guide and the underlying FHIR are licensed as public domain, this guide mandates the use of terminologies including LOINC, SNOMED CT and
    RxNorm which have more restrictive licensing requirements.  Implementers should make themselves familiar with licensing and any other constraints of terminologies,
    questionnaires, data elements and other components used as part of their implementation process.  In some cases, licensing requirements may limit what systems
    data captured using this implementation guide may be shared with.
  </p>
</div>
