<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../../../schema/fhir-single.xsd">
  <div>
    <a name="scope"/>
    <h3>Scope and Usage</h3>
    <p>
      This profile sets expectations for use of the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}codesystem.html">CodeSystem</a> resource within the 
      <a href="{{site.data.refs.sdc}}sdc.html">Structured Data Capture</a> implementation guide.  This includes
      identifying which core elements and extensions must be supported.
    </p>
    <p>
      For the purposes of this profile, <i>Supported</i> means that clients SHALL be capable of processing the element/extension and use the information to control the display
      and information capture associated with the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}codesystem.html">CodeSystem</a>.  It means that servers SHALL be capable of persisting those 
      elements and returning them in response to requests.  For systems rendering <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}questionnaire.html">Questionnaires</a>, these <i>Supported</i> 
      elements and extensions must be supported in the rendering of allowed choices associated with questions.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <a name="boundaries"/>
    <h3>Boundaries and Relationships</h3>
    <p>
      This profile relies on the use of the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}codesystem-extensions.html">codesystem-extensions</a> profile which defines a number of less common 
      properties for code systems, several of which are mandated for this profile.  It also makes use of the 
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}rendering-extensions.html">rendering-extensions</a> which defines rendering information for display names and labels of codes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <a name="content"> </a>
  <h3>Content</h3>
  <table class="lines">
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2">
        <b>Profiles</b>: </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="sdcde-codesystem.html">SDCDE-CodeSystem</a>
      </td>
      <td>Defines how CodeSystem is used to reflect code lists found in data element defintions for exchange and maintenance between data element registries according to 
      requirements established by the ONC's Structured Data Capture standard.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>
