<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
An implementation guide (IG) is a set of rules about how FHIR resources are used (or should be used) to solve
a particular problem, with associated documentation to support and clarify the usage. Classically, FHIR
implementation guides are published on the web after they are generated using the 
<a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/FHIR/IG+Publisher+Documentation">FHIR Implementation Guide Publisher</a>.
</p>
<p>
The <code>ImplementationGuide</code> resource is a single resource that defines the content of the IG,
along with the important entry pages into the publication, as a single logical package, so that the
contents of the IG are computable for purposes of publication, validation, registry look-up, and other uses.
</p>
<p>
In particular, validators are able to use the ImplementationGuide resource to validate content
against the implementation guide as a whole. The significant conformance expectation introduced 
by the ImplementationGuide resource is the idea of <a href="#default">Default Profiles</a>. 
Implementations may conform to multiple implementation guides at once, but this requires that 
the implementation guides are compatible (see <a href="#compatibility">below</a>).
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Implementation Guides contain two different types of resource references:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Contents: A set of logical statements which implementations must conform to. These are almost always <a href="conformance-module.html">conformance resources</a></li>
 <li>Examples: Examples that illustrate the intent of the profiles defined in the implementation guide. These can be any kind of resource</li>
</ul>
<p>
An application's <a href="capabilitystatement.html">Capability Statement</a> may identify one or more implementation guides that an application conforms to.
</p>
</div>


</div>
