<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="packaging"></a>
<h3>Distributing Implementation Guides</h3>
<p>
Implementation Guides are published through the FHIR Package distribution system.
For further details, see the <a href="packages.html">FHIR NPM Packages</a>.
</p>

<a name="authoring"></a>
<h3>Authoring Implementation Guides</h3>
<p>
Implementation Guides can be produced using any tooling that produces a human
readable output and a package that includes an ImplementationGuide along with 
all the supporting resources it refers to, and their dependencies. Note that 
dependencies included in other packages that the Implementation guide identifies 
as dependencies are not included in the package.
</p> 
<p>
See the <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/FHIR/Authoring+FHIR+Implementation+Guides+-+Introduction">for a 
list of tools that can assist with authoring implementation guides. HL7 publishes 
a <a href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/FHIR/ig-guidance/">Guidance Implementation Guide</a> that provides specific guidance 
on best practices around IG creation as well as information about some of the tooling extensions and capabilities relevant to 
creation and publication of implementation guides. Note that this documentation mixes general documentation about the design 
of implementation guides with tooling specific advice based on one particular tool.
</p>

<a name="roles"></a>
<h3>Roles of Implementation Guides</h3>
<p>
Implementation Guides are packages of both computer processible content (resources) and human readable 
documentation (html). The resources typically specify some combination of:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Terminology: <a href="codesystem.html">Code Systems</a>, <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a> and <a href="conceptmap.html">concept maps</a></li>
<li>Content rules: <a href="structuredefinition.html">Profiles and Extensions</a> and <a href="structuremap.html">Mappings to other content</a></li>
<li>API Details: <a href="capabilitystatement.html">Capability Statement</a>, <a href="operationdefinition.html">operation definitions</a> and 
additional <a href="searchparameter.html">search parameters</a></li>
<li>Clinical Logic: <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaires</a>, <a href="library.html">logic libraries</a> and <a href="measure.html">measure definitions</a></li>
<li>Test Information: <a href="testscript.html">Test Scripts</a></li>
<li>Supporting Examples</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note that any kinds of resources can be included; these are just the common uses.
</p>
<p>
In addition, in the human readable portions, implementation guides often:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Describe security arrangements in place for the relevent data exchanges, along with consent and access control requirements</li>
<li>Detail additional rules about the user of the narrative in the resources</li>
<li>Specify other conformance expectations that aren't testable directly</li>
<li>Outline the business arrangements and expectations under which the data is exchanged</li>
</ul>

<a name="versions"></a>
<h3>Multi-Version Implementation Guides</h3>
<p>
Most implementation guides target a single version - that is, they describe how to use a 
particular version, and all the profiles, value sets and examples they contain etc are valid 
for that particular version. 
</p>
<p>
In other cases, however, implementation of an implementation guide is not confined to a single 
version. Typically, the requirement to support multiple versions arises as implementation matures 
and different implementation communities are stuck at different versions by regulation or 
market dynamics. Applications may be stuck at different versions of the specification. 
See <a href="versioning.html">Managing Multiple Versions</a> for further information about
cross-version support.
</p>
<p>
For this reason, implementation guides might describe how to use multiple different versions of 
FHIR for the same purpose. The different versions might have different profiles, extensions, and 
examples, while sharing common value set definitions, for example. For some reasons, profiles
and examples could be common across all versions. And an implementation guide will generally have
a lot of common narrative describing the problem, security approaches, and other deployment 
information irrespective of specific FHIR versions. 
</p>
<p>
An implementation guide specifies which versions of FHIR it describes in the
<a href="implementationguide-definitions.html#ImplementationGuide.fhirVersion">ImplementationGuide.fhirVersion</a> property:
</p>
<div class="json">
<pre>
  "fhirVersion" : ["4.0", "5.0"],
</pre>
</div>
<p>
This specifies that the implementation guide applies to both <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R4">Release 4</a> and <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R5">Release 5</a>. 
Note that the patch version (".1" for Release 3) is omitted, since the patch releases never make changes
that make any difference to Implementation Guides.
</p>
<p>
Note that it is possible to have an Implementation Guide that declares support for one version 
and imports an Implementation Guide that declares support for a different version.  
It is up to the importing IG ad/or the tooling that supports Implementation Guides to determine 
whether it's safe and/or appropriate to reference the different resources from the new IG, and
what to make of this.
</p>
[%dragons-start%]
<p>
As yet, there is no experience with multi-version implementation guides and current publication tooling 
does not support creation of such IGs.  As we work to evolve the tools to provide such support, 
additional guidance on how such guides should be created, what types of content can safely be 
shared across versions, and how such sharing should occur will be forthcoming.
</p>
[%dragons-end%]

<a name="default"></a>
<h3>Default Profiles</h3>
<p>
An implementation guide can define default profiles using <code>ImplementationGuide.global</code>- these are profiles that apply to any resource that
does not otherwise have an explicit profile assigned by the implementation guide. Default profiles 
are always references to profiles (<a href="structuredefinition.html">StructureDefinition</a> resources)
that are also contained in the resources. By defining default profiles, an implementation guide
can save itself from exhaustively defining profiles on every resource type just to profile every
reference to a particular resource type. 
</p>
<p>
Note that a resource can conform to the default profile by conforming to any profile derived from it. 
</p>
<!--

commented out 31/12/2019 - I don't even know what this is. (GG)

<a name="compatibility"></a>
<h3>Compatibility list</h3>
<p>
This table declares the compatibility between the various resources as determined
by the Implementation Guide comparison tool:
</p>
<p>
<i>Yet to be done</i>
</p>
-->

</div>
