<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<h3>Overview</h3>
<p>
Observation-genetics-profile (i.e. Standard Profile for Genetics) extends <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resource to enable reporting of structured genetic test results. In addition, the genetics profile contextualizes well established standards from the field of clinical genetics into the standards of healthcare (e.g. HGNC - HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee's international standard for gene names, symbols, and identifiers).
</p>
<p>
<h4>Genetic Standards and Resources include:</h4>
			<ul> 
				<li>Variant Databases: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/snp_ref.cgi">dbSNP</a> , <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/">ClinVar</a>, and <a href="http://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/cosmic/">COSMIC</a> </li>
				<li>Reference Sequences: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/refseq/">RefSeq</a> and <a href="http://www.ensembl.org/index.html">ENSEMBL</a> </li>
				<li> Gene Symbols and Identifiers: <a href="http://www.genenames.org">HGNC</a> - Human Genee Nomenclature Committee</li>
				<li>Variant Nomenclature: <a href="http://www.hgvs.org">HGVS</a> nomenclature from the Human Genome Variantion Society</li>
				<li>Variant Feature Annotation: <a href="http://www.sequenceontology.org">Sequence Ontology (SO)</a> and <a href="https://loinc.org">LOINC</a> </li>
                <li>Locus: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene">Gene</a></li>
			</ul>
</p>
<h3>Scope and Usage</h3>
<p>
The Standard Profile for Genetics supports reporting of a DNA variant at the genomic, cDNA, and protein change level. In addition, a condition context may be provided, as AssessedCondition. For large genomic tests, a condition may be used as an input into the analytic pipeline to aid in the identification of clinically relevant variants related to the test order. It is strongly encouraged to provide all available information in this profile for any reported variants, because receiving systems (e.g. discovery research, outcomes analysis, and public health reporting) may use this information to normalize variants over time or across sources.  However, these data should not be used to dynamically correct/change variant representations for clinical use outside of the laboratory, due to insufficient information.

</p>
<p>
Implementers should be aware that semantic equivalency of results of genetic variants cannot be guaranteed unless there is an agreed upon standard between sending and receiving systems.
</p>
<p>
These challenges raised above are discussed in the HL7 Clinical Sequencing Domain Analysis Model (passed January 2015 ballot and in process of being published).
</p>
<p>
Hl7 Clinical Genomics Work Group emphasizes the importance of transmitting structured genetic findings within the clinical, translational, and research environments fully integrated with other clinical data, in order to drive outcomes analysis, operational decision making, discovery research, and public health reporting. the standard doesn't currently cover the reporting of clinically relevant negative or wildtype results within genetic data portion of the message.
</p>
<p>
    <a href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public_temp_65DE7F6D-1C23-BA17-0CB30D7343EDE16D/wg/clingenomics/docs/V3DAM_CG_CLINSEQ_R1_O1_2013JAN.pdf">Here</a> is the document of HL7 Version 3 Domain Analysis Model where the examples used in genetics profile are from (Page 5).
</p>

<h3>Component</h3>

<p>Observation.component should be used in genetic profile for observations without sequence information while Observation.extension still be used for sequence information as component is only suitable for flat obervations. </p>
<p>Here is a loinc panel which could be supported by Observation.component for example:</p>
<p><strong>55232-3 Genetic analysis summary panel ­ Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method</strong></p>

<ul>
    <li>51967­8 Genetic disease assessed [Identifier] in Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method</li>
    <li>51963­7 Medication assessed [Identifier] in Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method </li>
    <li>53039­4 Genetic disease analysis overall carrier interpretation [interpretation] in Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method</li>
    <li>51964­5 Drug efficacy analysis overall interpretation [interpretation] in Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method</li>
    <li>51971­0 Drug metabolism analysis overall interpretation [interpretation] in Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method</li>
    <li>51969­4 Genetic analysis summary report in Blood or Tissue Document by Molecular genetics method</li>
    <li>53577­3 Reason for study additional note [Text] in Blood or Tissue by Molecular genetics method Narrative</li>

</ul>


<p>The usage of component is shown in example3-mutationlist-1/2/3/4.</p>

<h3>Category</h3>
<p>Extensions added in genetics profile can be grouped into 4 categories:</p>
<ul>
    <li><strong>Sequence Information:</strong> geneticsGenomeBuild, geneticsChromosome, geneticsGenomicStart, geneticsGenomicStop, geneticsReferenceAllele, geneticsObservedAllele, geneticsTranscriptReferenceSequenceId, geneticsProteinReferenceSequenceId, geneticsCIGAR</li>
    <li><strong>Variation:</strong> geneticsDNASequenceVariation, geneticsVariationId, geneticsDNASequenceVariationType, geneticsAminoAcidChange, geneticsAminoAcidChangeType</li>
    <li><strong>Context:</strong> geneticsGene, geneticsDNARegionName, geneticsAlleleName, geneticsGenomicSourceClass, geneticsAminoSpecies, geneticsResult</li>
    <li><strong>State:</strong> geneticsAllelicState, geneticsAllelicFrequency, geneticsCopyNumberEvent, geneticsReadCoverage</li>
</ul>
    
</div>
