<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Notes:</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    The element, Observation.value[x], has a variable name depending on the type as follows:
    <ul>
     <li>valueQuantity</li>
     <li>valueCodeableConcept</li>
     <li>valueAttachment</li>
     <li>valueRatio</li>
     <li>valuePeriod</li>
     <li>valueSampledData</li>
     <li>valueString</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    The appliesDateTime or appliesPeriod is the time that the observation is most 
    relevant as an observation of the subject. For a biological subject (e.g. a human patient), 
    this is the physiologically relevant time of the observation. 
	In the case of an observation using a specimen, this represents the start and 
    end of the specimen collection (e.g. 24 hour Urine Sodium), but if the collection time is 
    sufficiently short, this is reported as a point in time value (e.g. normal venepuncture). 
    In the case of an observation obtained directly from a subject (e.g., BP, 
    Chest X-ray), this is the start and end time of the observation process, which again, is 
    often reported as a single point in time.
  </li>
  <li>
    At its simplest, resource instances can consist of only a type and a value, with a reliability and status flag.  
    The relevance of other properties will vary based on the type of observation.  
	Reference ranges may be useful for lab tests and other measures like systolic blood pressure, but will have little 
	relevance for something like "pregnancy status"
  </li>
  <li>
    Most observations only have one generic reference range. Systems MAY choose to restrict to only supplying the relevant reference range based on knowledge about the patient (e.g. specific to the patient's age, gender, weight and other factors), but this may not be possible or appropriate. Whenever more than one reference range is supplied, the differences between them SHOULD be provided in the reference range and/or age properties
  </li>
  <li>
    Profiles will be created to provide guidance on capturing certain types 
    of simple observations.  This resource focuses on the level of detail
    captured by most systems.  However, any "simple" observation can easily 
	be broken into numerous components and sub-components to provide additional
    information relevant in certain circumstances.  As with other resources, 
	extensions can be used to introduce this additional complexity.
 </li>
 <li>
   Because there are multiple types allowed for the <i>value</i> element, multiple value search parameters are defined. There is no standard parameter for searching values of type Attachment, or Ratio
 </li>
</ul>

</div>



