<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<h2>Notes:</h2>
	<ul>
		<li>
    The element, Observation.value[x], has a variable name depending on the type as follows:
    <ul>
				<li>valueQuantity</li>
				<li>valueCodeableConcept</li>
				<li>valueString</li>
				<li>valueRange</li>
				<li>valueRatio</li>
				<li>valueSampledData</li>
				<li>valueAttachment</li>
				<li>valueTime</li>
				<li>valueDateTime</li>
				<li>valuePeriod</li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li>
		If the data element is usually coded or if the type associated with the Observation.code defines a coded value, use CodeableConcept instead   of string datatype even if the value is uncoded text.  For example the LOINC 43304-5 <i>Chlamydia trachomatis rRNA [Presence] in Unspecified specimen by Probe and target amplification method</i> is typically associated with coded presence/absence concepts. Using the coded value for 'negative' wtih a standard code translation the Observation.valueCodeableConcept would be:
			<pre class="json">
			"valueCodeableConcept": {
			"coding": [
			  {
				"system": "http://snomed.info/sct",
				"code": "260385009",
				"display": "Negative"
			  },
			  {
				"system": "urn:oid:2.16.840.1.113883.3.72.5.24",
				"code": "NEG",
				"display": "Negative"
			  }
			],
			"text": "Negative for Chlamydia Trachomatis rRNA"
			  }
			</pre>
	
		
		Using text only, the Observation.valueCodeableConcept the would be:
				<pre class="json">
			"valueCodeableConcept": {
			"text": "Negative for Chlamydia Trachomatis rRNA"
			  }
			</pre>
		</li>
		<li>
   Because there are multiple types allowed for the <i>value</i> element, multiple value search parameters are defined. There is no standard parameter for searching values of type Attachment, or Ratio
 </li>
		<li>
    The appliesDateTime or appliesPeriod is the time that the observation is most 
    relevant as an observation of the subject. For a biological subject (e.g. a human patient), 
    this is the physiologically relevant time of the observation. 
	In the case of an observation using a specimen, this represents the start and 
    end of the specimen collection (e.g. 24 hour Urine Sodium), but if the collection time is 
    sufficiently short, this is reported as a point in time value (e.g. normal venepuncture). 
    In the case of an observation obtained directly from a subject (e.g., BP, 
    Chest X-ray), this is the start and end time of the observation process, which again, is 
    often reported as a single point in time.
  </li>
		<li>
    At its simplest, resource instances can consist of only a type and a value, with a reliability and status flag.  
    The relevance of other properties will vary based on the type of observation.  
	Reference ranges may be useful for lab tests and other measures like systolic blood pressure, but will have little 
	relevance for something like "pregnancy status"
  </li>
		<li>Some observations have important relationships to other observations and need to be assembled in groups together (traditionally referred to as "panels" or " batteries" by laboratories) that can be used to represent relationships between the individual data items.  In addition to being able to group indiviual results in the <a href="diagnosticreport.html#4.21.2">DiagnosticReport</a>resource, the Observation resource has two structure for grouping observations which allows for complex nesting of results.  In Observation, panels can be assembled as a set of component observations or as separate resources referenced using the related element with a defined relationship type.  If the attributes within the resource for each observation is different and/or each panel result exists or needs to be processed as indepedent FHIR resources, then a panel observation referencing related panel members observations using the Observation.related element should be used to group them.  This structure also permits recursive grouping.  Conversely, if the panel members share the same attributes and are not separable observation or don't need to be processed independently, then the Observation.component element may be used to group them.
		<ul>
				<li>Several <a href="diagnosticreport-examples.html">examples</a> which demonstrate observation grouping using DiagnosticReport. </li>
				<li>The <a href="observation-example-glasgow.html">Glasgow score example</a> and <a href="obs-uslab-example6.html">GC-CT PCR</a> demonstrate grouping of observations usin the Observation.related element.</li>
				<li>The <a href="observation-example-bloodpressure.html">Blood Pressure Panel</a> and <a href="observation-example-f205-egfr.html">GFR example</a> demonstrate grouping of observations using Observation.component.</li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li>
    Most observations only have one generic reference range. Systems MAY choose to restrict to only supplying the relevant reference range based on knowledge about the patient (e.g. specific to the patient's age, gender, weight and other factors), but this may not be possible or appropriate. Whenever more than one reference range is supplied, the differences between them SHOULD be provided in the reference range and/or age properties
  </li>
		<li>
    Profiles will be created to provide guidance on capturing certain types 
    of simple observations.  This resource focuses on the level of detail
    captured by most systems.  However, any "simple" observation can easily 
	be broken into numerous components and sub-components to provide additional
    information relevant in certain circumstances.  As with other resources, 
	extensions can be used to introduce this additional complexity.
 </li>
	</ul>
</div>
