<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Observations are a central element in healthcare, used to support diagnosis, monitor progress, determine baselines and patterns 
and even capture demographic characteristics.  Most observations are simple name/value pair assertions with some metadata, 
but some observations group other observations together logically, or even are multi-component observations.
Note that the  <a href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a> resource 
provide a clinical or workflow context for a set of observations. Expected uses for the Observation resource include:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Vital signs: temperature, blood pressure, respiration rate</li>
	<li>Laboratory Data</li>
	<li>Imaging results like bone density or fetal measurements</li>
	<li>Devices Measurements such as EKG data or Pulse Oximetry data</li>
  <li>Clinical assessment tools such as APGAR</li>
  <li>Personal characteristics: height, weight, eye-color</li>
  <!--EH 12/7/2014 
  <li>Diagnoses (Note: trackable conditions, allergies, adverse reactions and more complex structures are handled elsewhere)</li>
  -->
  <li>Social history: tobacco use, family supports, cognitive status</li>
  <li>Core characteristics: pregnancy status, death assertion</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
The observation resource has the following aspects:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>status (mandatory) - all users of observations SHALL be sure of the status of the observation</li>
 <li>reliability -  provides an estimate of the degree to which quality issues have impacted on the value of an observation</li>
 <li>code (mandatory) - describes what was observed. This is the 'name' in the name/value pair assertion pattern used in this resource</li>
 <li>identifier - Unique identifier for this particular observation so it can be recognized in all contexts where it is represented</li>
 <li>value - the actual value that was observed</li>
 <li>related observations - Other observations that are components of this observation, or provide supporting information, context or warnings about this observation</li>
 <li>subject,.bodySite[x] - the patient, or group of patients, location, or device, that this observation was made on. Note that group of patients is most often used in veterinary care. For individual patients, the location on the body may also be specified, though this is often implicit in the Observation.code</li>
 <li>applies[x] - The time or time-period the observed value is asserted as being true. For biological subjects - e.g. human patients - this is usually called the "physiologically relevant time.</li>
 <li>interpretation, comments, and reference range: information to help understand the observed value</li>
 <li>method, issued, performer - additional information about how the test was performed that may help understand the observation. The method is often implicit in the Observation.code</li>
</ul>  
<p>
Typically, an observation will have either a value or component observations, and not both.
</p>

</div>
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>In contrast to the Observation resource, the <a href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a> resource typically includes additional clinical context and and some mix of atomic results, images, imaging reports, textual and coded interpretation, and formatted representations.  Laboratory reports, pathology reports, and imaging reports should be represented using the DiagnosticReport resource. The Observation resource is referenced by the DiagnosticReport to provide the atomic results for a particular investigation.</p>
<p>
    The Observation resources should not be used to record diagnosis or clinical assessments about a patient or subject that are typically captured in the <a href="condition.html">Condition</a>  resource.  However, the Observation resource is often referenced by the Condition resource to provide specific subjective and objective data to support its assertions.  There are other resources that can be considered "specializations" of the Observation resource and should be used for those specific contexts and use cases.  They include <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a> resource, <a href="familymemberhistory.html"> FamilyMemberHistory</a> resource, <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> resource, and <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resource.
</p>  
<p>In some cases, such as when source data is coming from a v2 feed, a system may not have information that allows it to distinguish diagnosis, allergy and other "specialized" types of observations from lab, vital sign and other observation types intended to be conveyed with this resource.  In those circumstances, such specialized observations may also appear using this resource.</p>
</div>
</div>
