<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
   
<p> The purpose of a Communication resource is to surface that data was shared to track adherence to guidelines or protocols or to provide business documentation of actions taken.  Communication can also be used as part of an information exchange to provide context about the information sharing occurring.</p>

<p>Communication is one of the <a href="workflow.html#event">event</a> resources in the FHIR <a href="workflow.html">workflow</a> specification.</p>
   
<p>
This resource is a record of a communication even if it is planned or has failed. A communication is a record of the conveyance of information from one entity, a sender, to another entity, a receiver. The sender and receivers may be patients, practitioners, related persons, organizations, or devices. Communication use cases include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A reminder or alert delivered to a responsible provider</li>
<li>A recorded notification from the nurse to the on-call physician (or any other specified person) that a patient's temperature exceeds a value</li>
<li>A response from a public health agency to a provider caring for a patient presenting with a communicable disease reportable to the public health agency</li>
<li>Patient educational material sent by a provider to a patient</li>
<li>Unable to deliver lab results to ordering physician</li>
<li>Submission of supplementary health information to a payer in support of a claim</li>
</ul>
<p>
Non-patient specific communication use cases may include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A nurse call from a hall bathroom</li>
<li>Advisory for battery service from a pump</li>
</ul>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): -->
<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource is a record of a communication that has occurred. It does not represent the actual flow of communication.
While <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> can track electronic disclosures of information, it cannot track conversations,
phone calls, letters and other interactions that are not system-to-system.  And even for system-to-system communications, the
specific end recipients might not be known.  Furthermore, <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvents</a> are not considered to be "part"
of the patient record, while <b>Communication</b> instances are.  The <b>Communication</b> resource is not used as a general
audit mechanism to track every disclosure of every record.  Rather, it is used when a clinician or other user wants to ensure
a record of a particular communication is itself maintained as part of the reviewable health record.
</p>
<p>
<a href="flag.html">Flag</a> resources represent a continuous ongoing "communication" alerting anyone dealing with the patient
of certain precautions to take or issues to be aware of.  The flags are continuously present as an ongoing reminder.  This is 
distinct from <b>Communication</b> where there is a specific intended sender and receiver and the information is delivered only
once.
</p>
<p>
 When there is a need to organize clinical and administrative content into sections, the <a href="composition.html">Composition</a> resource should be used instead.  For example, an initial case report to a public health agency may include organized sections for vital signs, immunizations, social history, etc..
</p>

<p><b>Communication and Encounter</b></p>
<p>
The Communication is about the transfer of information (which might or might not occur as part of an encounter), while Encounter 
is about the coming together (in person or virtually) of a Patient with a Practitioner.  Communication does not deal with 
the duration of a call, it represents the fact that information was transferred at a particular point in time.
</p>
<p>
The phone calls involving the Patient should be handled using <a href="encounter.html">Encounter</a>.  Phone calls not involving the patient 
(e.g. between practitioners or practitioner to relative) that are tracked for billing or other purposes can use Communication 
to represent the information transferred but are not ideal to represent the call itself.  
A better mechanism for handling such calls will be explored in a future release.
</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
