<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
    <p>
        <b>These resources have not yet undergone proper review by PC, CQI, CDS, and OO. At this time, 
            they are to be considered only as draft resource proposals for potential submission for DSTU2.</b>
    </p>
    
    <p>
	  This resource is a record of a communication. A communication is a conveyance of information from one entity, a sender, to another entity, a receiver. 
	  The sender and receivers may be patients, practitioners, related persons, organizations, and devices. Communication use cases include 
	  <li>A reminder or alert delivered to a responsible provider</li>
	  <li>A recorded notification from the nurse that a patient's temperature exceeds a value</li>
	  <li>A notification to a public health agency of a patient presenting with a communicable disease reportable to the public health agency</li>
      <li>Patient educational material sent by a provider to a patient</li>
    </p>
</p>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): -->
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource is a record of a communication that has occurred. It does not represent the actual flow of communication.

The resource excludes the types of communications supported by the Alert resource (need to better describe this overlap).

It excludes the type of communication where two systems are exchanging data.

</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
