<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
    
<p>
This resource is a record of a communication. A communication is a conveyance of information from one entity, a sender, to another entity, a receiver. 
The sender and receivers may be patients, practitioners, related persons, organizations, or devices. Communication use cases include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A reminder or alert delivered to a responsible provider</li>
<li>A recorded notification from the nurse that a patient's temperature exceeds a value</li>
<li>A notification to a public health agency of a patient presenting with a communicable disease reportable to the public health agency</li>
<li>Patient educational material sent by a provider to a patient</li>
</ul>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): -->
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource is a record of a communication that has occurred. It does not represent the actual flow of communication.
While <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvent</a> can track electronic disclosures of information, it cannot track conversations,
phone calls, letters and other interactions that are not system-to-system.  And even for system-to-system communications, the
specific end recipients may not be known.  As well, <a href="auditevent.html">AuditEvents</a> are not considered to be "part"
of the patient record, while <b>Communication</b> instances are.  The <b>Communication</b> resource is not used as a general
audit mechanism to track every disclosure of every record.  Rather, it is used when a clinician or other user wants to ensure
a record of a particular communication is itself maintaned as part of the reviewable health record.
</p>
<p>
<a href="flag.html">Flag</a> resources represent a continuous ongoing "communication" alerting anyone dealing with the patient
of certain precautions to take or issues to be aware of.  The flags are continuously present as an ongoing reminder.  This is 
distinct from <b>Communication</b> where there is a specific intended sender and receiver and the information is delivered only
once.
</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
