<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="notes"> </a>
<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul>
 <li>The Conformance resource provides for an application to describe its use of the RESTful
  paradigm messaging events, or FHIR documents. Usually, an application would only describe one, 
  but more than one may be described</li>
 <li>RESTful conformance rules:
  <ul class="dense">
   <li>RESTful servers are required to provide <a href="http.html#conformance">this resource on demand</a>. 
   Servers SHALL specify what resource types and operations are supported, and SHOULD also 
   specify profiles for each resource type.</li>
   <li>RESTful clients SHOULD publish a conformance statement</li>
   <li>The search parameters that a server supports (or a client makes use of) are specified in the resource profile that the conformance statement references</li>
   <li>Resource Types or operations that are not listed are not supported</li>
  </ul>  
 </li>
 <li>Messaging conformance rules:
  <ul class="dense">
   <li>The interpretation of request and response depends on the mode. If the mode is sender, 
   then request specifies what the application sends, and response specifies what it accepts. 
   If the mode is "receiver", then this is reversed</li>
   <li>If a request or response is not specified for an event, then no rules are made for it</li>
   <li>Events that are not listed are not supported</li>
  </ul>  
 </li>
 <li>Document conformance rules:
  <ul class="dense">
   <li>Document Profiles should directly constrain the Document.information.class &amp; type elements so  
    so that there is no ambiguity concerning which profile any given document conforms to</li>
  </ul>  
 </li>
 <li>Other service based use of resources: Due to the variability of these services, the <i>Conformance</i> resource 
   does not attempt to describe service based use of resources. The various service specifications will need to describe this usage in their own way</li>
</ul>  

<a name="profiles"> </a>
<h3>Supporting Profiles</h3>
<a name="tags"> </a>
<p>
A conformance profile declares two different kinds of profiles for the functionality it describes. 
The Resource Profiles are specified using Conformance.rest.resource.profile element and the System Profiles are specified using Conformance.profile element. 
</p>
<h4>Resource Profiles</h4>
<p>
These profiles describe the general features that are supported by the system for each kind of 
resource. Typically, this is the superset of all the different use-cases implemented by the system. 
This is a resource-level perspective of the system functionality. 
</p>
<h4>System Profiles</h4>
<p>
These profiles describe the information handled/produced by the system on a per use case basis.
Some examples of the uses for system profiles:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A Laboratory service producing a set of different reports - general chemistry, blood count, etc. Typical labs would support several hundred different reports</li>
 <li>A care manager which handles a set of different types of care plans and associated clinical resources</li>
 <li>A medications formulary that handles several different levels of sophistication in its medication representations</li>
</ul> 
<p>
Typically, these profiles are a series of variations on the same set of resources - different use cases leading to handling 
the resources that represent them differently. These use-cases described above all pertain to system that produce and publish
data, but the same concept applies to systems that consume data. For instance:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>An expert service that provides analysis on several different sets of data conforming to a particular pattern - tests x,y and z with particular codes and units</li>
</ul>
<p>
For producer and a consumer systems to exchange data successfully based on 
one of these system supported profiles, it's not enough to know that the
systems happen to have system profiles that overlap for the use case 
of interest; the consumer must be able to filter the total set of resources
made available by the producer system and deal only with the ones relevant
to the use case. 
</p>
<p>
As an example consider a laboratory system generating 1000s of reports 
a day. 1% of those reports are a particular endocrine report that a 
decision support system knows how to process. Both systems declare that 
they support the particular endocrine profile, but how does the expert
system actually find the endocrine reports that it knows how to process? 
</p>
<p>
One possible option is for the expert system to receive every single 
report coming from the lab system, check whether it conforms to the 
profile or not, and then decide whether to process it. Checking whether
a resource conforms to a particular profile or not is a straight 
forward operation (on option is to use the <a href="downloads.html">provided tools for this</a>),
but this is very inefficient way - the expert system has to receive 
and process 100 times many resources as it uses. To help a consumer 
find the correct set of reports for a use-case, the producer of the 
resources also SHALL:
</p>
<ol>
 <li><a href="resource.html#tags">Mark resources</a> with profile assertions documenting the profile(s) they conform to (this enables indexing by the profile)</li>
 <li>(if a server) support searching by the <a href="search.html#profile">_profile parameter</a> for the declared profiles</li>
</ol>
<p>
Beyond these requirements, a producer of resources SHOULD ensure that any data that would reasonably be expected
to conform to the declared profiles SHOULD be published in this form. 
</p>

<a name="dstu"> </a>
<blockquote>
<p>
DSTU note: there are many uninvestigated issues associated with system profiles. 
HL7 is actively seeking feedback from users who experiment with system profiles, and users
should be prepared for changes to features and obligations in this area in the future.
</p>
</blockquote>

</div>
