<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    
<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource is used to share relevant information required to support a referral request or a transfer of care request from one 
practitioner or organization to another. It is intended for use when a patient is required to be referred to another provider for a 
consultation/second opinion and/or for short term or longer term management of one or more health issues or problems. 
</p>
<p>
Examples include:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Request for a consult from a specialist</li>
  <li>Referral for support from community services</li>
  <li>District nursing services referral</li>
  <li>Request for Aged care placement assessment</li>
  <li>Request for a pharmacist medication review</li>
  <li>Referral for physiotherapy or occupational therapy</li>
</ul>
<p>
ReferralRequest is also intended for use when a complete and more permanent transfer of care responsibility from one 
practitioner/organization to another. For example as in the case of requesting the transfer of care for a patient from 
an acute care setting to rehabilitation, aged care, or skilled nursing facility.
</p>
</div>
    

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
ReferralRequest is closely related to other types of "request" resources, particularly <a href="diagnosticorder.html">DiagnosticOrder</a>
and <a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a>.  In fact, for some services, it may be appropriate to use any one of these
resources to request that the service be performed.  Which one is used may be driven by organization practice and by context.  When
it is unclear which to use, the following principles may be helpful:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
ProcedureRequest or DiagnosticOrder are typically used when the requesting clinician has and wishes to exercise the authority 
(and expertise) to decide exactly what action will be done.
</li>
<li>
A ReferralRequest is used when the requesting practitioner is seeking another practitioner or organization to use their own expertise
and/or authority to determine the specific action to take.
</li>
<li>
Whether an activity is deemed to be a procedure or only a diagnostic order is typically driven by how invasive the diagnostic process
is.  More invasive processes are typically represented as procedures, though the dividing line may vary by organization.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Irrespective of the guidance above, systems should be prepared for some degree of overlap between these resources and be
prepared to execute searches against multiple resources in cases where differentiation cannot be guaranteed.  As well, in some workflows
more than one type of resource or even all three might exist.  E.g. Upon receiving a ReferralRequest a practitioner might initiate a 
DiagnosticOrder.  The diagnostic service might then initiate a ProcedureRequest.
</p>
<p>
A "referral" is often thought of as a document that contains a great deal of information about the patient being referred.  This
resource does not actually contain the clinical background information for the patient.  Instead, it supports references to
the numerous other resources that define this information.  For example, Condition, Family History, Allergy/Intolerance, Alerts, 
Medication, Diagnostic Reports, etc.  While some systems may choose to bundle up a ReferralRequest and this referenced information
into a <a href="documents.html">Document</a> for delivery to the recipient.  However, <a href="http.html">REST</a>,
<a href="messaging.html">Messaging</a> and <a href="services.html">Services</a> are also valid architectures for managing
referrals and may be more appropriate where active workflow management is needed.
</p>
<p>
The details of the type of care desired as part of a referral may be conveyed using any of the "request" or "order" resources,
likely with a status of "proposed".  The <a href="careplan.html">CarePlan</a> resource can be used to describe more sophisticated
requests for combinations of services.  Likewise, ReferralRequest may be referenced as part of a CarePlan.
</p>
<p>
Referrals may be targeted (identifying a specific Practitioner or Organization to perform the requested care) or untargeted
(merely identifying the type of care desired).  The <a href="order.html">Order</a> and <a href="orderresponse.html">OrderResponse</a>
resources may be used to help manage such workflows
</p>
</div>

<!--
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
