<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<!--
subjects to cover:

* using login 
 * hashing
* claim types
  * searching claim types
  

-->
<h3>Managing the Authentication Process</h3>

<p>
The SecurityPrincipal resource is used to:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>identify the user/device</li>
 <li>connect that user to their associated resources</li>
 <li>relate the user to a set of claims that are used by the access control system to grant specific requests</li>
 <li>identify the target of a <a href="auditevent.html">audit event</a></li>
</ul>
<p>
The user may be authenticated by a variety of methods, including by delegation to
an identity server (e.g. by using OAuth). The choice of which authentication method is appropriate is 
driven by context, and business and regulatory considerations.
</p>
<p>
One way to authenticate the user is directly by username/password. The SecurityPrincipal
resource includes the elements "login" and "passwordHash" to support this process. The
expectation in this case is that a server will provide an HTML form for the user
to fill out the username and password, and/or it will provide an endpoint that 
accepts a username and password. Note that this specification does not specify any
protocol for this exchange. Either way, the server's hash of the password 
must match the hash record in the resource. 
</p>
<p>
Server's that use a password based login, and that allow clients to administer the
users have to provide a method for the client to generate a password hash, in order
for the client to correctly populate the passwordHash element. This can be achieved 
using the <a href="securityprincipal-operations.html">$hash operation</a>.
</p>

<h3>Security Claim Types</h3>

<p>
For further information concerning security claims, see <a href="securityclaimtype.html">Security Claim Types</a>.
This resource defines two search parameters for claims, "type" and "claim". <i>type</i> is a uri search that searches for 
any security principal resources with claims of a partocular type, but a URL. <i>claim</i> is a token search that searches
both "type" and "claim" - if the token includes a namespace, portion, then the namespace portion relates to the 
security type (e.g. the "type" and "claim" correspond to "system" and "code" from a <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a>
data type for searching purposes).
</p>
<p>
The claims function as a Set - that is, the full set of claims for a principal is the union of the claims made
for the principal itself, and those made for all the principal's groups.
</p>


</div>
