<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"> </a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p><b><i>For an overview of this resource and others in the Medication Definition domain, also see the <a href="medication-definition-module.html">module page</a></i></b></p>
		<p>
			ClinicalUseDefinition is to record an instance of facts about a particular medication, substance, 
			device, procedure, biologically derived product or nutrition product, in relation to its intended use (indication), 
			situations where it should not normally be used (contraindication), 
			known side effects (undesirable effects), clashes with other substances - medications, foods etc.. 
			(interactions) and critical information about risks or hazards to caution the user or consumer (warnings). 
			The resource is used to record one such instance, and all its details. 
		</p>
	</div>
	<div>
		<a name="bnr"> </a>
		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
		<p>
			The ClinicalUseDefinition resource is designed to represent definitional facts about the potential use of a medication, substance, 
			device, procedure, biologically derived product, or nutrition product.
		</p>
		<p>
			These may be used when submitting a product dossier to regulators, as part of an electronic medication or medical device knowledge base, or directly during
			decision support activities.
		</p>
		<p>
			The clinical issue does not refer to any actual instance of the medication, device or procedure etc.. being used, or to any actual patient event. 
		</p>
		<p>
			The resource is used to record one instance of one of these: 
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Indication - A medical situation in which a medicinal product, medical device or procedure etc.. is appropriate for use</li>
			<li>Contraindication - A reason why a medicinal product, medical device or procedure etc.. is not to be used in a certain context</li>
			<li>Interaction - The interactions of the medicinal product or medical device etc.. with other medicinal products, food, substances etc..</li>
			<li>Undesirable Effect - A potential negative outcome from the use of a medicinal product, medical device or procedure etc.. See also AdverseEvent, which is for actual events (or near misses), and AllergyIntolerance.</li>
			<li>Warning – Critical information about the environmental or health or physical risks or hazards, that serve as caution to the user or consumer.</li>
		</ul>
	</div>

</div>
