<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource covers the supply of all medications to a patient.  Examples include dispensing and pick-up from an out-patient pharmacy, 
dispensing patient-specific medications from in-patient pharmacy to ward as well as issuing a single dose from ward stock to a patient for consumption.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
<b>The Medication domain includes a number of related resources</b>
</p>
<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="2" frame="box">
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationprescription.html">MedicationPrescription</a></td>
        <td>An order for both supply of the medication and the instructions for administration of the medicine to a patient.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>MedicationDispense</td>
        <td>Provision of a supply of a medication with the intention that it is subsequently consumed by a patient (usually in response to a prescription).  </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationadministration.html">MedicationAdministration</a></td>
        <td>When a patient actually consumes a medicine, or it is otherwise administered to them</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationstatement.html">MedicationStatement</a></td>
        <td>This is a record of medication being taken by a patient, or that the medication has been given to a patient where the record is the result of a report from the patient, or another clinician. 
          A medication statement is not a part of the prescribe->dispense->administer sequence but is a report that such a sequence (or at least a part of it) did take place resulting in a belief that the patient has received a particular medication.
        </td>
    </tr>
</table>
<p>
This resource does not deal with the supply or transfer of non-medication related items to a patient.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>    
    The supply and the associated administration instructions may not exactly follow the original order (prescription) either because some details were left for completion at this point in the process, or because the dispenser exercised their clinical judgment to make some appropriate modification.
</p>
</div>
    
</div>
