<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The audit event is based on the IHE-ATNA Audit record definitions, originally from <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3881">RFC 3881</a>, and now managed by
DICOM (see <a href="http://medical.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/html/part15.html#sect_A.5">DICOM Part 15 Annex A5</a>). 
</p>
<ul>
<li>ASTM E2147 – Setup the concept of security audit logs for healthcare including accounting of disclosures</li>
<li>IETF RFC 3881 – Defined the Information Model (IETF rule forced this to be informative)</li>
<li>DICOM Audit Log Message – Made the information model Normative, defined Vocabulary, Transport Binding, and Schema</li>
<li>IHE ATNA – defines the grouping with secure transport and access controls; and defined specific audit log records for specific IHE transactions.</li>
<li>NIST SP800-92 – shows how to do audit log management and reporting – consistent with our model</li>
<li>HL7 PASS – Defined an Audit Service with responsibilities and a query interface for reporting use</li>
<li>ISO 27789 – Defined the subset of audit events that an EHR would need </li>
</ul>
<p>
This resource is managed collaboratively between HL7, DICOM, and IHE. 
</p>
<p>
The primary purpose of this resource is the maintenance of security audit log information.  However, 
it can also be used for any audit logging needs and simple event-based notification.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Servers that provide support for Audit Event resources would not generally accept update or delete 
operations on the resources, as this would compromise the integrity of the audit record. Access of the AuditEvent
would typically be limited to Security office, Privacy office, or other Systems Administration purposes. The AuditEvent 
is not intended to be used directly by Providers or Patients, although reports generated from the raw data would 
be useful. An example is a Patient centric Accounting of Disclosures or an Access Report.
</p>
<p>
All actors involved in an auditable event should record an AuditEvent (See Audit Event Sub-Type vocabulary for guidance on 
some security relevant events). This would result in duplicate AuditEvent entries which show the properly working system 
of systems. Thus it is typical to get an auditable event recorded by both the application, and server. I this way duplicate 
entries are expected, this is helpful because detecting when only one actor records that an auditable event is an indication 
of a security problem.  There may be non-participaing actors that also detect a security relevant event and thus would record 
an AuditEvent, such as a trusted intermediary.
</p>
<p>
Security Relevant events are not limited to communications or RESTful events. They include software startup and shutdown; 
user login and logout; access control decisions; configuration events; software installation; policy rules changes; 
and manipulation of data that exposes the data to users.
</p>
<p>
Audit Event resources are often (though not exclusively) 
created by the application responding to the create/read/query/update/delete/execute etc. event. 
A <a href="provenance.html">Provenance resource</a> contains overlapping information, but is a 
record-keeping assertion that gathers information about the context in which the information in a resource was obtained. 
Provenance resources are prepared by the application that initiates the create/update of the resource.
</p>
</div>

</div>
