<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Notes</h2>
<ul>
 <li>The value of the <i>system</i> and <i>code</i> element are the same as used by the <a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a> data type</li>
 <li>When a mapping equivalence is characterized as "narrower", some explanation of the scope difference SHALL be provided in the comments</li>
 <li>The concept map is a statement of mapping in a single direction. The existence of a matching mapping in the reverse direction cannot be assumed to exist automatically, but only through human review</li>
</ul>

<h2>Concept Translation</h2>
<p>
An application may offer to provide concept translation services for other 
applications. In this case, the standard way for an application to 
ask for concept translation is to perform a 
<a href="search.html">search</a> on the value set with _query=translate:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [service-url]/ConceptMap/?_query=translate&amp;identity=:valueSet&amp;system=:system&amp;version=:version&amp;code=:code&amp;...
</pre>
<p>
The identifier is the <a href="valueset-definitions.html#ValueSet.identifier">ValueSet.identifier</a> of the 
value set used when the concept (system/code pair) was chosen. If an identifier is provided, the application
performing the translation can locate a concept map for a matching value set; if no value set is identified,
the application must look for a code equivalence assertion in a concept map where the value set the provides
context matches the entire code system. The values for system, version, and code are those from the 
<a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a> data type. Version is optional, and code and system are mandatory. 
Alternatively, the parameter "coding" or "codeableconcept" can be used - the value of these parameters is a 
URL encoded XML or JSON representation of the two data types respectively. 
</p>
<p>
The result of this query is an <a href="operationoutcome.html">Operation Outcome</a> with an extension
<a href="general-extensions.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/Profile/general-extensions#translation</a>, which 
is a codeableConcept that expresses the translation, if one could be found, or an error if one could not 
be found. The Operation Outcome may include warnings about how the translation was made. 
</p>

</div>
