<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<a name="srch"></a>
<h2>SearchParameters on Extensions</h2>
<p>
The SearchParameter resource may be used to define searches on extensions.
A simple definition defines the code, the base resource the extension can be 
found in, and a type, and an expression. Assume that the extension is <code>http://example.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/extension-thumb-length</code>
which has a value that is a quantity, and that is used on patient, then an appropriate SearchParameter would be:
</p>
<pre class="json">
   "code" : "thumb-length",
   "base" : ["Patient"],
   "type" : "quantity",
   "expression" : "Patient.extension('http://example.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/extension-thumb-length').value"
</pre>
<p>
Servers MAY attempt to process expressions that just select the extension without the <code>.value</code>, but this
is not required and may be discouraged or deprecated in the future. 
</p>
<p>
Extensions may have multiple types with different search behaviours, so the type can be specifically selected:
</p>
<pre class="json">
   "code" : "thumb-length-code",
   "base" : ["Patient"],
   "type" : "token",
   "expression" : "Patient.extension('http://example.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/extension-thumb-length').value.ofType(CodeableConcept)"
</pre>
<p>
This example would select coded thumb lengths and index them only for the <code>thumb-length-code</code> search parameter.
When an extension can have multiple types with incompatible search behaviour, the search 
parameters have to do this. Note that is type casting the extension directly (e.g.
<code>Patient.extension('...').ofType(CodeableConcept)</code>) will lead to an empty index, 
since the extension is not a CodeableConcept itself.
</p>
<p>
When extensions can be used in multiple places, these places are enumerated in the expression:
</p>
<pre>
Patient.extension('http://example.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/extension-thumb-length').value
 | Patient.contact.extension('http://example.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/extension-thumb-length').value
 | Practitioner.extension('http://example.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/extension-thumb-length').value
</pre>
<p>
Notes:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    If the extension's context specifies multiple resources, they are represented with multiple 
    elements in the <code>SearchParameter.base</code> array
  </li>
  <li>
    An expression like <code>Resource.descendents.extension('extension-url').value is possible, but this 
    is a low performance option for a server to evaluate, and search parameter expressions are performance 
    sensitive</code>
  </li>
</ul>

</div>
