<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->

<p>CommunicationRequest is one of the <a href="workflow.html#request">request</a> resources in the FHIR <a href="workflow.html">workflow</a> specification.</p>

<p>
This resource is a record of a request for a communication to be performed. A communication is a conveyance of information from one entity, a sender, to another entity, a receiver. The requester requests the sender to send the payload to the recipient. The sender and receivers may be patients, practitioners, related persons, organizations, and devices. Some uses of communication request include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A computer-based decision-support system requesting a reminder or alert be delivered to a responsible provider</li>
<li>A physician requesting notification from the nurse if a patient's temperature exceeds a value</li>
<li>A monitoring system or a provider requesting a staff member or department to notify a public health agency of a patient presenting with a communicable disease reportable to the public health agency</li>
<li>A computer-based decision-support system proposes to send educational material to a patient</li>
<li>A physician requesting that the results of an imaging order they placed are also sent to a third party (provider, organization, etc.)</li>
</ul>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): -->
<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>

<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource is a record of a request. It does not represent the actual flow of communication.
</p>
<p>
The use of <b>CommunicationRequest</b> excludes requests for referrals and requests for therapy or counseling which would be handled by the <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a> resource.
The fulfillment of a <b>CommunicationRequest</b> may result in a <a href="communication.html">Communication</a> resource.
</p>
<p>
The CommunicationRequest resource represents an authorization for a service to be provided. Details about the fulfillment of the authorization are handled by the <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource. For further information about this separation of responsibilities, refer to the <a href="request.html#fulfillment">Fulfillment/Execution</a> section of the Request pattern.
</p>

</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
