<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
    
<p>
This resource is a record of a request for a communication to be performed. A communication is a conveyance of information from one entity, a sender, to another entity, a receiver. The sender and receivers may be patients, practitioners, related persons, organizations, and devices. Uses of communication request include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A computer-based decision-support system requesting a reminder or alert be delivered to a responsible provider</li>
<li>A physician requesting notification from the nurse if a patient's temperature exceeds a value</li>
<li>A monitoring system or a provider requesting a staff member or department to notify a public health agency of a patient presenting with a communicable disease reportable to the public health agency</li>
<li>A computer-based decision-support system proposes to send educational material to a patient</li>
</ul>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): -->
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource is a record of a request. It does not represent the actual flow of communication.

The use of <b>CommunicationRequest</b> excludes requests for referrals which are covered by the <a href="referralrequest.html">ReferralRequest</a> resource.
It also excludes requests for therapy or counciling which would be handled by the <a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a> resource.
The performance of a <b>CommunicationRequest</b> may result in a <a href="communication.html">Communication</a> resource.

</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
