<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
    <p>
        <b>These resources have not yet undergone proper review by PC, CQI, CDS, and OO. At this time, 
            they are to be considered only as draft resource proposals for potential submission.</b>
    </p>
    
    <p>
	  This resource is a record of a request for a communication to be performed. A communication is a conveyance of information from one entity, a sender, to another entity, a receiver. The sender and receivers may be patients, practitioners, related persons, organizations, and devices. Uses of communication request include 
	  <li>A computer-based decision-support system requesting a reminder or alert be delivered to a responsible provider</li>
	  <li>A physician requesting notification from the nurse if a patient's temperature exceeds a value</li>
	  <li>A monitoring system or a provider requesting a staff member or department to notify a public health agency of a patient presenting with a communicable disease reportable to the public health agency</li>
      <li>A computer-based decision-support system proposes to send educational material to a patient</li>
    </p>
</p>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): -->
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource is a record of a request. It does not represent the actual flow of communication.

The use of CommunicationRequest excludes requests for referrals which are covered by the ReferralRequest resource.

The resource also excludes the types of communications supported by the Alert resource (need to better describe this overlap).

The transmission of orders and the ensuing responses are described by Order and OrderResponse resources.

The performance of a communication request may result in a Communication resource.

</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
