<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The ProcessRequest resource allows for the specification of an action to be performed on an existing resporce or resources and the 
provides the additional supporting information to support that action. The actions currently defined are: cancel, poll, 
reprocess, and status. 
</p>
<p>

</p>
<p>
<b>Cancel</b> indicates the resource which is to be reversed and provides both supporting 
information for the reversal and whether the receiving system is permitted to retain a copy of the 
reversed resource.
</p>
<p>
The Cancel is the formal request to cease processing an incomplete prior request or to reverse 
and/or nullify a complete prior request or information submission. When nullify=true then all copies 
of the original submission are to be purged, although audit logs may be retained. When Nullify=false 
a copy of the original request may be retained. A ProcessResponse may be craeted or returned to indicate 
whether the requestion action was accepted and scucessful.
</p>

<p>
<b>Poll</b> provides supporting information for the poll request. The response to 
this is a previously undelivered response or a StatusResponse (or other acknowledgement stype resource which may 
contain errors). 
</p>
<p>
This is a formal request for Payors or systems which require such and/or transports which don't 
support a 'Get Operation', for the retrieval of pended, held, resources.
</p>
<p>
A simple Poll request, one which doesn't specify: request, include, exclude or period; would return
any pended resource. Specific types of business behaviors may be supported by providing values for the
filtering elements, for example:
<ul>
<li>Get any pended resource - no filters specified</li>
<li>Get deferred response to a Claim - specify the Claim in the 'request'</li>
<li>Get all Supporting Documentation - specify 'SupportingDocumentation' as an 'include'</li>
<li>Get an Explanation of Benefit - specify 'ExplanationOfBenefit' as an 'include'</li>
<li>Get a payment reconciliation - specify a 'period' which contains the expected reconciliation 
creation date, and specify 'PaymentReconciliation' as an 'include'</li> 
</ul> 
</p>

<p>

<p>
<b>Reprocess</b> indicates the resource which is to be reprocessed, for example a claim to be readjudicated or a specemin or diagnostic image to be re-examined, 
and provides both supporting information for the reprocessing and the line items which are to be reprocessed.
</p>
<p>
This is necessary for the limited supporters who require the ability to formally request the 
reprocessing of specified service sub-trees from an already processed resource such as a previously adjudicated Claim.
</p>

<p>
<b>Status</b> indicates the resource for which the processing status is requested and 
provides supporting information for the status request.

</p>
<p>
This is a formal request for Payors which require such and/or transports which don't support a
'Get Operation', for the processing status of a previously submitted processing request.
</p>

<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
</p>
</div>

<!-- (recommended): 
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Explains how this resource relates to others. Particularly important is to differentiate between appropriate usages for related resources when an implementer might be confused about what to reference when.
</p>
</div>
-->

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->


</div>
