<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

		<a name="notes"></a>
		<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Many service requests will create a need to specify a specimen, body site, or body system. The request <code>code</code> will often have this information embedded in it - for example, 'serum glucose' or 'chest x-ray'. Alternatively, the <code>servicerequest-specimenSuggestion</code> extension may be used to specify an existing specimen or the type of specimen expected to be collected, or a <code>bodyStructure</code> element may be used to specify a body site or body system.</li>
			<li>Most commonly the association between the Specimen and ServiceRequest resources will be from the Specimen to the ServiceRequest, as usually the ServiceRequest is created first and provides the authorization for the specimen to be collected, and the reference to the ServiceRequest is recorded using the <a href="specimen-definitions.html#Specimen.request">Specimen.request</a> element.</li>
			<li>In the less common cases where the specimen to be used to perform the test is already known and available and needs to be specified at the time the ServiceRequest is created, it is preferable to use the 'specimenSuggestion' extension on the ServiceRequest resource, which enables specifying a particular specimen to be used either by a direct reference to a Specimen resource, more generally by a coded concept specifying the specimen type, or by a reference to another ServiceRequest that produced the existing specimen(s). When a specimen is suggested, it is expected to be used. If for some reason the suggested specimen is unable to be used (doesn't exist, wrong specimen type, insufficient quantity or quality, etc.), the decision to collect another specimen or to not perform the test must be based on established policies or determined by some other means agreed to with the requester.</li>
			<li>The <code>reason</code> element may be used to support billing. It may relate to the resources referred to in <code>supportingInfo</code> element and may also be used to decide how a procedure or diagnostic investigation will be performed, or even if it will be performed at all</li>
			<li>To capture the workflow around the solicitation of potential ServiceRequests based on time, price, etc, use the level 2 code "solicit-offer" on the "ask" ServiceRequest. For the ServiceRequest response to an "ask" ServiceRequest, use the level 2 code "offer-response" along with a basedOn reference to the "ask" ServiceRequest.</li>
		</ul>
</div>
