<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

		<a name="notes"></a>
		<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
		<ul>
			<li>Many service requests will create a need to specify a specimen, body site, or body system. The request <code>code</code> will often have this information embedded in it - for example, 'serum glucose' or 'chest x-ray'. Alternatively, the <code>servicerequest-specimenSuggestion</code> extension may be used to specify an existing specimen or the type of specimen expected to be collected, or a <code>bodyStructure</code> element may be used to specify a body site or body system.</li>
			<li>Most commonly the association between the Specimen and ServiceRequest resources will be from the Specimen to the ServiceRequest, as usually the ServiceRequest is created first and provides the authorization for the specimen to be collected, and the reference to the ServiceRequest is recorded using the <a href="specimen-definitions.html#Specimen.request">Specimen.request</a> element.</li>
			<li>In the less common cases where the specimen to be used to perform the test is already known and available and needs to be specified at the time the ServiceRequest is created, it is preferable to use the 'specimenSuggestion' extension on the ServiceRequest resource, which enables specifying a particular specimen to be used either by a direct reference to a Specimen resource, more generally by a coded concept specifying the specimen type, or by a reference to another ServiceRequest that produced the existing specimen(s). When a specimen is suggested, it is expected to be used. If for some reason the suggested specimen is unable to be used (doesn't exist, wrong specimen type, insufficient quantity or quality, etc.), the decision to collect another specimen or to not perform the test must be based on established policies or determined by some other means agreed to with the requester.</li>
			<li>The <code>reason</code> element may be used to support billing. It may relate to the resources referred to in <code>supportingInfo</code> element and may also be used to decide how a procedure or diagnostic investigation will be performed, or even if it will be performed at all</li>
			<li>To capture the workflow around the solicitation of potential ServiceRequests based on time, price, etc, use the level 2 code "solicit-offer" on the "ask" ServiceRequest. For the ServiceRequest response to an "ask" ServiceRequest, use the level 2 code "offer-response" along with a basedOn reference to the "ask" ServiceRequest.</li>
			<li>Use <code>orderDetail</code> to provide details about the request, such as information to collect from the patient, body positioning, appropriate device settings, preferred bandage size, etc. Each repetition of <code>orderDetail</code> includes a list of parameter codes and values providing the details. If the details pertain to a specific device, substance, medication, or other item involved in the service, that item is indicated in the <code>parameterFocus[x]</code> element; if the details are more generally about the service itself, <code>parameterFocus</code> is omitted.
				<p>The <code>parameterFocus[x]</code> choice element allows several ways to identify the target of the parameters:</p>
				<ul>
					<li><code>parameterFocusReference</code> is used when there is a specific resource that is the target of the focus. This is the most common choice type, and, depending on the referenced resource, may indicate a specific item (e.g., Device, BiologicallyDerivedProduct), or types of items (e.g., Medication, Substance); it may also reference related requests. This would be appropriate when providing details, e.g. oxygen flow rate, for a specific ventilator device known to be at the patient's bedside.</li>
					<li><code>parameterFocusCanonical</code> is used when a canonical resource provides the definition of a type of resource. This could be used when the specific instance is not known for the device to be used, but that it ought to be a particular make and model.</li>
					<li><code>parameterFocusCodeableConcept</code> may be used to specify, for example, device or medication types as a coded value. The specificity of the code is implementation dependent, and could identify a broad class of device (e.g. "ventilator") or a specific model.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>Generally, <code>parameterFocusReference</code> or <code>parameterFocusCanonical</code> provide more information; however, implementations that do not use definitional resources (such as DeviceDefinition or Medication) might prefer to use <code>parameterFocusCodeableConcept</code>.</p>
				<p>The <code>orderDetail.parameter.code</code> is used to identify the detail being specified. The codes used are typically dependent on the focus item (if any) and may be implementation specific. Similarly, the type of the <code>orderDetail.parameter.value[x]</code> choice element and the appropriate value will depend on the focus item (if any) and parameter code.</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
</div>
