<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
  <a name="scope"></a>
  <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
  <p>
    This document contains information about the <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> resource and details specific to options in it.  It is defined as part of the topic-based model of Subscriptions (Publish / Subscribe pattern).
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> resource is used to define conceptual or computable events for <code>Subscription</code> resources.  Conceptually, subscription topics specify:
    <ul>
      <li>What causes a notification, either by referencing an event definition in an event trigger (e.g., <code>http://example.com/fhir/events#something-interesting-happened</code>) or by describing a resource state change in a resource trigger (e.g., an <code>Encounter</code> is created or updated to have an <code>Encounter.state</code> of <code>active</code>).</li>
      <li>What filters a client is allowed to request.  For example, a topic that allows clients to restrict notifications to a particular patient id or group, a specific procedure, etc., relevant to that particular topic.</li>
      <li>What related resources the server MAY include in notifications.  For example, while a discharge notification would likely be focused on the <code>Encounter</code> resource, since that is the resource that is updated, it is likely desireable to include the patient information, observations, diagnosed conditions, location information, etc.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    Subscription Topics are intended to be discoverable, reusable, and extensible.  Definitions should be computably defined whenever possible, but the conceptual definition is the arbiter between any discrepancies.  For example, a query-based and a FHIRPath-based definition may differ slightly because of what is expressable in each language.  In such cases, the goal is correct implementation of the concept - not literal translations between computable definitions.
  </p>
</div>

<div>
  <a name="bnr"></a>
  <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
  <p>
    The <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> resource is used in the Pub/Sub (Publisher/Subscriber) model of FHIR Subscriptions.  Information about the Boundaries and Relationships both within the Subscriptions Framework and to other areas of the FHIR specification can be found <a href="subscription.html#bnr">here</a>.
  </p>
</div>

</div>
