<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
  <a name="scope"></a>
  <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
  <p>
    The <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> resource is used to define conceptual or computable events for <a href="subscription.html">Subscription</a> resources.  A <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> defines the <b>data</b> and <b>change</b> of interest so that implementing servers can implement specific functionality around subscriptions and clearly communicate boundaries to clients.  In other words, a SubscriptionTopic is a way of describing a state change to know that it is of interest.  Because it covers a state change, a SubscriptionTopic is typically defined with either a resource-operation pair or resource values tested against the previous and current states.
  </p>
  <p>
    A <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> represents a well-defined concept to both a client and a server.  These concepts fall under several categories:
    <ul>
      <li>
        Concept Definition - e.g., Start of a Clinical Encounter, New Observation
      </li>
      <li>
        Resource Operation Pairs - e.g., <code>create</code> on <code>Observation</code> resources
      </li>
      <li>
        Resource Value Tests - e.g., Encounter:<code>%previous.status!='in-progress' and %current.status='in-progress'</code>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
</div>

<div>
  <a name="bnr"></a>
  <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
  <p>
    There is a close relationship between <a href="subscriptiontopic.html">SubscriptionTopic</a> and <code>Subscription</code>.
    <ul>
      <li>
        A <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> defines the <b>data</b> and <b>change</b> a <code>Subscription</code> uses to trigger notifications.
      </li>
      <li>
        A <code>Subscription</code> describes a particular client's request to be notified about events defined in a <code>SubscriptionTopic</code> and how those notifications should be delivered.
      </li>
      <li>
        A <code>Subscription</code> may define additional filters to be applied when detecting events for notifications, but only as defined and allowed in the relevant <code>SubscriptionTopic</code>.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    The use of Subscriptions requires the use of SubscriptionTopics - without an underlying SubscriptionTopic, a Subscription has no meaning and will not trigger any client notifications.
  </p>
</div>

</div>
