<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
An instance of ObservationDefinition represents the definitional aspects of a kind of observation. This resource is used in a catalog of products or services for healthcare. It provides the definition of observations, which are used as input or produced as outcome of these products and services. The focus of the definitional aspects of ObservationDefinition is not on the action of performing observations of that kind. Rather, it is on the outcome of the observations. An instance of ObservationDefinition represents a set of constraints applicable to the value produced by observations of this kind. This set of constraints may have two utilities: 1) It guides the entry of the result of an observation of the kind defined. 2) It helps the consumer of the results of observations of that kind, to interpret properly these results.
</p>
<p>
For instance, in a catalog of laboratory in vitro diagnostic services, the ObservationDefinition resources describe the observations that should be provided by the orderer alongside with an ordered service (questions asked at order entry or at specimen collection, prior results) as well as the observations that will be reported once the service has been performed.
</p>
<p>
In a catalog of medications, ObservationDefinition resources can be used to describe observations the result thereof need to be checked against the prescription of a particular medicinal product (therapeutic range, units ...)
</p>
<p>
In the catalog of tests of an in vitro diagnostic device, ObservationDefinition resources can be used to characterize (absolute range, unit, decimal precision, critical values ...) the observations that will be produced by the IVD tests performed by the device.
</p>
<p>
ObservationDefinition may be used to characterize observations from any discipline.
</p>
</div>


<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
An ObservationDefinition resource provides the definitional characteristics for a certain kind of observation. Each time that kind of observation is collected and recorded it is instantiated as an Observation resource, which conforms to these definitional characteristics. Thus, there is a relationship between ObservationDefinition and Observation: The latter may instantiate the former.
</p>
<p>
When an Observation instantiates an ObservationDefinition, the elements of the Observation resource are expected to inherit their content from the corresponding definitional elements declared in the ObservationDefinition resource:</p>
 <ul>
<li>Category, code, datatype of the value, bodySite, method.</li>
<li>Each referenceRange element present in Observation should come from a qualifiedInterval element of ObservationDefinition.</li>
<li>If ObservationDefinition has declared a ValueSet of valid coded values, and if Observation has a valueCodeableConcept, the value is expected to be part of that ValueSet.</li>
<li>The subject of the Observation should be conformant with one of the subjectCodeableConcept listed in ObservationDefinition.</li>
<li>If the Observation has a device element, the referenced Device resource should conform to a DeviceDefinition or Device referenced by ObservationDefinition.device (if present).</li>
<li>If the Observation has a specimen element, the referenced Specimen resource should conform to a SpecimenDefinition referenced by ObservationDefinition.specimen (if present).</li>
</ul>
<p>
ObservationDefinition enables to express some Quantity results in two distinct units of measure: the primary or SI one, represented by element unit, and a converted one, provided for accommodation of some actors, represented by element customaryUnit. Observation may pick only the primary unit, or may express its result in both units, in two component results.</p>
</div>


<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
