<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
<p><b>Note to Balloters for Ballot5</b>: ObservationDefinition changes in this window include repeatable identifiers, new bindings on <code>subjectType</code> and <code>performerType</code>, restored jurisdiction status, and focused narrative, mapping, and terminology cleanup.</p>
<p><b>Compatible substantive</b></p>
<ul>
<li>Cardinality of <code>ObservationDefinition.identifier</code> relaxed to <code>0..*</code> so a definition can carry more than one business identifier <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-55272">FHIR-55272</a></li>
<li>Added the missing value-set binding for <code>ObservationDefinition.subjectType</code> <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54594">FHIR-54594</a></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Non-substantive</b></p>
<ul>
<li><code>ObservationDefinition.jurisdiction</code> is no longer marked deprecated; an explanatory deprecation note is retained on the element <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53766">FHIR-53766</a></li>
<li>Added the missing value-set binding for the coded concept on <code>ObservationDefinition.performerType</code> <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54593">FHIR-54593</a></li>
<li>Clarified the short description of <code>ObservationDefinition.subject</code> <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53677">FHIR-53677</a></li>
<li>Updated the Five Ws mappings <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54961">FHIR-54961</a></li>
<li>Minor cleanup of value-set display names <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-56060">FHIR-56060</a></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Additional changes</b></p>
<ul>
<li>Additional changes as described in <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54843">FHIR-54843</a> and <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53681">FHIR-53681</a>.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
An instance of ObservationDefinition represents the definitional aspects of a kind of observation. This resource is used in a catalog of products or services for healthcare. It represents a set of constraints applicable to the value produced by observations of this kind. It helps the consumer of the results of observations of that kind, to interpret properly these results. If one wants to technically constrain an Observation resource for a particular use case across implementers, a profile is the preferred option and may include profiling on ObservationDefinition and Observation.
</p>
<p>
For instance, in a catalog of laboratory in vitro diagnostic services, the ObservationDefinition resources describe the observations that should be provided by the orderer alongside an ordered service (questions asked at order entry or at specimen collection, prior results) as well as the observations that will be reported once the service has been performed.
</p>
<p>
Observation Definition resources can be used to describe observations which may need to be evaluated in order to determine whether a specific medicine can be administered or held (e.g., weight, lab value result) and provide guidance on the dose to be administered (e.g., sliding scale insulin dose).
</p>
<p>
In the catalog of tests of an in vitro diagnostic device, ObservationDefinition resources can be used to characterize (absolute range, unit, decimal precision, critical values, etc.) the observations that will be produced by the IVD tests performed by the device.
</p>
<p>
ObservationDefinition may be used to characterize observations from any discipline.
</p>
</div>


<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
An ObservationDefinition resource provides the definitional characteristics for a certain kind of observation. Each time that kind of observation is collected and recorded it is instantiated as an Observation resource, which conforms to these definitional characteristics. Thus, there is a relationship between ObservationDefinition and Observation: The latter may instantiate the former.
</p>
<p>
When an Observation instantiates an ObservationDefinition, the elements of the Observation resource are expected to inherit their content from the corresponding definitional elements declared in the ObservationDefinition resource:</p>
 <ul>
<li>Category, code, datatype of the value, bodyStructure, method.</li>
<li>Each referenceRange element present in Observation should come from a qualifiedValue element of ObservationDefinition.</li>
<li>If ObservationDefinition has declared a ValueSet of valid coded values, and if Observation has a valueCodeableConcept, the value is expected to be part of that ValueSet.</li>
<li>The subject of the Observation should be conformant with one of the codeable concepts in subject listed in ObservationDefinition.</li>
<li>If the Observation has a device element, the referenced Device resource should conform to a DeviceDefinition or Device referenced by ObservationDefinition.device (if present).</li>
<li>If the Observation has a specimen element, the referenced Specimen resource should conform to a SpecimenDefinition referenced by ObservationDefinition.specimen (if present).</li>
</ul>
<p>
ObservationDefinition can specify units allowed for the valueQuantity element by setting ObservationDefinition.permittedUnit.
</p>
<p>
ObservationDefinitions are only to be used when describing the contents of an observation (including observations in order catalogs or panels). When additional structure, sequence, or rules are needed, the Questionnaire resource should be used.
</p>
</div>


<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
