<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<a name="use"></a>
<h3>Use Cases</h3>
<p>The Group resource is used in one of two ways:</p>
<ol>
  <li>To define a group of specific people, animals, devices, etc. that is being tracked, examined, acting collectively or otherwise referenced as part of healthcare-related activities</li>
  <li>To define a set of <i>possible</i> people, animals, devices, etc. that are of interest for some intended future healthcare-related activities</li>
</ol>

<p>Examples of the former could include a family, a household, or group therapy or treatment sessions, exposed entities tracked as part of public health, etc.  The latter might be used to define expected subjects for a clinical study.</p>

<p>Both use cases are handled by a single resource because the data elements captured tend to be similar.</p>
<p>NOTE: While <a href="specimen.html">Specimen</a> does not quite fit with this definition, it is being retained as part of
Group to avoid making a breaking change to the <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resource.</p>
<h3>Defining Group Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</h3>
<h4>Group.type</h4>
<p>In the conventional use of&nbsp;Group&nbsp;resource, the type specifies the type of FHIR resources that can be used to represent&nbsp;Group&nbsp;members.&nbsp;The&nbsp;Group.type&nbsp;element is required if the&nbsp;Group.membership&nbsp;element has a value of&nbsp;definitional&nbsp;or&nbsp;enumerated&nbsp;</p>
<p>In other words,&nbsp;type&nbsp;is letting you know the type of group (Person, Specimen,...).&nbsp; The choices in Group.type are limited to concepts represented in FHIR. If&nbsp;type&nbsp;is&nbsp;person,&nbsp;then the members would have to be resources of type&nbsp;person. If type is&nbsp;device&nbsp;you will expect a different set of resources.&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Group.membership</h4>
<p>Group.membership requires one of three codes:</p>
<ul>
    <li>'enumerated':&nbsp;Use this code if you desire to list the group members and/or specify the number of entities in the group.</li>
    <li>'definitional': Use this code if the&nbsp;Group.characteristics specified are both necessary and sufficient to determine qualifications for membership (for defining what makes something a member of the group). If a group is both&nbsp;enumerated&nbsp;and&nbsp;definitional, then use the&nbsp;enumerated&nbsp;code.</li>
    <li>'conceptual': Use this code if the Group is neither enumerated (listing or counting actual members) nor&nbsp;definitional&nbsp;(providing complete definition for membership qualifications). A different use of conceptual is when the 'conceptual' Group is a 'definitional' Group in which the Group.type is not bound to FHIR types.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Group.code</h4>
<p>Group.code is used to describe the&nbsp;kind&nbsp;of group members, especially when a more specific classification than the Group.type value is desired. For example, if Group.type is 'animal', then Group.code may be 'cow'. If Group.type is 'device',&nbsp;then Group.code could be 'syringe' or 'cytometer'.&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Group.quantity</h4>
<p>Group.quantity is a count of group members, so it must be an integer if used.</p>
<h4>Group.combinationMethod</h4>
<p>Group.combinationMethod is used when there are two or more Group.characteristic instances to define how the characteristics are combined.&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
    <li>Use a code&nbsp;all-of&nbsp;to indicate that each of the characteristics must be met. This is functionally equivalent to&nbsp; combining all characteristics with an AND operator.</li>
    <li>Use a code&nbsp;any-of&nbsp;to indicate that at least one of the characteristics must be met. This is functionally equivalent to combining all characteristics with an OR operator.</li>
    <li>Use a code&nbsp;at-least&nbsp;to indicate that at least&nbsp;n&nbsp;of the characteristics must be met. Use Group.combinationThreshold to specify the value of&nbsp;n.</li>
    <li>Use a code&nbsp;at-most&nbsp;to indicate that at most&nbsp;n&nbsp;of the characteristics must be met. Use Group.combinationThreshold to specify the value of&nbsp;n.</li>
    <li>Use a code&nbsp;except-subset&nbsp;to indicate that the characteristics expressed as exclusion criteria are used as exceptions to meeting the characteristics expressed as inclusion criteria. Explaining by example: “Cancer of any kind (except basal cell skin cancer or cancer in situ) unless documented to be disease-free for five years” (<a href="https://fevir.net/resources/Group/170441" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">https://fevir.net/resources/Group/170441</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<h4>Group.combinationThreshold</h4>
<p>Provides the value of "n" when "at-least" or "at-most" codes are used for Group.combinationMethod (see above)</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.code&nbsp;</h4>
<p>Each characteristic must have a code value (CodeableConcept datatype) to specify the attribute. For instance:&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
    <li>for a characteristic of "age &gt; 18 years” the attribute is “age” and the attribute of age may be expressed as&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<p>"code": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "coding": [<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://snomed.info/sct" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://snomed.info/sct</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "397669002",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "display": "Age"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ]<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }</p>
<ul>
    <li>for a characteristic of "Body mass index &gt;= 30 kg/m2" the attribute is "Body mass index" and the attribute may be expressed as.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "coding": [<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://loinc.org/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://loinc.org</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "39156-5",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "display": "Body mass index (BMI) [Ratio]"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ]<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }</p>
<p>(Examples taken from&nbsp;<a href="https://fevir.net/resources/Group/171819" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">https://fevir.net/resources/Group/171819</a>)</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.value[x]</h4>
<p>Each characteristic must have a value[x] value to specify the value of the attribute that holds for members of the group. There is no [x] in the JSON or XML expression as it is replaced with the data type (CodeableConcept, boolean, Quantity, Range, Reference, uri, or Expression)</p>
<p>For instance:&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
    <li>for a characteristic of "age &gt; 18 years” the value is “&gt; 18 years” and the value may be expressed with a Quantity datatype as&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>"valueQuantity": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "comparator": "&gt;=",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "value": 18,<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "unit": "years",</p>
<p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://unitsofmeasure.org/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://unitsofmeasure.org</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "a"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;}</p>
<p><br></p>
<ul>
    <li>for a characteristic of "Body mass index &gt;= 30 kg/m2" the value is "&gt;= 30 kg/m2" and the value may be expressed as</li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<p>"valueQuantity": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "comparator": "&gt;=",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "value": 30,<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "unit": "kg/m2",</p>
<p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://unitsofmeasure.org/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://unitsofmeasure.org</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "kg/m2"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;}</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>(Examples taken from&nbsp;<a href="https://fevir.net/resources/Group/171819" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">https://fevir.net/resources/Group/171819</a>)</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>→ Further examples for other types to be added.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.exclude</h4>
<p>Sometimes group membership is determined by characteristics not possessed. When this is the case, the Group.characteristic.exclude element has a value of true ("exclude": true). For characteristics that are not exclusion criteria, the Group.characteristic.exclude element has a value of false ("exclude": false). The exclude element is required.</p>
<p>For example, an exclusion criterion of HbA1c ≥ 14.0% is expressed as:</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>{<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "description": "HbA1c ≥ 14.0%",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "coding": [<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://loinc.org/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://loinc.org</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "59261-8",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "display": "Hemoglobin A1c/Hemoglobin.total in Blood"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ]<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; },<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "valueQuantity": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "value": 14,<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "comparator": "&gt;=",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "unit": "%",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://unitsofmeasure.org/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://unitsofmeasure.org</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "%"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; },<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "exclude": true<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; }</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>modified off:</p>
<p>StudyEligibilityCriteria: Eligibility Criteria for Bariatric Surgery Randomized Trial (Diabetes Surgery Study) [Database Entry: FHIR Group Resource]. Contributors: Brian S. Alper [Authors/Creators]. In: Fast Evidence Interoperability Resources (FEvIR) Platform, FOI 170443. Revised 2022-09-09. Available at:&nbsp;<a href="https://fevir.net/resources/Group/170443" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">https://fevir.net/resources/Group/170443</a>. Computable resource at:&nbsp;<a href="https://fevir.net/resources/Group/170443" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">https://fevir.net/resources/Group/170443</a>.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.description</h4>
<p>A short, natural language description of the characteristic (using the markdown datatype) that could be used to communicate the criteria to an end-user. &nbsp;The description element is for convenience so that end users can understand the characteristic and is neither a required part of the characteristic nor part of the structured representation of the characteristic.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.method</h4>
<p>The method modifies the Group.characteristic.code and indicates how the value is to be determined, using the CodeableConcept datatype. &nbsp;For example, HbA1C values can be determined by High-Performance Liquid Chromatography or by Capillary electrophoresis.</p>
<p>The method may be expressed as multiple concepts, eg. standing barefoot for Height measurements could be expressed as two separate concepts that express the one method.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.determinedBy[x]</h4>
<p>determinedBy[x] modifies the Group.characteristic.code and indicates how the value is to be determined, using either a Reference datatype or an Expression datatype. &nbsp;This provides a means of expressing or modifying the method not as a set of concepts but as either a reference to a device or as an Expression. &nbsp;The reference to a device can be either to a specific device using the Device resource or the DeviceMetric resource if a specific set of device parameters is needed, or a type of device using the DeviceDefinition resource.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.offset</h4>
<p>Defines the reference point for comparison when other than 0. &nbsp;As an example, to express a characteristic of a calcium level greater than the normal limit or a hemoglobin level less than 1gm/dL below the reference range, the offset concept would represent "normal limit" or "reference range".</p>
<p>This is a modifier element because it modifies the meaning of the characteristic.value[x].</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.instances[x]</h4>
<p>Number of occurrences meeting the characteristic.</p>
<p>There should be a constraint on the Quantity.value and Range.low.value and Range.high.value that it can only be non-negative whole numbers.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.duration[x]</h4>
<p>Length of time in which the characteristic is met.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.period</h4>
<p>The period over which the characteristic is tested; e.g. the patient had an operation during the month of June.</p>
<h4>Group.characteristic.timing</h4>
<p>The relative time in which the characteristic is tested, eg. within a month following patient discharge.</p>
<p>Note: RelativeTime is a recent addition to the Group Resource.&nbsp;RelativeTime is used to express a point in time or an interval of time relative to an event defined in data types other than dateTime.</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>Example:<a href="https://fevir.net/resources/Group/172484" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">https://fevir.net/resources/Group/172484</a></p>
<p>Example includes timing and offset "At 12months form inclusion in a clinical trial. Inclusion is defined as enrollment via the SNOMED code.</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>&nbsp;"timing": [<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "contextCode": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "coding": [<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://snomed.info/sct" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://snomed.info/sct</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "709491003",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "display": "Enrollment in clinical trial"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; ]<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; },<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "offsetDuration": {<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "value": 12,<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "unit": "months",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "system": "<a href="http://unitsofmeasure.org/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow">http://unitsofmeasure.org</a>",<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "code": "mo"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; },<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; "text": "at 12 months"<br>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; }</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
There are a number of mechanisms in FHIR for communicating collections of resources:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
The <a href="list.html">List</a> resource - enumerates a flat collection of resources and provides features for managing the collection.
While a particular List instance may represent a "snapshot", from a business process perspective the notion of "List" 
is dynamic – items are added and removed over time.  The List resource references other resources.  Lists may be 
curated and have specific business meaning. For use cases where Group is suitable (e.g. for a list of Patients to be
viewed on a dashboard), the Group resource should be preferred to the List resource. The underlying rationale is that a collection of
patients, practitioners, etc. is likely to be of interest as the subject of a measure, observation, communication, etc.,
which Group is intended to support.
</li>
<li>
This Group resource - defines a group of specific people, animals, devices etc. by enumerating them, 
or by describing qualities that group members have. The group resource refers to other resources, possibly implicitly.  
Groups are intended to be acted upon or observed as a whole; e.g. performing therapy on a group, calculating risk for a group, 
etc.  This resource will commonly be used for public health (e.g. describing an at-risk population), clinical trials (e.g. 
defining a test subject pool) and similar purposes.
</li>
<li><a href="careteam.html">CareTeam</a>. Group is distinct from CareTeam. Group is patient-independent and identifies an 
undifferentiated set of individuals who are intended to be the target of one or more clinical activities (e.g. set of 
clinical trial participants, set of individuals impacted by or at risk of a public health event, a herd or flock, etc.) 
The CareTeam resource establishes a set of relationships and roles and is specific to a particular Patient. 
The actors are the individual members or organized group of individuals. CareTeam can be referenced by EpisodeOfCare, 
Encounter, or CarePlan to identify the set of individuals (and their respective roles) who are intended to be involved 
in providing the care defined by those resources. Groups containing practitioners are not allowed to perform actions
for patient care.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="bundle.html">Bundle</a> resource - is an infrastructure container for a group of resources.  It does not have narrative 
and is used to group collections of resources for transmission, persistence or processing (e.g. messages, documents, transactions, 
query responses, etc.)  The content of bundles is typically algorithmically determined for a particular exchange or persistence purpose.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="composition.html">Composition</a> resource - defines a set of healthcare-related information that is assembled 
together into a single logical document that provides a single coherent statement of meaning, establishes its own context and 
that has clinical attestation with regard to who is making the statement. The composition resource provides the basic structure 
of a FHIR <a href="documents.html">document</a>.  The full content of the document is expressed using a bundle.  Compositions will 
often reference Lists as the focus of particular sections.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="domainresource.html">DomainResource</a>.<code>contained</code> element - allows multiple resources to be nested
inside any DomainResource.  This is a special type of grouping where the grouped resources lose independent existence - they
no longer have their own identifiers, can't easily be queried independently, etc.  Use of this grouping is a technical 
mechanism for managing the independence of resources and has no impact on meaning.  
</li>
</ul>

</div>

</div>
