<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
A DocumentReference resource is used to index a document, clinical note, and other binary objects such as a photo, video, or audio recording, including those resulting from diagnostic or care provision procedures, to make them available to a healthcare system. A document is some sequence of bytes that is identifiable, establishes its own context (e.g., what subject, author, etc. can be presented to the user), and has defined update management. The DocumentReference resource can be used with any document format that has a recognized mime type and that conforms to this definition.
</p>
<p>
Typically, DocumentReference resources are used in document indexing systems, such as <a href="https://profiles.ihe.net/ITI/TF/Volume1/ch-10.html">IHE XDS</a> and as profiled in <a href="https://profiles.ihe.net/ITI/MHD/">IHE Mobile Access to Health Documents</a>.
</p>
<p>
DocumentReference contains metadata, inline content or direct references to documents such as:</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> documents in FHIR systems</li>
 <li><a href="documents.html">FHIR documents</a> stored elsewhere (i.e. registry/repository following the XDS model)</li>
 <li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portable_Document_Format">PDF documents</a>, Scanned Paper, and digital records of faxes</li>
 <li>Clinical Notes in various forms</li>
 <li>Image files (e.g., JPEG, GIF, TIFF)</li>
 <li>Video files (e.g., MP4, WMV)</li>
 <li>Audio files (e.g., WAV, MP3)</li>
 <li>Non-Standard formats (e.g., CSV, RTF, WORD)</li>
 <li>Other kinds of documents, such as records of prescriptions or immunizations</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource captures data that might not be in FHIR format. The document can be any object (e.g. file), 
and is not limited to the formal HL7 definitions of <a href="documents.html">Document</a>. This resource may be a report with 
unstructured text or report that is not expressed in a DiagnosticReport. This resource may be an 
<a href="observation.html">Observation</a> whose value is audio, video or image data. This resource is the preferred 
representation of such forms of information as it exposes the metadata relevant for interpreting the 
information. 
</p>
<p>
This resource is able to contain medical images in a DICOM format. These images may also be made 
accessible through an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource, which provides a direct reference to the image to a 
<a href="ftp://medical.nema.org/medical/dicom/final/sup161_ft.pdf">WADO-RS</a> server. For such images, the WADO-RS framework is a preferred method for representing the 
images - the WADO-RS service may include rendering the image with annotations and display parameters 
from an associated DICOM presentation state, for instance. On the other hand, the DocumentReference 
resource allows for a robust transfer of an image across boundaries where the WADO-RS service is 
not available. For this reason, medical images can also be represented in a DocumentReference resource, 
but the DocumentReference.content.attachment.url should provide a reference to a source WADO-RS service for the image.
</p>
<p>
FHIR defines both a <a href="documents.html">document format</a> and this document reference. FHIR documents are for documents
that are authored and assembled in FHIR. DocumentReference is intended for general references to any type of media file <em>including</em> assembled documents.
</p>
<p>
The document that is a target of the reference can be a reference to a FHIR document served by another server, or
the target can be stored in the special <a href="http.html#binary">FHIR Binary Resource</a>, or the target can be
stored on some other server system. The document reference is also able to address documents that are retrieved
by a service call such as an XDS.b RetrieveDocumentSet, or a DICOM exchange, or an <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=185">HL7 v2</a> message query - though
the way each of these service calls works must be specified in some external standard or other documentation.
</p>
<p>
A <code>DocumentReference</code> describes some other document. This means that there are two sets of
provenance information relevant here: the provenance of the document, and the provenance of the document
reference. Sometimes, the provenance information is closely related, as when the document producer also
produces the document reference, but in other workflows, the document reference is generated later by
other actors. In the <code>DocumentReference</code> resource, the <a href="resource.html#Meta">meta</a>
content refers to the provenance of the reference itself, while the content described below concerns
the document it references. Like all resources, there is overlap between the information in the
resource directly, and in the general <a href="provenance.html">Provenance</a> resource. This is
discussed as <a href="provenance.html#overlap">part of the description of the Provenance resource</a>.
</p>
</div>

</div>
</div>
