<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Implementation Notes</h2>
<ul>
 <li>The use of the .docStatus codes is discussed in the <a href="composition.html#status">Composition description</a></li>
 <li>The resources maintain one way relationships that point backwards - e.g. the document that replaces one document points towards the document that it replaced. The reverse relationships can be followed by using 
  indexes built from the resources. Typically, this is done using the search parameters described below. Given that documents may have other documents that replace or append them, clients should always check these relationships when accessing documents</li>
  
</ul>

<h3>Document Formats</h3>
<p>
In addition to a mime type (which is mandatory), there is also a <i>format</i> element which carries
a URI. This element has one or more identifiers that indicate that the format and/or content of the 
document conforms to additional rules beyond the base format indicated in the mimeType. This is most 
often used when the mime-type is text/xml, to provide additional information for finding the correct
document.
</p>
<p>
Defined URIs:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="http://www.astm.org/Standards/E2369.htm">ASTM CCR</a>: urn:astm-org:CCR</li>
 <li>CCDA: urn:hl7-org:sdwg:ccda-level-1:1.1, urn:hl7-org:sdwg:ccda-level-2:1.1 and urn:hl7-org:sdwg:ccda-level-3:1.1</li>
 <li>IHE defines URIs <a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php?title=IHE_Format_Codes">here</a> and 
   OIDs <a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php?title=PCC_Vocabulary_Registry_and_Data_Dictionary">here</a> (prefix OIDs with urn:oid: in the resource).</li> 
</ul>
<p>
Other URIs can be used for items not on this list.
</p>


<h3>Generating a Document Reference</h3>
<p>
A client can ask a server to generate a document reference from a document.
The server reads the existing document and generates a matching DocumentReference
resource, or returns one it has previously generated. Servers may be able to 
return or generate document references for the following types of content:
</p>
<table class="grid">
  <tr> <td><b>Type</b></td> <td><b>Comments</b></td> </tr>
  <tr> <td><a href="documents.html">FHIR Documents</a></td> <td>The uri refers to an existing Document</td> </tr>
  <tr> <td>CDA Document</td> <td>The uri is a reference to a <a href="compartments.html#Binary">Binary</a> end-point that returns either a CDA 
    document, or some kind of CDA Package that the server knows how to process (e.g. an IHE .zip) </td> </tr>
  <tr> <td>Other</td> <td>The server can be asked to generate a document reference for other kinds of 
    documents. For some of these documents (e.g. PDF documents) a server could only provide a 
    DocumentReference it is already existed, or the server had special knowledge of the document</td> </tr>
</table>
<p>
The server either returns a search result containing a single DocumentReference, 
or it returns an error. 
If some the URI refers to another server, it is at the discretion of the 
server whether to retrieve it or return an error. 
</p>
<p>
The operation is initiated by a named query, using _query=generate on the /DocumentReference
end point:
</p>
<pre>
  GET [service-url]/DocumentReference/?_query=generate&amp;uri=:url&amp;...
</pre>
<p>
The "uri" parameter is a relative or absolute reference to one of the 
document types described above. Other parameters may be supplied:
</p>
<table class="grid">
  <tr> <td><b>Name</b></td> <td><b>Meaning</b></td> </tr>
  <tr> <td>persist</td> <td>Whether to store the document at the document end-point (/Document) or not once it is generated. Value = true or false (default is for the server to decide)</td> </tr>
</table>

</div>
