<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p> 
A document reference resource is used to describe a document that is made available to a healthcare system. 
A document is some sequence of bytes that is identifiable, establishes its own context (e.g. what subject, 
author etc), can be displayed to the user, and has defined update management. The document resource can be 
used with any document format that has a recognized mime type, and that conforms to this definition.
</p>
<p>
Typically, Document Reference Resources are used in document indexing systems, such as IHE XDS (see the <a href="xds-profile.html">XDS specific profile</a>),
and are used to refer to:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA documents</a> in FHIR systems</li>
 <li><a href="documents.html">FHIR documents</a> stored elsewhere (i.e. registry/repository following the XDS model)</li>
 <li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portable_Document_Format">PDF documents</a>, and even digital records of faxes where sufficient information is available</li>
 <li>Other kinds of documents, such as records of prescriptions.</li> 
</ul>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
FHIR defines both a <a href="documents.html">document format</a> and this document reference. FHIR documents are for documents 
that are authored and assembled in FHIR. This resource is mainly intended for general references to other documents. 
</p>
<p/>
<p>
The document that is a target of the reference can be a reference to a FHIR document served by another server, or 
the target can be stored in the special <a href="http.html#binary">FHIR Binary Resource</a>, or the target can be 
stored on some other server system. The document reference is also able to address documents that are retrieved 
by a service call such as an XDS.b RetrieveDocumentSet, or a DICOM exchange, or a v2 message query, though 
the way each of these service calls works must be specified in some external stanard or other documentation.
</p>
</div>

</div>
