<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<!-- still to do:

practiceSettingCode - what is this?
referenceIdList - what type is this?
-->

<p>
The XDS profile describes in detail how the <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> and <a href="documentmanifest.html">DocumentManifest</a> resources 
are used in the context of XDS. The two resources may be used as a facade to an existing
XDS server, such as is used for the <a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php?title=Mobile_access_to_Health_Documents_(MHD)">IHE MHD</a> specification,
or it can be used the other way around, where the XDS functionality is implemented using a FHIR based server as the storage mechanism.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
The FHIR DocumentReference and DocumentManifest is based on the functionality defined by XDS, but they differ from XDS in 
some significant ways:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>SubmissionSet = DocumentManifest, and DocumentEntry = DocumentReference. These renamings are appropriate in the wider context of how these resources are used in FHIR.</li>
 <li>There is no direct association between a transaction and a DocumentManifest in FHIR, however a <a href="http.html#transaction">transaction</a> may be used to ensure consistent commits</li>
 <li>Patient, Author and Authenticator are represented using standard <a href="patient.html">Patient</a> and <a href="practitioner.html">Practitioner</a> resources.</li>
 <li>The functionality expressed through the XDSFolder resource is implemented using the <a href="list.html">List</a> resource, or by <a href="resource.html#tags">tags</a></li>
 <li>Some XDS specific fields that are not generally applicable do not have matching elements in the DocumentReference resource, and are implemented as FHIR extensions</li>
</ul>

<h3>Mapping Notes</h3>
<p>
The formal mappings are found below, but this section provides some additional description to help understand 
the relationships between the XDS tranasction and the FHIR resources.
</p>

<table class="grid">
 <tr>
  <td>Patient</td>
  <td>The following attributes of patient are all found in the <a href="patient.html">Patient</a> resource:
   <ul>
    <li><b>patientId</b>: Patient.identifier. The patientId has a use of "official"</li>
    <li><b>sourcePatientId</b>: Patient.identifier. The sourcePatientId  has a use of "usual"</li>
    <li><b>PatientInfo</b>: Various properties as appropriate in the Patient resource</li>
   </ul>  
  </td>
 </tr>

 <tr>
  <td>Author</td>
  <td>The following attributes of author are all found in the <a href="practitioner.html">Practitioner</a> resource:
   <ul>
    <li><b>authorInstitution</b>: Practitioner.organization (and possibly Organization.identifier and Organization.name in a target Organization resource)</li>
    <li><b>authorPerson</b>: Practitioner.identifier and Practitioner.name</li>
    <li><b>authorRole</b>: Practitioner.role</li>
    <li><b>authorSpecialty</b>: Practitioner.specialty</li>
    <li><b>authorTelecommunication</b>: Practitioner.telecom</li>
   </ul>  
  </td>
 </tr>

 <tr>
  <td>LegalAuthenticator</td>
  <td>In XDS, policy is that there is a "legal authenticator", and this is represented in the DocumentReference.authenticator element (it has a more general meaning so it's not so restrictive outside the XDS use case)</td>
 </tr>

 
 <tr>
  <td>Identifiers</td>
  <td>The different identifiers go in different places, depending on the nature of the identifier:
   <ul>
    <li><b>entryUUID</b>: <a href="resources.html#metadata">Logical Id</a> of the DocumentReference/DocumentManifest resource</li>
    <li><b>uniqueId</b>: DocumentReference.masterIdentier - the identifier of the document itself</li>
    <li><b>homeCommunityId &amp; repositoryUniqueId</b>: These data items are not needed in a FHIR context because the document reference is directly available. If it's still needed for XDS service calls, use a service parameter by the name same name. Where the homeCommunityId is needed in a manifest, an <a href="extensibility.html">extension</a> is defined (http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/xdshomeCommunityId, which contains a <a href="datatypes.html#uri">uri</a>)</li>
   </ul>  
  </td>
 </tr>
 
 <tr>
  <td>Availability Status</td>
  <td>
    <p>Approved (available for patient care): DocumentReference/Manifest.status = current</p>
    <p>Deprecated (obsolete): DocumentReference/Manifest.status = superceded</p>
  </td>
 </tr>

 <tr>
  <td>Comments</td>
  <td>The information that currently is found in the comments slot is placed in the equivalent resource narrative (for human consumption).</td>
 </tr>

 <tr>
  <td>Folders</td>
  <td>There is no direct equivalent between to XDS folders in FHIR. Workflow associated with a document reference may be managed using <a href="resource.html#tags">Tags</a>, or documents can be explicitly grouped using the <a href="list.html">List resource</a></td>
 </tr>


</table>

<h3>Handling Updates</h3>
<p>
The <a href="http.html">RESTful API</a> allows updates to the DocumentReference/DocumentManifest resources that the document repository is built on.
</p>
<p>
In the context of XDS, servers SHALL ensure that the masterIdentifier element of a DocumentReference is never changed after
the resource is created. When a new document is created, a new DocumentReference SHALL be created. The server SHOULD ensure
that the supercedes element is correctly populated, along with the status of any existing documents that are being
superceded. It MAY choose to do this by requiring the clients to perform this operation, or simply performing the 
operation itself.
</p>
<p>
When used with XDS, updates to the document reference resource are only performed to correct the details associated 
with the document description - other identifiers, context, location etc. The document itself, the hash value, etc, 
SHOULD never change. Servers MAY choose to maintain the repository of resources so that there is only one DocumentReference for 
each original document (unique masterIdentifiers), but doing so will require some way of resolving conflicting 
claims around the document metadata from different submitters.
</p>
<p>
In order to implement the XDS profile, a server SHALL keep a full version history of DocumentReference, 
DocumentManifest, Patient, and Practitioner resources. This allows for Audit investigations, and also
replication using stnadard pub/sub arrangements.
</p>
</div>

</div>
