<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource applies to any circumstance where there is a concern about an existing or proposed set of clinical activity.  The issue could relate to multiple actions/proposed actions or could be specific to a single action.  It does not apply to administrative issues (e.g. lack of user permissions) but could relate to violation of patient consent limitations.  Examples include:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Drug-drug interactions</li>
  <li>In appropriate therapy (wrong dose, frequency, body site)</li>
  <li>Duplicate therapy</li>
</ul>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
<p>
This resource is <b>not</b> intended to be used in defining general prohibitions on actions such as "No NSAIDs", "No solid oral dose forms" or "No MRIs - metalic tatoos".  These guidelines can be captured using the <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a>, <a href="adversereaction.html">AdverseReaction</a> and/or <a href="alert.html">Alert</a> resources.  Similarly this resource is not to be used to capture clinical facts that may imply contraindications such as pregnancy, breast feeding, patient preferences, past procedures, etc.  These would be represented using <a href="condition.html">Condition</a>, <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> or other resources.
</p>
</div>


<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resources only applies to documenting a risk associated with a specific planned or ongoing action, not a general propensity to risk.  The latter would be handled using <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a> for substance-specific issues or <a href="alert.html">Alert</a> for other types of issues.
</p>
<p>This resource is limited to clinical issues associated with a proposed or ongoing action.  It does not cover business/technical issues such as lack of permission, duplicate identifiers and other business rule violations.  Business and technical issues are conveyed using the <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> resource.  It is possible to have both <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> and <b>Contraindication together</b>, where the first might indicate that a requested action was rejected due to a clinical issue and the latter provides the details of the issue.</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Contraindications are typically identified by decision support systems.  However, they may also be captured directly by clinicians.  The latter typically happens for one of two reasons:
</p>
<ol>
  <li>A clinician wishes to communicate an issue to another clinician whose responsibility it would be to resolve it (e.g. a pharmacist identifying an issue with a prescription prior to putting it on hold)</li>
  <li>A clinician wishes to pre-emptively identify that an issue is known and being managed (to avoid red flags being raised as part of downstream workflow).  E.g. Noting that a duplicate therapy is actually intended.</li>
</ol>
<p>
Decision-support generated contraindications can result from calling a decision-support engine directly (e.g. via a custom <a href="operationdefinition.html">OperationDefinition</a>) or as part of an attempt to perform some other function (creating an order, submitting an insurance claim, capturing a medication list).  When the contraindications are generated as a byproduct of performing some other sort of action, they may be included in the "response" to the requested action in the same manner as an <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a>.  In fact, both may be present - the <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> indicating that there was a warning or error associated with the request and a <b>Contraindication</b> providing the clinical details.  (The <a href="operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> could point to the <b>Contraindication</b> via an extension.)
</p>
<p>
In those circumstances where requested operations are rejected as a result of a contraindication, the workflow may support allowing the operation to be re-tried provided the identified contraindication is included as part of the submission (possibly also including a mitigation).  In doing so, the sender acknowledges the contraindication and takes responsibility for it, thus allowing the requested operation to proceed.  See <a href="#linking">Linking to Contraindications</a> for guidance on how a <b>Contraindication</b> instance might be included as part of another operation.
</p>
<p>
Systems that require such workflows should document expected behavior as part of their <a href="conformance.html">Conformance</a> declarations.
</p>

</div>

</div>
