<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
	<a name="scope_and_usage"> </a>
	<h3>Scope and Usage</h3>
<p>
This profile sets expectations for use of the <a href="list.html">List</a> resource within the 
<a href="daf.html">Data Access Framework (DAF)</a> Implementation Guide. This profile identifies which core data elements, extensions, vocabularies and value sets must be <i>Supported</i> by DAF actors.
For the definition of <i>Supported</i> please refer to <a href="daf.html">DAF FHIR IG</a>. The data elements identified by the profile are based on ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC and DAF use cases. 
The mappings between the ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC data elements and DAF data elements are captured in the table below, where the first column identifies the ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC data element name, 
the second column maps the ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC data elements to DAF data elements which are derived from ONC 2014 Edition S&amp;CC standards and DAF use cases and lastly the third column identifies the mapping to FHIR resources and attributes.
</p>
</div>

<div>
	<a name="MU_data_element_mapping"> </a>
	<h3>Meaningful Use Data Element Mapping</h3>
<p>
The DAF List profile mapping to Meaningful Use data elements and FHIR Resources are as shown below.
</p>
<br/>
	<table class="grid">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Meaningful Use Data Element Name</th>
			<th>Mapping to Priority DAF Data Elements</th>
            <th>FHIR Resource Mapping</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
			<td>Problem List</td>
			<td>Active Problem List</td>
			<td>List using DAFProblemList profile</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>Problems</td>
			<td>No known Problems</td>
			<td>List (Empty DAFProblemList with coded List.emptyReason)</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td>Medication allergies</td>
			<td>List of documented allergies</td>
			<td>List using DAFAllergyIntoleranceList profile</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td>Medication Allergies</td>
			<td>No known Allergies</td>
			<td>List (Empty DAFAllergyIntoleranceList with coded List.emptyReason)</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td>Medications List*</td>
			<td>List of active Medications*</td>
			<td>List using DAFMedicationList profile</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>Medications</td>
			<td>No known Medications</td>
			<td>List (Empty DAFMedicationList with coded List.emptyReason)</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td>Immunization List</td>
			<td>List of Immunizations</td>
			<td>List using DAFImmunizationList profile</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>Immunizations</td>
			<td>No known Immunizations</td>
			<td>List (Empty DAFImmunizationList with coded List.emptyReason)</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
			<td>Laboratory Result Values</td>
			<td>List of lab results</td>
			<td>List using DAFResultsList profile</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>Laboratory Result Values</td>
			<td>No known Laboratory Results</td>
			<td>List (Empty DAFResultsList with coded List.emptyReason)</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>Encounter Diagnoses</td>
			<td>List of encounters for a patient</td>
			<td>List using DAFEncounterList profile</td>
		  </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p><b>*</b>: The DAFMedicationList summarizes information from other DAF medication profiles. This profile supports three types of medication lists:</p>
	<ul>
	<li>Admission Medications - Contains the medications taken by the patient prior to and at the time of admission to the facility (LOINC: 42346-7). This list will contain instances of DAFMedicationStatement and DAFMedicationPrescription.</li>

	<li>Medications - The DAFMedicationsList contains a patient's current medications and pertinent medication history (LOINC: 10160-0).  At a minimum, the currently active medications are listed. An entire medication history is an option. Typically a DAF Responder system is expected to maintain only one current medication list per patient outside of an individual episode or encounter. This list will contain instances of DAFMedicationStatement, DAFMedicationPrescription, and may include instances of  DAFMedicationDispense and DAFMedicationAdministration.</li>

	<li>Discharge Medications - Contains the medications the patient is intended to take after discharge (LOINC: 75311-1). Current, active medications must be listed. This list will contain instances of DAFMedicationPrescription.</li>

	</ul>
</div>


<div>
	<a name="boundaries_and_relationships"> </a>
	<h3>Boundaries and Relationships</h3>
	
<p>
This profile relies on the following other profiles:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="extensibility.html">FHIR Extensibility</a> defines how extensions can be applied to FHIR resources and data types. 
  Specifically the <a href="extension-data-absent-reason.html">data-absent-reason</a> extension can be used to code data elements with missing information when appropriate.
  See <a href="daf.html">DAF FHIR IG</a> for additional guidance.</li>
</ul>
</div>


</div>





