<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The List resource is a flat, possibly ordered, collection of records. List resources are used in many places, 
including allergies, medications, alerts, family history, medical history, etc. List resources can be used to 
support patient-specific clinical lists as well as lists that manage workflows such as tracking patients, managing 
teaching cases, etc. Resources supported by the List resource can be homogenous – consisting of only one type of 
resource (e.g. allergy list) as well as heterogeneous – containing a variety of resources (e.g. a problem list 
including <a href="condition.html">Conditions</a>, <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerances</a>, 
recent <a href="procedure.html">Procedures</a>, etc.).
</p>
<p>
Lists will typically include references to the resources that make up the list, however in some cases the details 
of the content of the List might be expressed in narrative only.  E.g. A text record of a family history.  The List 
resource is only needed if there is a need to filter the set of resources by a mechanism that cannot be accomplished 
via a simple query.  I.e. There is no need to have a List for all <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerances</a>
that exist on a server for a given Patient.  However, List is an appropriate mechanism to provide a filtered list of the 
subset of AllergyIntolerances that are deemed to be "current". Lists are allowed to contain other lists, so 
that there is a nested collection of lists.
</p>
<p>
Note that the presence of an item in a List resource SHALL NOT change the meaning of any information that would be 
understood by looking at the item outside the context of the List, because items may be accessed directly outside 
the list by RESTful means, or after a document is processed. For example, a List with a code that means 
"refuted conditions" can not have items that are Condition resources that do not have a 
<a href="condition.html">Condition.clinicalStatus</a> of <a href="condition-status.html#refuted">refuted</a>.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
There are five mechanisms in FHIR for communicating collections of resources:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
This List resource - enumerates a flat collection of resources and provides features for managing the collection.  
While a particular List instance may represent a "snapshot", from a business process perspective the notion of "List" 
is dynamic – items are added and removed over time.  The list resource references other resources.  Lists may be 
curated and have specific business meaning.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="group.html">Group</a> resource - defines a group of specific people, animals, devices, etc. by enumerating them, 
or by describing qualities that group members have. The group resource refers to other resources, possibly implicitly.  
Groups are intended to be acted upon or observed as a whole.  E.g. performing therapy on a group, calculating risk for a group, 
etc.  This resource will commonly be used for public health (e.g. describing an at-risk population), clinical trials (e.g. 
defining a test subject pool) and similar purposes.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="composition.html">Composition</a> resource – defines a set of healthcare-related information that is assembled 
together into a single logical document that provides a single coherent statement of meaning, establishes its own context and 
that has clinical attestation with regard to who is making the statement. The composition resource provides the basic structure 
of a FHIR <a href="documents.html">document</a>.  The full content of the document is expressed using a bundle.  Compositions will 
often reference Lists as the focus of particular sections.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="bundle.html">Bundle</a> resource is an infrastructure container for a group of resources.  It does not have narrative 
and is used to group collections of resources for transmission, persistence or processing (e.g. messages, documents, transactions, 
query responses, etc.)  The content of bundles is typically algorithmically determined for a particular exchange or persistence purpose.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="domainresource.html">DomainResource</a>.<code>contained</code> element allows multiple resources to be nested
inside any DomainResource.  This is a special type of grouping where the grouped resources lose independent existence - they
no longer have their own identifiers, can't easily be queried independently, etc.  Use of this grouping is a technical 
mechanism for managing the independence of resources and has no impact on meaning.  Contained, bundles and remotely referenced
resources convey the same meaning.
</li>
</ul>

</div>


</div>
