<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="status"> </a>
<h2>List Mode &amp; Item Deleted</h2>

<p>
There are several different kinds of uses for a List resource:
</p>
<%codelist ListMode%>

<p>
The final mode - a changes list, may include deleted items. A typical case is a medication
list in a discharge summary, where the list includes items that have been both added and deleted.
In order to ensure that the list is safe to process, any item where the flag implies that the 
item has actually been deleted SHALL have the deleted element set to true. 
</p>
<p>
Note that there is no implication about the status of a resource that has been deleted.
The only statement that is made is that the resource has been dropped from the list. 
However applications should ensure that the implication of adding or deleting items
from the list is consistent with the logical status of the resource and its contents.
</p>
<p>
A proper use of List.mode = "changes" with a deleted resource is in a medications list 
for a discharge summary. See Example "med-list". An improper use would be if the list 
was a working list of patient medications in a clinical tracking system, and list item
flags were used to implement version tracking history within the resource.
</p>

<a name="narrative"> </a>
<h2>Narrative Content</h2>

<p>
The narrative portion of the List resource should contain a summary 
of the items in the list, their key information, along with a human-readable 
summary of their flags (if present). The narrative may be generated
from the data content and/or narrative of the resources referred to in
the list, or it may be a narrative written by a human which is partially or
completely matched by structured data in the linked resources, or human
written narrative may be the only content if the list has no entries
(which would equate to a narrative only section in a document).
</p>
<p>
An HTML table is the recommended approach, though this is not required.
Each List.item should appear in the narrative for the resource.  I.e. It 
SHALL not be necessary to retrieve the list items in order to have a 
human-readable rendering of the content. In addition, if the List.text.status is 
"generated", then the narrative should not suggest the list 
contains items for which there are no corresponding List.item elements. 
If the list has flags, the representation should make clear use of visual 
hints (borders, lines, bullet marks, etc.) to ensure that human readers 
do not get confused about which flags belong with which item on space-poor 
displays (e.g. to prevent wrapping from separating the flags from the items).
</p>

<p>
Note that when a List resource is used in a <a href="documents.html">Document</a>,
the narrative of the list is part of the attested content of the document.
</p>

<p>
In a dynamic environment, the narrative content of the list will be limited to the
version of the linked resources at the time the list was last updated. It may be
even earlier if the narrative isn't updated to reflect the most recent version
of all referenced resources at each update.  Best practice for 'working' lists is to update 
the narrative to reflect the most recent content of all list elements each time the list
is revised.  Lists should therefore not be
relied on as a real-time view of the referenced content.  There are a few
possible approaches to work around this issue:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Provide minimal information about the listed resources, possibly limited to only a link.  
 (Not recommended as this severely limits the usefulness of the narrative and is particularly
 problematic for things like documents where the only attested content might be the List
 narrative)</li>
 <li>Include only "generated" narrative, so the retriever can easily generate their own "current"
 view of the list by retrieving the referenced resources, ignoring the fixed narrative.</li>
 <li>The server hosting the list can subscribe to all referenced resources and auto-update the
 narrative each time one of the referenced resources changes (or at least on a semi-frequent basis)</li>
</ul>

<a name="emptyReason"> </a>
<h2>Empty Reason</h2>

<p>
If the list is empty, there could be several different reasons why this is so. For example:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>There are no appropriate entries for the list (i.e. the patient has no known medications/allergies/history)</li>
 <li>The sender (human or system) deemed that these were not related to this context of patient care (usually for privacy related reasons)</li>
 <li>The source system doesn't support these type of entries</li>
 <li>The information to populate the list wasn't gathered - i.e. "Not asked"</li>
</ul>
<p>
Given these possibilities, and the common and significant first case, source systems SHOULD 
provide an empty reason if the list is empty. Because of the importance of this case, the 
<a href="special-values.html">special value "nil-known"</a> should be used when 
there are no (significant) entries in this context of care. Note that this concept is 
sometimes described differently, such as "patient denies taking medications", or 
"patient was unable to identify any relevant medical history".
</p>
<p>
When receiving a list, systems should not assume that the list is complete (some entries may 
have been withheld for a variety of reasons), unless there are specific trading partner
arrangements in place or, if the list is empty, that there are actually nil known, 
unless the "nil-known" code is present.
</p>
<p>
If the list is empty, the narrative should contain text equivalent to the empty reason.
</p>

</div>
