<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This specification defines a series of different types of resource that can be used to exchange and/or store data 
in order to solve a wide range of healthcare related problems, both clinical and administrative. In addition,
this specification defines several different ways of exchanging the resources. All the resources defined in this 
specification and elsewhere are specializations of this Resource type.
</p>
<p>
A resource is an entity that:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>has a known identity by which it can be addressed</li>
 <li>identifies itself as one of the types of resource defined in this specification or as described below</li>
 <li>contains a set of structured data items as described by the definition of the resource type</li>
 <li>has an identified version that changes if the contents of the resource change</li>
</ul>
<p>
Resources have <a href="resource-formats.html">multiple representations</a>. 
</p>

</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

<p>
The following optional elements and properties are defined for all resources:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>An identity</li>
 <li>Meta data</li>
 <li>A base language</li>
 <li>A reference to "Implicit Rules"</li>
</ul>
<p>
Resource is the ancestor of <a href="domainresource.html">DomainResource</a> from which most recources are derived. <a href="bundle.html">Bundle</a>, <a href="parameters.html">Parameters</a>, and <a href="binary.html">Binary</a> extend Resource directly.
</p>
<p>
Note: there is documentation for the <a href="formats.html">Structure</a>, <a href="formats.html#uml">UML</a>, <a href="xml.html">XML</a>, and <a href="json.html">JSON</a> representations of the resource structure. 
</p>

<a name="additional"></a>
<h3>Additional Resources defined Outside This Specification</h3>
<p>
This specification defines the base <%res-type-count%> resources that comprise 
the "FHIR resources". Additional resources may be defined in other specifications,
and used as part of the FHIR framework. For those implementers who wish to use 
other resources, or find that they need to, the following rules apply:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Additional Resources to be used like this SHALL be registered with HL7</li>
 <li>Unapproved resources SHALL NOT be used</li>
 <li>Registered and approved resources are given a name by HL7, and this is the name that must be used for the resource</li>
 <li>All such registered and approved resources SHALL have a publicly available definition using a <a href="structuredefinition.html">StructureDefinition</a>
   published as part of an <a href="implementationguide.html">ImplementationGuide</a>, published at the canonical URL. Note that the definitions will be reviewed for quality by HL7 prior to approval</li>
</ul>
<p>
HL7 publishes the list of approved resource at <b>(somewhere?)</b> (todo: this needs further work, but at 
this time the functional list is published here: <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FHIR/ig-registry/refs/heads/master/additional-resources.json">IG Registry</a>).
If you wish to register such a resource, the process starts by making a proposal <a href="https://chat.fhir.org/#narrow/channel/491058-Additional-Resource-Proposals">here</a>.
</p>
<p>
These sections contain information about how additional resources work in the various places that they may be 
encountered through this specification:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="json.html#additional">JSON representation</a></li>
 <li><a href="xml.html#additional">XML representation</a></li>
 <li><a href="structuredefinition.html#additional">Defining Additional Resources</a></li>
 <li><a href="bundle.html#additional">Bundle.entry</a></li>
 <li><a href="capabilitystatement.html#additional">CapabilityStatement.rest.resource</a></li>
 <li><a href="domainresource.html#additional">DomainResource.contained</a></li>
 <li><a href="parameters.html#additional">Parameters.parameter.resource</a></li>
</ul>

<a name="moving"></a>
<h3>Moving Additional Resources to FHIR Core</h3>

<p>
Additional resources are all expected to eventually migrate to this specification once they are stable.
</p>
<p>
Generally, the process for moving an Additional Resource to core is:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>The responsible WG/WGs need to request moving into core.</li>
 <li>FMG needs to approve moving into core (criteria TBD by FMG).</li>
 <li>The resource will be added to the next ballot of FHIR core.</li>
 <li>The resource will be officially available when the milestone release that includes it is published.</li>
 <li>Concurrently with that FHIR Core publication, the status of the 'additional' definition should be updated so that it is deprecated and then eventually removed</li>
</ul>

<blockquote class="ballot-note">
<p><b>Note to Balloters:</b>
Additional resources are a new and major feature introduced as part of FHIR R6.
The primary driver is to support distributed development of new resources on 
faster life cycles than the main specification, which we expect to slow considerably 
once R6 is published
</p><p>
We expect considerable debate about this idea and how it's implemented, and
we welcome comment in the ballot, or directly on <a href="http://chat.fhir.org">chat.fhir.org</a>
</p></blockquote>

</div>


</div>
