<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This specification defines a series of different types of resource that can be used to exchange and/or store data 
in order to solve a wide range of healthcare related problems, both clinical and administrative. In addition,
this specification defines several different ways of exchanging the resources.
</p>
<p>
A resource is an entity that:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>has a known identity (a url) by which it can be addressed</li>
 <li>identifies itself as one of the types of resource defined in this specification</li>
 <li>contains a set of structured data items as described by the definition of the resource type</li>
 <li>contains a human-readable XHTML representation of the content of the resource</li>
 <li>has an identified version that changes if the contents of the resource change</li>
</ul>
<p>
Resources have multiple representations. A resource is valid if it meets the above rules, and is represented in 
either <a href="xml.html">XML</a> or <a href="json.html">JSON</a> according to the rules defined in this specification. 
Other representations are allowed, but are not described by this specification.
</p>
<!--
<p>
Basic definitions:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr> <td>Resource</td> <td>An instance of data that is stored or exchanged</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>Resource Definition</td> <td>Defines the data elements that are part of the resource</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>Profile</td> <td>Additional rules about the data elements for a particular context of use. There's a specific type of resource - the <a href="profile.html">Profile Resource</a> that is used to represent a profile</td> </tr>
</table>
-->

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

<p>
All resources have the following optional or mandatory elements and properties:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>An identity</li>
 <li>Meta data</li>
 <li>A base language</li>
 <li>A reference to "Implicit Rules"</li>
</ul>
<p>
Most resources are derived from <a href="domainresource.html">Domain Resources</a> - they also contain text, contained resources, and extensions,
and data elements specific to the particular domain of the resource. There is a special type of resource called <a href="bundle.html">Bundle</a> for groups/lists of resources. 
</p>
<p>
Note: there is documentation for the <a href="formats.html">Struture</a>, <a href="formats.html#uml">UML</a>, <a href="xml.html">XML</a>, and <a href="json.html">JSON</a> representations. 
</p>

</div>


</div>
