<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="id"> </a>
<h3>Resource Identity</h3>

<p>
Each resource has an "id" element which contains the logical identity of the resource 
assigned by the server responsible for storing it. Resources always have a known identity
except for the special case when a new resources is being sent to a server to assign
an identity (<a href="http.html#create">create interaction</a>). 
The logical identity is unique within the space of all resources of the same type on 
the same server. Once assigned, the identity is never changed, though copies of the 
same resource made elsewhere may not retain the same identity.
</p>

<p>
The full identity of a resource is an absolute URL constructed from the server base address at 
which it is found, the resource type, and the Logical Id, such as http://test.fhir.org/rest/Patient/123 
(where 123 is the Logical Id). Note that implementations SHOULD NOT assume that the identity of a resource 
is always resolvable to a literal server - it may be temporarily unavailable, or not available by policy (e.g. firewalls) or in some 
cases, it may not actually exist (e.g. use of resource outside a RESTful environment). Resources reference each other by their identity. 
These references are allowed to be absolute or relative (see <a href="references.html">Resource References</a> for further discussion).
Copying or moving resources from one server to another means that resources acquire a new identity. For further details, 
see <a href="managing.html">Managing Resource Identity</a>.
</p>

<p>
Logical ids are case sensitive. Ids are always opaque, and external systems need not and should not 
attempt to determine their internal structure. An id SHALL always be represented in the same way in 
resource references and URLs. Ids can be up to 64 characters long, and contain any combination of 
upper and lowercase ASCII letters, numerals, "-" and ".". 
</p>

<a name="metadata"> </a>
<a name="meta"> </a>
<a name="Meta"></a>

<h3 style="margin-bottom: 1px">
Resource Metadata
</h3>

<p>
Each resource contains an element "meta", of type "Meta", which is a set of 
metadata that provides technical and workflow context to the resource. The 
metadata items are all optional, though some of all of them may be required 
in particular implementations or contexts of use.
</p>

<table class="grid">
  <tr>
    <th>Metadata Item</th>
    <th>Type</th>
    <th>Usage</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>versionId (0..1)</td>
    <td><a href="datatypes.html#id">id</a></td>
    <td>Changes each time the content of the resource changes. Can be referenced in a <a href="references.html#Resource">resource reference</a>. 
      Can be used to ensure that updates are based on the latest version of the resource. 
    <br/>The version can be globally unique, or scoped by the Logical Id of the resource. 
     Version identifiers are generally either a serially incrementing id scoped by the logical id, or a uuid, though neither of these approaches 
     is required. Note that servers SHOULD support versions, but some are unable to</td>
  </tr>
	 
  <tr>
   <td>lastUpdated (0..1)</td>
   <td><a href="datatypes.html#instant">instant</a></td>
   <td>If populated, this value changes each time the content of the resource 
    changes. it can be used by a system or a human to judge the currency of the resource content. 
    Note that <a href="http.html#update">version aware updates</a> do not use this element</td>
  </tr>
	
  <tr>
   <td>profile (0..*)</td>
   <td><a href="datatypes.html#uri">uri</a></td>
   <td>An assertion that the content conforms to a profile. See <a href="profiling.html#resources">Extending and Restricting Resources</a> for further discussion. 
    Can be changed as profiles and value sets change or the system rechecks conformance</td>
  </tr>
	
  <tr>
   <td>security (0..*)</td>
   <td><a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a></td>
   <td><a href="security-labels.html">Security labels</a> applied to this resource. These tags connect resources in specific ways to 
    the overall security policy and infrastructure. Security tags can be updated when the resource changes, or whenever the security sub-system chooses to</td>
  </tr>
	
  <tr>
   <td>tag (0..*)</td>
   <td><a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a></td>
   <td><a href="extras.html">Tags</a> applied to this resource. Tags are used to relate resources to process and workflow. Applications are not required to consider 
    the tags when interpreting the meaning of a resource.</td>
  </tr>
		
</table>
  
[%dt Meta%]

<p>
Meta is used in the following places: [%dtusage Meta%]
</p>
  
<a name="implicitRules"> </a>
  
<h3>Implicit Rules</h3>
<p>
A reference to a <a href="profiling.html#agreement">custom agreement</a> about how the resources are used 
that was followed when the resource was constructed, and which must be understood when processing the content.
</p>
<p>
Asserting this rule set restricts the content to be only understood by a limited set of 
trading partners. This inherently limits the usefulness of the data in the long term,
and should be avoided where possible. However the existing health 
eco-system is highly fractured, and not yet ready to define, collect, and exchange 
data in a generally exchangeable sense. 
</p>
<p>
Note that resources are almost always constructed following some custom agreement.
Best practice is that such agreements make all knowledge about the content 
of the resource explicit; if custom agreements do this, and declare their extensions
as required, then it is not necessary to understand the agreement when processing the 
resource content.
</p>

<a name="lang"> </a>
<a name="language"> </a>
<h3>Language</h3>

<p>
Each resource may have a language element that specifies the base language of the content using a <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp47">code defined in BCP 47</a>.
The language element is provided to support indexing and accessibility (e.g. text-to-speech use the language tag). 
</p>
<p>
There is no default language, though one may be inferred from the context of use.
Not all of the content of the resource has to be in the specified language. 
</p>
<p>
If a language is specified, it should also be specified on the <a href="narrative.html#Narrative">Narrative Text</a>. 
The html language tag in the narrative is used when processing the narrative. The language tag on the resource is provided 
for use to specify the language of alternate presentations generated from the data in the resource
</p>

<a name="tags"> </a>
<a name="tag"> </a>
<h3>Tags, Profiles, and Security Labels</h3>
<p>
These 3 metadata attributes are part of the resource, but are never used to keep information 
that needs to be understood when interpreting the content of a resource; their 
function is limited to finding and controlling access to the resource, and connecting 
resources to technical or clinical workflow.
</p>

<h4>Tags</h4>
<p>
Tags are used to associate additional operational information with the Resources, including
such as workflow management. A typical use of tagging would be to maintain an informal list
of resources that need review.
</p>
<p>
In a general tag, the <a href="datatypes.html#coding">concept</a> may be a reference to a 
healthcare vocabulary, including ones defined in this specification, or vocabularies such 
as those defined by HL7 for other purposes (e.g. v2 and v3/CDA), LOINC, or SNOMED CT. 
Alternatively, the concept may be one defined by the implementation in the local context. 
</p>

<a name="profile-tags"> </a>
<h4>Profile Tags</h4>
<p>
A profile assertion represents a claim that the resource conforms to <a href="profile.html">the identified profile</a>,
which makes sets of rules about what 
content is allowed to be in a resource. In a profile tag, the term
is a URL that references a profile resource.
</p>
<p>
It's always possible to determine whether a resource conforms to a 
profile simply by testing it against the profile (the <a href="downloads.html">validation tools</a>
provide the functionality to perform this test in a variety of contexts). 
However there are several circumstances where simply examining whether 
a resource conforms to a particular profile as needed is impractical:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A server searching a set of resources for ones that conform to a particular profile</li>
 <li>A receiver that has many profiles to choose when validating resource</li>
</ul>
<p>
Profile Tags serve these use cases - a client/creator of a resource can tag the 
resource with an assertion that the resource conforms to a profile. The server/receiver
of the resource can choose to take this assertion at face value, or to assist in locating
the profile against which to validate the resource. 
</p>
<p>
Note: resources can conform to multiple profiles at once. A resource can conform to 
a profile without ever being labelled that it does, or a resource may falsely claim to conform 
to a profile. For this reason, applications processing resources SHOULD always 
depend on the contents of the resource when processing them, and/or check resources
against profiles directly rather than relying the existence of profile tags.
Many trading partner agreements will make rules about what claims can be made 
and when they must be tested, which will make the profile assertion more reliable. 
</p>
<p>
Profile Tags are provided as a method of finding resources that conform to 
a particular profile, not statements of meaning about the resource.
</p>

<h4>Security Labels</h4>
<p>
A security label is attached to a resource to provide specific security metadata 
about the information in the resource. For further information, see 
<a href="security-labels.html">Security Labels</a>.
</p>

<h3>Further Information</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="conformance-rules.html">Conformance Rules</a></li>
  <li><a href="resources.html">Resource Definitions</a></li>
  <li><a href="references.html">References between Resources</a></li>
  <li><a href="narrative.html">Narratives</a></li>
  <li><a href="formats.html">Formats:</a> <a href="xml.html">XML</a>, <a href="json.html">JSON</a> </li>
  <li><a href="extensibility.html">Extensibility</a> (<a href="extensibility-examples.html">Examples</a>)</li>
  <li><a href="resource-definitions.html">Detailed Descriptions</a></li>
  <li><a href="compatibility.html">Inter-version Compatibility</a></li>
</ul>

  <script src="external/jquery/jquery.js"> </script>
<script src="jquery-ui.min.js"> </script>
<script>
 try {
   var currentTabIndex = sessionStorage.getItem('fhir-resource-tab-index');
 } catch(exception){ 
  if (navigator.userAgent.toLowerCase().indexof('msie') == -1)
    alert(exception);
 }
 if (!currentTabIndex)
   currentTabIndex = '0';

$( '#tabs-Meta' ).tabs({ active: currentTabIndex, activate: function( event, ui ) { store(ui.newTab.index()); } });
    
     
function store(currentTab) {
  try {
    sessionStorage.setItem('fhir-resource-tab-index', currentTab);
  } catch(exception){ 
  if (navigator.userAgent.toLowerCase().indexof('msie') == -1)
    alert(exception);
  }
  $( '#tabs-Meta' ).tabs('option', 'active', currentTab);
}     
</script>

</div>


