<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
  <p><b>Note to Balloters for Ballot5</b>: Changes include compatible substantive updates to BodyStructure cardinalities and included-structure detail, plus clarification updates to narrative guidance, examples, search-parameter wording, 5Ws mappings, and artifact-scoped terminology.</p>
  <p>Reviewers should pay particular attention to the included-structure changes and the change making <code>BodyStructure.patient</code> optional, because these affect how anatomical and pathological structures can be represented, reused, and tracked.</p>
  <p>This resource is referenced from the <a href="diagnostics-module.html">Diagnostics Module</a>; reviewers should also consider related module-page ballot content when reviewing this resource.</p>
  <p><b>Compatible substantive</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>BodyStructure.includedStructure.morphology</code> now permits multiple morphology values <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-56262">FHIR-56262</a></li>
    <li><code>BodyStructure.includedStructure.origin</code> was added to record origin information for an included structure <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-53864">FHIR-53864</a></li>
    <li><code>BodyStructure.patient</code> was relaxed from required to optional <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54450">FHIR-54450</a></li>
  </ul>
  <p><b>Non-substantive</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>The BodyStructure introduction and boundaries guidance was clarified, including when to reference BodyStructure and how body structure and laterality fit with imaging selection guidance <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54747">FHIR-54747</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54845">FHIR-54845</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54872">FHIR-54872</a></li>
    <li>Additional BodyStructure example material was added, including a breast-mass example and examples-list updates <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-57518">FHIR-57518</a></li>
    <li>The 5Ws mapping exceptions and artifact-scoped terminology/display content received cleanup updates <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54961">FHIR-54961</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-56060">FHIR-56060</a></li>
  </ul>
  <p><b>Additional changes</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>Additional changes as described in <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54873">FHIR-54873</a> and <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-54843">FHIR-54843</a>.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>The BodyStructure resource contains details about an anatomical or pathological structure (e.g. a cyst) and may include patient information, identifiers, text descriptions, images, and spatially relevant characteristics.
</p>
<p>BodyStructure is used when a coded concept alone does not provide sufficient detail, identity, persistence, or reuse for the use case. It supports representation of complex anatomical structures and locations using included and excluded structures and can provide additional detail such as laterality, directionality, qualifiers, morphology, images, landmark-based positioning, and spatial references.</p>
<p>Some anatomical structures are discontiguous or consist of multiple related structures. A single BodyStructure instance may represent multiple included structures when they are considered a single anatomical or pathological entity for recording, tracking, or clinical management purposes. Separate BodyStructure instances should be used when structures need to be identified, assessed, tracked, treated, or managed independently over time.
</p>
<p>The BodyStructure resource supports recording and tracking an anatomic location or structure on a patient outside the context of another resource.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>A BodyStructure instance is appropriate when the anatomical structure or pathological structures need to be recorded and tracked outside the context of a single resource, reused across resources, or described with additional detail such as laterality, qualifiers, morphology, images, or spatial description.
</p>
<p>The <code>bodyStructure</code> element in resources that support it can be used when the resource's code does not fully specify the relevant body structure. As a <a href="references.html#CodeableReference">CodeableReference</a>, it supports both simple coded body structure concepts and references to a BodyStructure instance when additional detail or site-specific identity is needed; repeating elements allow multiple body structures to be represented.
</p>
<p>Referencing resources, such as <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> or <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, can use one or more BodyStructure instances to identify the relevant structures consistently across multiple records and over time.
</p>
<p>Resources that support references to BodyStructure should generally allow multiple references where multiple anatomical or pathological structures may be relevant to the clinical context. A resource may reference multiple BodyStructure instances when the structures are distinct entities that need to be identified or managed independently. A single BodyStructure instance may represent multiple related structures through its includedStructure elements when those structures are treated as a single anatomical or pathological entity.
</p>
<p>If a resource's code implies a body structure, any referenced BodyStructure should be consistent with that code and used to provide additional anatomical detail.
</p>
</div>
</div>
