<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<blockquote class="ballot-note" id="bn1">
<p><b>Note to Balloters:</b> To ensure this resource is ready for Normative status, we are seeking ballot comment on the substantive content. The key changes made since R5 include:</p>
<ul>
 <li>BodyStructure.morphology has been moved to BodyStructure.includedStructure.morphology</li>
 <li>Added BodyStructure.includedStructure.image to provide an image of the includedStructure or excludedStructure.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>
The BodyStructure resource contains details about the anatomical location of a specimen or body part, including patient information, identifiers, as well as text descriptions and images. Note that some body structures are discontiguous.
</p>
<p>
When needed, it allows the the representation of complex body structures and/or locations using the included and excluded elements. It can provide indications of laterality and directionality to the anatomic location. This capability may be required when not indicated in a corresponding code (e.g., includedStructure.structure or excludedStructure.structure). The BodyStructure resource supports recording and tracking an anatomic location or structure on a patient outside the context of another resource. For example, it can be the target of a <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a> or <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resource.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
If a resource's code value implies a body structure, then the bodyStructure resource should be used consistent with the code and to provide any additional detail. The bodySite element in any resource can be used when the resource's code is not implicit about the body structure and does not require extensive detail. 
</p>
</div>
</div>
