<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!--
also from Russ, consider whether to put somewhere:

I think that is a key concept, that having an allergy list as a distinct and separate element of clinical documentation is typical, even invariant.  And . 

-->
<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Allergy/Intolerance resources are used to provide information about 
adverse sensitivities to substances that lead to physiologic changes 
that are clinically observable.  An adverse sensitivity is defined as:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
  A condition expected to result in undesirable physiologic reaction to an 
  amount of a substance that would not produce a reaction in most individuals.  
  The substance is the trigger of an immunologic response that produces the 
  observed physiologic changes, or in some instances nonimmunologic mechanisms 
  that produce clinically identical physiologic changes.  The immunologic 
  response might be considered the actual cause of the reaction, but it is 
  exposure to the trigger substance that is clinically observable.
  </p>  
</blockquote>  
<p>
This definition excludes clinically identical episodes that may be caused by 
physical agents, such as heat, cold, sunlight, or vibration, by exercise activity, 
or by infectious agents. Those conditions caused by physical agents or infectious 
would be captured on the problem list (<a href="list.html">List</a>/<a href="condition.html">Condition</a> Resources). The allergy/intolerance list is a list of 
conditions that represent a propensity unique to this individual for 
a reaction upon future exposure to a specified substance. 
</p>
<p>
Note that this specification draws a distinction between the 
patients condition/problem list and an allergy/intolerance list, even 
though allergies and intolerances are also conditions. This is because the distinction 
is a long established clinical workflow, even to patients. Asking an individual 
"if they have any problems" is not going to invoke an account of their past 
reactions to medications or foods. Instead, they are asked if they "have any allergies".    
An allergy/intolerance is also different in that a potential harm from exposure 
to an external substance that may be ordered by a provider in the course of 
their care but is not inherent to exposure to that substance for the general 
population.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Most of the details of the sensitivity can be found in the set of 
<a href="adversereaction.html">reactions</a> that are associated with the resource,
though these may not be present when the patient has not provided enough
information. <a href="adversereaction.html">Adverse Reactions</a> do not 
have to be always associated with an AllergyIntolerance which may appropriate 
when an single reaction has not provided enough evidence for a meaningful 
Allergy/Intolerance, or in specific views of events rather than in a general
clinical record.
</p>
</div>

</div>

