<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!--

Clarifications to provide: 

the duality of document and document bundle
why to include resources in the document bundle 
obligations involved in pulling content out of document
address question of immutability and it's meaning (including "the document id (the feed.id of the document id) can never be re-used for a different set of resources. The order of the resources, and their content, must be identical, if the feed.id is the same.")

my view is that the document exists whether there's an atom feed or not. but that the atom feed is necessary to allow normal systems to manage it. If you're a wizard level REST guy (see Josh/Lloyd) you might be able to manage all the implications of attestation and immutability in REST. Normal humans will author it piece meal, and then wrap it up in atom feed to give it trackable integrity.
[6:07:49 AM] Grahame Grieve: So the logical document exists without atom.

-->

<p>
FHIR resources can be used to build clinical documents that capture information about clinical observations and services. 
A clinical document is a <a href="extras.html#bundle">bundle</a> (a list of resources in an <a href="extras.html#bundles">atom feed</a>) that is 
fixed in scope, frozen in time and authored and/or attested as a set of logically contained resources by humans, organizations and devices. Documents built in 
this fashion may be exchanged between systems and also persisted in document storage and management 
systems, including systems such as IHE XDS. Applications claiming conformance to this framework claim 
to be conformant to "FHIR documents". 
</p>

<p>
Note that FHIR defines both this document format and also a <a href="documentreference.html">document reference resource</a>. FHIR documents are for documents 
that are authored and assembled in FHIR, while the document reference resource is for general references to other documents. 
</p>

<h2>Document Content</h2>
<p>
All documents have the same structure: a <a href="extras.html#bundle">bundle</a> 
<a href="extras.html#tags">identified by the tag</a> "http://hl7.org/fhir/tag/document", 
and that has a <i>Document</i> resource (see below) as the first resource in the bundle, 
followed by a series of other resources referenced from the <i>Document</i> 
resource that provides guidance on how they fit together. The bundle gathers all the content
of the document into a single XML document which may be signed and managed as required. The resources
include both human readable and computer processable portions.
</p>
<p>
The document resource identifies the document and its purpose, sets the context of the document and 
carries key information such as the subject and author. It also divides the document up into a 
series of sections that contain other resources identified in this specification that 
carry the content. Any resource referenced directly in the Document resource SHALL be included
in the bundle when the document is assembled. Other resources that these referenced resources refer to
may also be included in the bundle if the document originator chooses to. 
</p>
<p>
<a href="profile.html">Document profiles</a> can make additional rules about which resources
SHALL be included in the bundle along with the resources that are directly referenced in the Document resource. 
In addition, Document Profiles can specify what sections a document contains and what the 
constraints on those contents are. Applications should consider publishing <a href="conformance.html">conformance 
statements</a> that identify particular documents they support.
</p>
<h2>Document Status Codes</h2>
<p>
Every document has a status, which describes the status of the content of the document. Documents
themselves are never changed - once created, the document is frozen, but the information in them
can change, and new documents can be released in the same series. The document status relates to 
the standing of this information in the series. The status of the document is taken from this list of codes:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr> <td><b>Code</b></td> <td><b>Definition</b></td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>preliminary</td> <td>This is an preliminary document (also known as initial or interim). The content may be incomplete or unverified.</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>final</td> <td>The document is complete and verified by an appropriate person, and no further work is planned</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>appended</td> <td>The document has been modified subsequent to being released as "final", and is complete and verified by an authorised person. The modifications added new information to the document, but did not revise existing content</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>amended</td> <td>The document has been modified subsequent to being released as "final", and is complete and verified by an authorised person</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>retracted</td> <td>The document was originally created/issued in error, and this is an amendment that marks that the entire series should not be considered as valid</td> </tr>
</table>
<p>
A document status only moves down through this list - it moves from preliminary to final, and then it may progress to either appended or amended. 
In many workflows, only final documents are not made available, and the preliminary status is not used. When a document is marked as appended or 
amended, the document SHOULD reference the document that is being replaced in <i>Document.replaces</i> if it exists. if the document issuer issues
documents in request, rather then posting them to a repository in advance, there may be no docuemnt to replace. 
</p>
<p>
A very few documents are created entirely in error in the workflow - usually the document concerns the wrong patient or is written by the wrong author,
and the error is only detected after the document has been released. To support resolution of this case, a new document marked as "retracted" can
be created. This means that the entire series is now considered to be created in error, and systems receiving documents marked as retracted 
SHOULD remove data taken from earlier documents from routine use, and/or take other appropriate actions. Systems are not required to 
provide this workflow, or support retracted documents, but they SHALL not ignore a status of retracted. Note that systems that handle 
documents and don't support the retracted status need to define some other way of handling documents that are created in error; while
this is not a common occurrence, many clinical systems have no provision for removing erroneous information from a patient's record, 
and there is no way for a user to know that it is not fit for use. 
</p>
<p>
Note: for RIM-centric readers, see the <a href="document-status.html">v3 mapping for the codes</a>, and the <a href="document-mappings.html#rim">RIM mapping for the element</a>.
</p>

<a name="bundle"> </a>
<h2>Document End-Points</h2>

<p>
There are several different RESTful end-points used with Document resources and document bundles. 
The use of the various end-points can be best be described by considering the consequences 
of posting to them:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr> <td><b>End-Point</b></td> <td><b>Type of Content</b></td> <td><b>Description</b></td> </tr>
 <tr> <td>[baseurl]/Document</td> <td>Document Resource</td> <td>Just a document resource, not an entire 
   document. The /document end-point is used for manipulating just the document backbone, not the entire 
   content. This is useful either when documents are being built, or when documents have been decomposed
   into constituent parts in order to allow the section content to be accessed directly</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td><a href="http.html#Binary">[baseurl]/binary</a></td> <td>Document Bundle</td> <td>Just store the entire document as 
   a sequence of bytes, and return exactly that sequence when requested. There is no way to find content in the /binary end-point,
   so usually this would be associated with a <a href="documentreference.html">Document Reference</a> so that applications
   can find and process the document, though this is not required</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td><a href="http.html#transaction">[baseurl]</a> (e.g. a transaction)</td> <td>Document Bundle</td> <td>Ignore the 
   fact that the bundle is a document, and process all the resources that it contains as individual resources. Clients SHOULD
   not expect that a document submitted using this method will be able to reassembled exactly by the server (e.g. even if the
   server can re-assemble the document (see below), it cannot be expected to be in the same order etc, and so a document signature is 
   very likely to be invalid)</td> </tr>
 <tr> <td><a href="message.html#mailbox">[baseurl]/mailbox</a></td> <td>Document Bundle</td> <td>Submit the 
 document to the client for processing. The exact processing the server performs is at the discretion of the
 server. It MAY perform one or more of these actions:
  <ul>
    <li>Resend the document elsewhere</li>
    <li>Break it up into individually accessible resources and make them available on a RESTful interface</li>
    <li>Retain the document in it's binary form and make it available on /binary, and perhaps also create a DocumentReference</li>
  </ul>
  The server is not obliged to do anything at all, or anything on this list, though it SHOULD declare what actions it takes in the 
  <a href="conformance.html">conformance statement</a>.
  </td> </tr>
</table>

<p>
Note: While these end-points are defined for use with document resources and document bundles, 
it is not necessary to use them. Documents may be transferred between systems using any method desired. 
</p>
</div>
