<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
FHIR resources can be used to build clinical documents that capture information about clinical observations and services. 
A clinical document is a <a href="extras.htm#bundle">bundle</a> (a list of resources in an <a href="extras.htm#bundles">atom feed</a>) that is 
fixed in scope, frozen in time and authored and/or attested as a set of logically contained resources by humans, organizations and devices. Documents built in 
this fashion may be exchanged between systems and also persisted in document storage and management 
systems, including systems such as IHE XDS. Applications claiming conformance to this framework claim 
to be conformant to "FHIR documents". 
</p>

<p>
Note that FHIR defines both this document format and also a <a href="documentreference.htm">document reference resource</a>. FHIR documents are for documents 
that are authored and assembled in FHIR, while the document reference resource is for general references to other documents. 
</p>

<h2>Document Content</h2>
<p>
All documents have the same structure: a <a href="extras.htm#bundle">bundle</a> 
<a href="extras.htm#tags">identified by the tag</a> "http://hl7.org/fhir/tag/document", 
and that has a <i>Document</i> resource (see below) as the first resource in the bundle, 
followed by a series of other resources referenced from the <i>Document</i> 
resource that provides guidance on how they fit together. The bundle gathers all the content
of the document into a single XML document which may be signed and managed as required. The resources
include both human and computer readable portions.
</p>
<p>
The document resource identifies the document and its purpose, sets the context of the document and 
carries key information such as the subject and author. It also divides the document up into a 
series of sections that contain other resources identified in this specification that 
carry the content. Any resource referenced directly in the Document resource must be included
in the bundle when the document is assembled. Other resources that these referenced resources refer to
may also be included in the bundle if the document originator chooses to. 
</p>
<p>
<a href="profile.htm">Document profiles</a> can make additional rules about which resources
must be included in the bundle along with the resources that are directly referenced in the Document resource. 
In addition, Document Profiles can specify what sections a document contains and what the 
constraints on those contents are. Applications should consider publishing <a href="conformance.htm">conformance 
statements</a> that identify particular documents they support.
</p>
<a name="bundle"> </a>
<h2>Document End-Points</h2>

<p>There are two RESTful end-points used for Documents:</p>

<ul>
 <li>[baseurl]/document/: a normal RESTful end point for document resources as standalone resources</li> 
 <li>[baseurl]/binary/: for documents as <a href="extras.htm#bundle">bundles</a></li> 
</ul>
<p>
Note: While these end-points are defined for use with document resources and document bundles, 
it is not necessary to use them. Documents may be transferred between systems by using the 
<a href="message.htm#mailbox">MailBox</a> target, or by using any other method desired. 
</p>
</div>
