<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul> 
 <li>The author and the attester are often the same person, but this may not be the case in some clinical workflows</li>
 <li>The attester attests to the collated narrative portions of the document resource, the subject resource, and the 
     resources referred to in the Document.section.content references. When a document is bundled, additional resources can be included, but these are not attested content</li>
 <li>The custodian is responsible for the maintenance of the document. Principally, they are responsible for the policy regarding persistence of the documents. They need not actually retain a copy of the document, but they should do so.</li>
</ul>  

<h2>Identifying a Document</h2>
<p>
There are two identifiers on the document information: <i>id</i> and <i>versionId</i>. These allow either
a logical document id or a version specific id to be provided, or both. This supports multiple different
identification strategies. The following combinations are allowed:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>A fully specified (both <a href="datatypes.htm#Identifier">Identifier</a> system and id) element is present for both <i>id</i> and <i>versionId</i>. This is the 
     preferred option: globally unique identifiers for both version and non-version specify the document</li>
 <li>A fully specified element for the <i>id</i> element and a local id (no system) for the version number. 
     This is equivalent to a document id and a version number. In this case the version number is assumed to be 
	 unique within the version series of the document identified by the <i>id</i> element</li>
 <li>A fully specified <i>versionId</i> with no <i>id</i> - this version of this document is identified, but there 
    is no version independent reference. This is discouraged, as explicit replacement tracking will be required and 
	this can be broken by missing links in the version chain</li>
</ul>
<p>
Any other combinations do not globally uniquely identity a document and are therefore not allowed.
</p>
<p>
Note that there is an additional identifier - the bundle identifier itself (<a href="extras.htm#bundles">atom</a> feed.id). This must be an absolute 
URI - in effect globally unique - but has no other particular meaning anywhere else in the specification.
For a document, it can be populated with some URI that is extracted from the <i>versionId</i> or <i>id</i>
above, or it can be a new UUID that has no other associated use. Implementers should not rely on its 
value matching one of the formal document identification elements.
</p>

<h2>Presenting a Document</h2>
<p>
The human display of the Document is the collated narrative portions of following resources (in order):
</p>
<ol>
 <li>The Document itself</li>
 <li>The Subject resource</li>
 <li>Resources referenced in the <i>section.content</i></li>
</ol>
<p>
The document narrative should summarize the important parts of the document header that are required 
to establish clinical context for the document (other than the subject, which is displayed in its own 
right). To actually build the combined narrative, simply append all the narrative &lt;div&gt; fragments. 
</p>

<a name="css"></a>
<h3>Styling Documents</h3>
<p>
In addition to the <a href="narrative.htm#css">basic style rules</a>, which must be followed, a document can 
contain a style sheet that contains additional styles that apply to the collated narrative. Unless
otherwise agreed in local trading partner agreements, applications displaying the collated narrative 
should use the style sheet provided in the document. Parties entering into such a trading agreement
should consider the implications it will have on their long term scope for document exchange 
very carefully. If the parties agree on a stylesheet that is not contained in the document, then 
it is likely that they will never be able to share their documents in a more general context, 
such as a regional or national EHR, or a global personal health record.
</p>

<h2>Document Handling Obligations</h2>
<p>
The authors and users of Clinical Documents, whether human or software, have 
obligations that they must satisfy. 
</p>

<h3>Author Obligations</h3>
<p>
A document author is an application that creates a document resource. The author may create 
new content resources and/or assemble already existing content resources while doing so. A document author 
has the following responsibilities:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Build a valid document header that conforms to the Document rules explained here and that only links to other valid resources</li>
 <li>Ensure that the content of the document and other resources conforms to any declared <a href="profile.htm">Profiles</a>.</li>
 <li>Ensure that the attesters are properly aware of the presentation of the document to which they are attesting</li>
</ul>

<h3>User Obligations</h3>
<p>
A document user is an application that receives or presents documents, or extracts data from them, or makes decisions because of them. 
The documents may be received directly from a document author, accessed via a document management system or forward by a third party. 
The document user is responsible for ensuring that received documents are processed and/or rendered in accordance 
to this specification. A document recipient has the following obligations:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>When storing/transmitting a document, any method may be used as long as the bundled document can be (re-)assembled with sufficient integrity to validate a digital signature (i.e. it is legitimate to unbundle the resources and store them on a FHIR RESTful server, but this is not required)</li>
 <li>When presenting the narrative of the document, the rules described above must be followed</li>
 <li>A user is allowed to extract resources or data from the document for other use, but such data is no longer considered to be attested by the document author</li>
 <li>Wherever the data (or information derived from it) is displayed to a user, there should always be a way for the user to access a presentation of the original document</li>
 <li>It must correctly determine when a document has been superseded (according the statements made in the 
    <i>setId</i>, <i>version</i> or <i>replaces</i> elements of received documents or those in the 
    source document management system) and either withdraw data extracted from superseded documents, 
    or warn users when they view the document</li>
</ul>

<a name="rest"></a>
<h2>Implementation Notes</h2>
<ul>
 <li>Document Bundles may be signed using digital signatures following the rules laid out in 
     the <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287" target="_blank">Atom specification</a>. 
     The signature SHOULD be provided by a listed attester of the document and the signature 
     SHOULD contain a <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmldsig-core/#sec-KeyInfo" target="_blank">KeyInfo 
     element</a> that contains a KeyName element whose value is a URI that matches the Atom <i>link</i> 
     element value for the matching attester resource.</li>
</ul>

</div>
