<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="identification"> </a>
<h2>Identifier and Version</h2>
<p>
The <i>identifier</i> and <i>version</i> elements may be used to reference this code system in a value set, or a 
<a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> template or <a href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186">HL7 v3</a> message 
(in the CD data type codeSystem and codeSystemVersion properties). These different contexts may make additional restrictions 
on the possible values of these elements.  These elements are generally not needed when using code systems with FHIR
implementations, as they can make use of the innate identifier and versioning mechanism associated with the resource.
</p>

<a name="properties"> </a>
<h2>Properties</h2>
<p>
Each code system can have one or more properties. Each concept defined by the code system
may have one more values for each property defined by the code system. Typical uses for 
properties include:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Tracking administrative status (inactive, deprecation date)</li>
 <li>Providing additional statements about the meaning of the concept</li>
 <li>Defining structured relationships with other concepts in the code system</li>
 <li>Assigning scoring values to the concepts</li>
</ul>
<p>
Properties are identified by their code (<code>CodeSystem.property.code</code>), which is used both internally within the 
code system resource (<code>CodeSystem.concept.property.code</code>) and also externally, in the following
places:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="">ConceptMap</a>: <code>ConceptMap.element.target.dependsOn.property</code> and <code>ConceptMap.element.target.product.property</code></li>
 <li><a href="">ValueSet</a>: <code>ValueSet.compose.include.filter.property</code> can refer to any defined code system property</li>
 <li><a href="">$lookup operation</a>: In <code>Parameters.parameter.name</code> when returning information about a code</li>
 <li><a href="">$translate operation</a>: In <code>Parameters.parameter.part.name</code> for dependencies and products</li>
 <li><a href="">$infer operation</a>: In <code>Parameters.parameter.name</code> when providing codes, and in <code>Parameters.parameter.name</code> when asking for codes</li>
</ul>
<p>
Properties are defined using the following elements:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr>
  <td><b>Name</b></td>
  <td><b>Details</b></td>
  <td><b>Description</b></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>code</td>
  <td><a href="datatypes.html#code">code</a></td>
  <td>Used to identify the property, as enumerated above</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>uri</td>
  <td>optional <a href="datatypes.html#code">uri</a></td>
  <td>Reference to the formal meaning of the property. One possible source of meaning is the <a href="codesystem-concept-properties.html">Concept Properties</a> code system. 
    This part of the definition is optional, but is recommended to provide an additional level of definitional consistency</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>description</td>
  <td>optional <a href="datatypes.html#code">string</a></td>
  <td>A description of the property- why it is defined, and how it's value might be used</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>type</td>
  <td>code | Coding | string | integer | boolean | dateTime</td>
  <td>The type of the property value. Properties of type "code" contain a code defined by the code system (e.g. a reference to anotherr defined concept)</td>
 </tr>
</table>
<p>
Note that properties provide a common view of concept relationships that is common across all code systems.
Some code systems define properties with more sophistication, such as groups of properties, or subsumption
relationships between properties (e.g. SNOMED CT). Servers providing support for these code systems will need
to know full details about the underlying relationships in order to provide the correct information about 
concepts and their properties, but this information does not surface in the resources or operations defined
by the FHIR specification.
</p>

</div>
