<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>

<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The ImmunizationEvaluation resource is intended to cover communicating the results of an evaluation of a vaccine administration event (documented using the Immunization resource) against a set of published recommendations (protocols). Evaluating administered doses in a patient's immunization history is central to ensuring that the patient if fully protected against vaccine-preventable diseases. It is also a necessary prerequisite to generating a customized set of immunization recommendations for the patient.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The ImmunizationEvaluation resource communicates the results of an evaluation of an instance of the Immunization resource relative to a set of published recommendations. It is intended to communicate if the vaccine administration event was "valid" or "not valid" relative to the recommendations. Once all vaccine administration events in a patient's record have been evaluated, it is then possible to generate a set of vaccination related recommendations, unique for the patient. These recommendations are communicated using the ImmunizationRecommedation resource.
</p>
<p>
As the ImmunizationEvaluation resource is focused on the evaluation of a single vaccine administration event, it does not include data regarding the overall patient status relative to the recommendations used in the evaluation. For example, a total of 3 doses of hepatitis B vaccine may be required for patient protection, but an instance of the ImmunizationEvaluation resource will be concerned with only one of the doses (although other instances of ImmunizationEvaluation should exist for the other doses). The ImmunizationRecommendation resource is used to convey the overall patient status (e.g. a dose is due or the patient is complete) relative to the hepatitis B series.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Through FHIR Release 3, the Immunization resource contained a 
"protocol" backbone element which functioned as an evaluation of the vaccine administration event. Beginning in Release 4, this new resource replaces the Immunization.protocol element.
</p>
</div>

</div>
