<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<h3>Relationship to ISO 11179</h3>
	<p>
One of the sources of the <b>DataElement</b> resource definition was the <a href="http://metadata-standards.org/11179/">ISO 11179</a>
Metadata Registries specification.  It defines a logical model for the classification, identification, naming and registration of 
Data Elements, Data Element Concepts and their associated Value and Conceptual Domains.</p>
	<p>
The <b>DataElement</b> resource can be used to represent both Data_Element and Data_Element_Concept in the ISO logical model.
(The <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a> resource provides the details for Value_Domain and Conceptual_Domain for enumerated elements.)
The determination of whether a <b>DataElement</b> resource instance is an ISO 11179 Data_Element or Data_Element_Concept is determined by 
whether the <code>type</code> property is specified - which corresponds to the ISO property Data_Element.domain.datatype which is required 
for Data_Elements.  I.e. If DataElement.type is present, the instance represents a 11179 data element.  If DataElement.type is absent, the
instance represents a 11179 data element concept.
</p>
	<p>
Unlike the 11179 logical specification, the
<b>DataElement</b> resource does not require a linkage from data element to a distinct data element concept, though this linkage can
be established through an extension if desired.  The typical means of identification of the data element concept is expected to instead
occur through the mapping of the data element to a particular code or reference model that formally defines the concept. It is possible this
reference model could be based on ISO's Object_Class and Property mechanism.  However, mappings to other reference models are also possible,
for example:
</p>
	<ul>
		<li>HL7's <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/rim.cfm">Reference Information Model</a>
		</li>
		<li>
			<a href="http://www.openehr.org/">Open EHR's</a> reference model</li>
		<li>the <a href="http://bridg.com">BRIDG</a> logical model</li>
		<li>terminologies such as <a href="http://loinc.org">LOINC</a> or <a href="http://www.ihtsdo.org/snomed-ct/">SNOMED</a>
		</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
	In the event of multiple
codes and/or mappings, the "authoritative" mapping (the one formally defining the concept) is identified by either setting the "primary" element
on the code or by specifying the "primary mapping" ISO 11179 extension.
    </p>
	<p>
It is possible to create instances that are "conforming", or even "strictly conforming" to the 11179 specification. However, doing
so will require the use of extensions to convey certain properties that are not part of the core resource and data types.  An initial
starter <a href="dataelement-11179.html">ISO 11179 profile</a> is included in the FHIR specification.  It defines extensions that are relevant to the 
<a href="dataelement-sdc.html">SDC DataElement</a> profile.  If there is sufficient interest, the existing starter set may be
enhanced to contain a complete set of extensions and a full 11179 in a future release of the specification.
</p>
	<h3>Data Elements vs. Codes</h3>
	<p>
Data elements (and their registries) and codes (and their code systems) serve different purposes.  Data elements describe the characteristics of a piece of
data while codes describe a particular concept (often in relation to other concepts).  However, because data elements provide
a definition of the meaning of a particular element, they  
can be thought of as being codes.  One of their purposes is to define variables, observations, or questions that include information about how to 
collect a variable's value--including information about data types and guidance about the use of about answer lists and/or units of measure.
This function is typically done by code systems such as <a href="http://loinc.org">LOINC</a> and
<a href="http://www.ihtsdo.org/snomed-ct/">SNOMED CT</a>.  (Note that LOINC provides considerable detail about allowed answers, while most other code 
systems such as SNOMED only allow identifying the question.)It would be possible to treat a registry of data elements using a common
identifier system/namespace as a code system.  Similarly, data elements can be mapped to each other (and to codes) in the same manner as 
codes can be mapped by making use of the <a href="conceptmap.html">ConceptMap</a> resource.
</p>
<p>
Refer to the <a href="valueset.html#detailed-metadata">Code systems with detailed metadata</a> section of <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a> resource
for additional discussion of the relationship between DataElement and code systems.
</p>
	<a name="standardization"/>
	<h3>Standardization through governance and registries</h3>
	<p>
As noted in the introduction, one of the main purposes for the use of data elements is 'standardization' - gaining consistent
(and thus comparable) data capture of data in <a href="questionnaire.html">questionnaires</a>, <a href="observation.html">observations</a>
and within other resources.  However, merely defining data elements is not, in itself, sufficient to improve standardization.  To
ensure consistency of data, there needs to be several additional things:
</p>
	<ul>
		<li>There must be a shared repository of data elements that will be consulted and used by the community where improved interoperability
    is targeted.  Numerous groups will define and register data elements in a wide variety of repositories for a wide variety of purposes.
    To improve interoperability, everyone in the target community needs to be working from the same set.</li>
		<li>There must be governance over the repository of data elements to ensure consistency of granularity and reference structures - those
    designing questionnaires, profiles, etc. need to be able to find the appropriate data element easily within the repository and there
    should ideally only be one data element for a given purpose.  If a repository accepts 15 data elements defining different ways of
    capturing the same piece of information, there will be no improvement in interoperability.</li>
		<li>There must be incentives or governance processes in place that encourage or require the use of data elements from the shared
    repository when defining forms, profiles and other structures where improved interoperability is desired.</li>
		<li>There must be allowance for (and a transition path for) legacy systems that capture data or have existing data that is not in
    alignment with the approved data elements.</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
		<b>Data Elements</b> are a tool through which improved standardization can be achieved but without adequate processes, they will not
achieve significant benefit.
</p>

<h3>Data Element granularity and hierarchy</h3>
<p>
Data elements can be defined at a wide variety of granularities.  For example:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Systolic Blood pressure</li>
  <li>Systolic Blood pressure (sitting)</li>
  <li>Systolic Blood pressure (sitting, pressure cuff)</li>
  <li>Systolic Blood pressure (sitting, pressure cuff) mmHg</li>
</ul>
<p>
Coded data elements can be defined without value sets, with suggested value sets, with required but extensible value sets or with
completely locked down value sets.  Numeric values can be defined with or without allowed ranges.  String data can be defined
with or without patterns or lengths.  All are valid data elements.
</p>
<p>
When defining data elements, it's important to decide what level of detail/granularity is appropriate for the intended purpose.
The tighter the data element is defined, the greater interoperability of the data, however the smaller the set of systems that
will be able to satisfy the constraints and the larger the number of data elements that will be required to cover a given
domain.  In some cases, multiple granularities may be appropriate, though this can introduce challenges in ensuring that the
appropriate granularity is selected for a given use.  As a rule, data elements should be defined as loosely as possible while
still ensuring that all data captured using the data element will be sufficiently comparable to meet the needs of the group
defining and using the data elements.  A corollary to this is that data elements defined by one group will not always meet
the needs of another group, even if they may be covering the same domain.
</p>

<h3>Comparability and conversion of data elements</h3>
<p>
Two pieces of data don't necessarily need to be based on the same data element in order to be comparable or aggregatable.
As noted above, it's possible for one data element to be a proper subset of another.  In addition, it may be possible to
convert data from being conformant with one data element to being conformant with another data element.  This conversion
could be lossless or may involve some loss of semantic precision.  For example, a weight measurement captured in pounds
can be seamlessly converted to kilograms.  Similarly, coded data captured using one value set can be converted to another
value set provided mappings are available.  The nature of the mappings would determine whether any loss of semantics
would occur.
</p>

<h3>Data Element stringency</h3>
<p>
The stringency element allows identifying the types of usages for which the data element is appropriate.  Some uses
(direct comparison of data, auto-population of data, etc.) are inappropriate with loose definitions of elements.  On the
other hand, overly-restrictive data elements can result in a large number of data elements and limited abilities to
compare similar but not identical data.  For now, the definition of what level of constraints are appropriate/necesssary
for a given level of stringency is left to implementers, though future versions this specification may assert at least
some level of guidance in this area.
</p>

<h3>Definitions</h3>
<p>
Data elements provide their value by clearly defining the meaning and content of a particular type of data to be exchanged.
This value depends on the meaning associated with the element being clear for all potential implementers of the element.
I.e. For a data element to be useful, it needs to have a good quality definition.  Characteristics of good quality
definitions include:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>The definition does not use the name of the element as part of the definition - it should provide additional information
  above and beyond the name.</li>
  <li>The definition should be more than one or two words.</li>
  <li>Ideally, the definition should be phrased in a manner such that the definition could be substituted for the data element
  name in a sentence.  E.g. "gender" might be defined as "the sexual identity of a person as used for administrative purposes"</li>
  <li>If the data element does not have a value set and does not make use of a simple type such as date, integer or boolean,
  it should list several example values as part of the definition.</li>
  <li>Information about the rationale for the element or additional usage notes should not be conveyed as part of the definition
  but should instead make use of the <code>notes</code> or <code>rationale</code> elements.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Data Elements and Access Control</h3>
<p>
Because Data Elements define precise pieces of data that can be conveyed in a variety of places, they may form a useful
mechanism for the definition of fine-grained data access controls.  The base resource does not include mechanisms for linking
access controls directly do data elements, however, an extension could allow a particular data element to be associated with
particular <a href="security-labels.html">Security Labels</a>.  Whether this level of control is appropriate may vary by
implementation environment.
</p>

<h3>References to and from Data Elements</h3>
<p>
One of the primary purposes of the DataElement resource is to allow data conveyed in a variety of different forms to be "linked"
to the data element and identified as being equivalent/comparable/semantically-aligned.  There are a variety of different ways
this can occur:
</p>
<ul>
<li><code>DataElement.element.code</code> allows a data element to be linked as "semantically equivalent" to the specified code.</li>
<li><code>DataElement.element.mapping</code> allows a data element to be linked to a particular data structure such as a FHIR resource, a CDA template, an OpenEHR archetype, etc.</li>
<li>The <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> extension <a href="extension-questionnaire-dereference.html">deReference</a> allows a
particular question in a questionnaire to be linked to a data element deemed to correspond to that question.  This mechanism supports
population of questionnaire instances on the basis of known data elements</li>
</ul>
</div>
