<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource covers two major use-cases: 
</p>
<ol>
  <li>Definitions of types of measurements or observations that may be requested or performed.  In HL7, these are sometimes referred to as service, test or observation "master files"</li>
  <li>Definitions of "data elements" (DEs) that may be used in <a href="questionnaire.html">questionnaires</a> (survey instruments and data collection forms) and <a href="profile.html">profiles</a> and potentially mapped to elements in other resources and profiles</li>
</ol>
<p>
The purpose of the first use-case is to allow systems to identify what types of lab orders, diagnostic studies and other types of observations may be requested or
performed within a particular organization or other context.  An ordering practitioner can query for a list of data elements by category name or other
criteria and identify which, within a set of similar tests, they wish to request to be performed.
</p>
<p>
The focus of the second use-case is standardizing data capture and reporting.  By defining standard names, data capture constraints, questions and other characteristics,
the data gathered within and across organizations via questionnaires, as part of clinical studies, etc. can be made more consistent.  When designing clinical studies,
constructing questionnaires, building profiles or performing other tasks that involve determining what data will be captured or exchanged and how, designers can query
to find pre-defined data element definitions they can leverage or map to.  By encouraging consistency around data element definitions, data types, value sets, string
lengths and other constraints, data becomes more easily exchangeable and comparable across systems.  This benefits interoperability and clinical research.  (For more 
discussion, see the section on <a href="#standardization">standardization</a> below.)
</p>
<p>
The scope covers base capabilities of the ISO 11179 Metadata Registries specification which defines DEs.  It also covers observation definitions by ontologies such as LOINC.  
The term "observation" is interpreted in its broadest sense as "any element that might be thought of as the 'value' in a name-value pair".  So it includes such concepts as
patient gender, practitioner address and other data elements that would not typically be captured using the <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resource.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
This resource has significant overlap with <a href="profile.html">Profile</a> and <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>.
</p>
<p>
Profile also defines data elements.  However,
it does so only in the context of constraints or extensions on FHIR resources.  As well, <a href="profile.html">Profile</a> typically identifies a number of data elements
together in context.  <b>DataElement</b> defines only a single data element and it does so in a manner that is not directly tied to FHIR.  Data elements
might define the value of an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, constrain the allowed answer to a question in a <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>
(including providing a list of permitted answers), describe the permitted value captured of an element in some
other resource (<a href="patient.html">Patient</a>, <a href="familyhistory.html">FamilyHistory</a>, etc.) or even used outside FHIR entirely in a CDA document or HL7 v2
specification.  Authors of <a href="profile.html">Profile</a>s may leverage (and reference) <b>DataElement</b>s when defining the data elements with the Profile.
(For implementability reasons, the data constraints should still be explicitly exposed within the <a href="profile.html">Profile</a> rather than being included "by reference" 
to the <b>DataElement.)</b>
</p>
<p>
<a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> is to both define forms, surveys and other structures that can be filled out.  <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> 
also defines data elements.  However, it does so only in the context of a particular questionnaire
design.  In contrast, <b>DataElement</b> is focused on defining data elements independent of use.  A single <b>DataElement</b> might be referenced in numerous 
<a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>s, or even potentially in multiple places within a single <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>.  This reference
might either be implicit or may be explicit through an extension.  (For implementability reasons, the data constraints should still be explicitly exposed within the
<a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> rather than being included "by reference" to the <b>DataElement</b>.)
</p>
<p>
<b>Note</b>: Extensions on <b>DataElement</b> that define the characteristics of a data element will typically also be applicable to <a href="profile.html">Profile</a>'s
ElementDefinition and <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>'s Question data element as both are also used to define the characteristics of a data element.
</p>
<p>
<b>Ballot Issue</b>: Should a shared structure be used in <a href="profile.html">Profile</a>, <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> and <b>DataElement</b>
to capture constraints on data elements, or is it acceptable for them to continue to be maintained in a separate, but "similar" manner?
</p>
<p>
<b>DataElement</b> differs from <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> in that it describes what kind of observations <b>can</b> occur, while 
<a href="observation.html">Observation</a> focuses on a specific observation of a specific subject at a particular time that <b>has</b> occurred.
</p>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
