<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<h3>ISO 11179</h3>
<p>
One of the sources of the <b>DataElement</b> resource definition was the <a href="http://metadata-standards.org/11179/">ISO 11179</a>
Metadata Registries specification.  It defines a logical model for the classification, identification, naming and registration of 
Data Elements, Data Element Concepts and their associated Value and Conceptual Domains.</p>
<p>
The <b>DataElement</b> resource can be used to represent both Data_Element and Data_Element_Concept in the ISO logical model.
(The <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a> resource provides the details for Value_Domain and Conceptual_Domain for enumerated elements.)
The determination of whether a <b>DatElement</b> is a Data_Element or Data_ElementConcept is determined by whether the <code>type</code> 
property is specified - which corresponds to the ISO property Data_Element.domain.datatype which is required for Data_Elements.
</p>
<p>
Unlike the 11179 logical specification, the
<b>DataElement</b> resource does not require a linkage from data element to a distinct data element concept, though this linkage can
be established through an extension if desired.  The typical means of identification of the data element concept is expected to instead
occur through the mapping of the data element to a particular reference model that formally defines the concept.  It is possible this
reference model could be based on ISO's Object_Class and Property mechanism.  However, mappings to other reference models are also possible,
for example:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>HL7's <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/rim.cfm">Reference Information Model</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.openehr.org/">Open EHR's</a> reference model</li>
  <li>the <a href="http://bridg.com">BRIDG</a> logical model</li>
  <li>terminologies such as <a href="http://loinc.org">LOINC</a> or <a href="http://www.ihtsdo.org/snomed-ct/">SNOMED</a></li>
</ul>
<p>
It is possible to create instances that are "conforming", or even "strictly conforming" to the 11179 specification, however doing
so will require the use of extensions to convey certain properties that are not part of the core resource and data types.  An initial
starter <a href="dataelement-11179.html">ISO 11179 profile</a> that defines extensions that are relevant to the 
<a href="dataelement-sdc.html">SDC DataElement</a> profile.  If there is sufficient interest, the existing starter set may be
enhanced to contain a complete set of extensions and a full 11179 in a future release of the specification.
</p>

</div>
