<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="base"></a>
<h3>Derived OperationDefinitions</h3>

<p>
OperationDefinitions can describe entirely new operations, but they can also describe a restricted implementation
of an existing operation e.g. when a server implements some but not all the features of an operation defined in 
another specification. These are called derived operation definitions.
</p>
<p>
An OperationDefinition does by declaring a base as shown in the <a href="operationdefinition-example.html">example</a>:
</p>
<pre class="json">
{
  "resourceType" : "OperationDefinition",
  "id" : "example",
  "url" : "http://hl7.org/fhir/OperationDefinition/example",
  "name" : "PopulateQuestionnaire",
  // snip
  "code" : "populate",
  "base" : "http://hl7.org/fhir/OperationDefinition/Questionnaire-populate"
  // snip
}
</pre>
<p>
When constraining an existing operation like this, operation definitions can make 
optional parameters required or not used, introduce new parameters (required or optional), 
clarify documentation, and even change the code for the operation (see next section).
The derived operation can't change the nature of the operation itself, nor can 
it change add types to parameters or prohibit mandatory parameters.
</p>

<a name="renaming"></a>
<a name="code"></a>
<h3>OperationDefinition Code</h3>

<p>
Operations are invoked by their code, not their name. The name is descriptive, for code generation, 
e.g. <code>ValueSetExpansion</code>, while the code is what is used in a URL e.g. 
<code>http://example.org/fhir/ValueSet/$expand</code>. When defining operations, 
for maximum compatibility, use only lowercase ASCII characters. 
See <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/FHIR/Guide+to+Designing+Resources#GuidetoDesigningResources-NamingRules&amp;Guidelines">Naming Rules &amp; Guidelines</a> 
for the internal HL7 rules around codes, which are useful additional advice for all implementers.
</p>
<p>
It is possible for two different organizations to create different operation definitions with the same code or, perhaps more likely, to define equivalent operations that have the 
same code but incompatible approaches in their parameter lists. Note that HL7 will never define multiple operations with the same code. 
</p>
<p>
It is also possible, though unlikely, that a server will be required to support both of 
these operations. If this is the case, the server is able to do this by giving one of them
a new code and referring to it by definition in the capability statement. To illustrate
this, assume that two different organizations, "orgA" and "orgB", both define an operation 
with a code <code>dothis</code>, and the definitions are incompatible. OrgA publishes its operation
definition at http://orga.com/fhir/dothis.xml, and OrgB publishes its operation at 
http://fhir.orgb.com/meta/OperationDefinition/dothis. The server is able to implement
both. Its capability statement will say:
</p>
<pre class="xml">
&lt;CapabilityStatement xmlns=&quot;http://hl7.org/fhir&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!-- snip --&gt;
  &lt;rest&gt;
    &lt;!-- snip --&gt;
    &lt;operation&gt;
      &lt;name value=&quot;dothis&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;definition&gt;
        &lt;reference value=&quot;http://orga.com/fhir/dothis.xml&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/definition&gt;
    &lt;/operation&gt;
    &lt;operation&gt;
      &lt;name value=&quot;dothis2&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;definition&gt;
        &lt;reference value=&quot;http://fhir.orgb.com/meta/OperationDefinition/dothis&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/definition&gt;
    &lt;/operation&gt;
    &lt;!-- snip --&gt;
  &lt;/rest&gt;
  &lt;!-- snip --&gt;
&lt;/CapabilityStatement&gt;
</pre>
<p>
If a general purpose cross server client is looking for the implementation of the 
http://fhir.orgb.com/meta/OperationDefinition/dothis operation and wants to be
robust against this name clash problem, instead of simply executing the $dothis
operation, it can look at the server's <a href="capabilitystatement.html">CapabilityStatement</a> for the underlying
definition URI and then execute with the name given in the capability statement.
</p>
<p>
Note to implementers: it would be more consistent if CapabilityStatement.rest.operation.name was 
actually called "code", since it relates to OperationDefinition.code, but the confusion this 
can cause wasn't appreciated until the resource was normative. 
</p>

<a name="desc"></a>
<h3>Describing Operation Parameters</h3>

<p>
There are 2 ways to describe the input and output parameters for
an operation:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Using <code>OperationDefinition.parameter</code> to describe the parameters</li>
  <li>Using <code>OperationDefinition.inputProfile</code> and <code>OperationDefinition.outputProfile</code></li>
</ul>
<p>
The parameters is a simple list of possible parameters, along with cardinalities and types.
The profiles allow a rich set of validation rules etc. to be provided. OperationDefinitions SHALL
always define the parameters using <code>OperationDefinition.parameter</code> in the resource,
and MAY also provide profiles for the parameters. If present, the profiles SHALL NOT disagree
with the parameters defined for the operation.
</p>
<p>
As an example, consider an operation that defines 3 parameters, 2 in and 1 out:
</p>
<table class="grid">
<tr><td colspan="6"><b>In Parameters:</b></td></tr>
<tr><td><b>Name</b></td><td><b>Cardinality</b></td><td><b>Type</b></td><td><b>Binding</b></td><td><b>Profile</b></td><td><b>Documentation</b></td></tr>
<tr><td>a</td><td>0..1</td><td><a href="datatypes.html#integer">integer</a></td><td></td><td></td><td><p>An integer parameter</p></td></tr>
<tr><td>b</td><td>0..1</td><td><a href="patient.html">Patient</a></td><td></td><td></td><td><p>A patient parameter</p></td></tr>
<tr><td colspan="6"><b>Out Parameters:</b></td></tr>
<tr><td><b>Name</b></td><td><b>Cardinality</b></td><td><b>Type</b></td><td><b>Binding</b></td><td><b>Profile</b></td><td><b>Documentation</b></td></tr>
<tr><td>c</td><td>1..1</td><td><a href="datatypes.html#decimal">decimal</a></td><td></td><td></td><td><p>A result parameter</p></td></tr>
</table>
<p>
In addition to specifying the operation parameters directly, an operation definition can also provide a profile:
</p>
<pre class="json">
 "inputProfile" : "http://example.org/StructureDefinition/op.x.in.profile"
</pre>
<p>
This profile would describe a parameters resource with 2 parameters (using slicing), with the same details as the table above.
The operation definition would still list the parameters directly to save applications consuming the definition (e.g. to produce
an <a href="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification">OpenAPI document</a>) from parsing and interpreting the profile.
</p>

<a name="exec"></a>
<h3>Executing Operations</h3>
<p>
OperationDefinitions with <code>kind = operation</code> are executed as defined in the <a href="operations.html">Operations Framework</a>.
</p>

<a name="equeries"></a>
<h3>Executing Named Queries</h3>
<p>
Named queries (OperationDefinitions with <code>kind = query</code>) are executed by performing a <a href="search.html">search</a> 
with the value of the search parameter "_query" set to the name provided in the definition. 
Named queries are a kind of search: both client and server must conform to all the requirements of search, 
including regarding the content of the result bundle. From a client's perspective, it's really just a kind 
of search, though it may have a completely separate processing pipeline.
Named queries cannot be invoked using the $[operationname] mechanism.
</p>
<p>
If the named query is to be performed over the RESTful API, all the parameters must be simple search parameters,
so that they can be represented directly in the URL without tricky encoding issues. Named queries 
always have a single output parameter named "result" of type Bundle.
</p>
<p>
The order of parameters doesn't matter; a <code>_query</code> parameter anywhere in the query means the entire query will be handled 
according to the named query OperationDefinition. Parameters may repeat if permitted by the OperationDefinition 
(or for unlisted common search parameters, as specified in this specification).
</p>
<p>
For named queries, all the standard search parameters are automatically in scope. Specifically, all common search parameters 
(e.g. _id, _text, _count, _sort, etc.) as well as search parameters that pertain to the resources 
returned by the operation (e.g. name for Patient or Organization) are allowed. "In scope" doesn't 
mean all servers will support them. If a server wishes to declare which search parameters it supports 
for a given named query, it must explicitly list these in its OperationDefinition (which might be a 
server-specific derived OperationDefinition).
</p>

<a name="passing"></a>
<h3>Passing Resources to Operations</h3> 

<p>
There are two ways to pass resources to an operation: directly or by reference.
The definition of an operation distinguishes between these two, since they have very different behaviors and consequences.
</p>
<p>
As an example, take the <a href="valueset-operation-expand.html">ValueSet.$expand operation</a>.  
This operation takes a valueset as a direct parameter. The type of the parameter is 
defined as 'ValueSet'. In a <a href="parameters.html">Parameters</a> resource, it would be represented like this:
</p>
<pre class="xml">
  &lt;parameter&gt;
    &lt;name value=&quot;valueset&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;resource&gt;
      &lt;ValueSet&gt;
        &lt;!-- ValueSet contents --&gt;
      &lt;/ValueSet&gt;
    &lt;/resource&gt;
  &lt;/parameter&gt; 
</pre>
<p>
or, in JSON:
</p>
<pre>
 "parameter": [
    {
      "name": "valueset",
      "resource": {
        "resourceType": "ValueSet",
        // ValueSet contents 
      }
    }
  ]
</pre>

<p>
Other parameters are passed by reference. For example, the <a href="chargeitemdefinition-operation-apply.html">ChargeItemDefinition.$apply operation</a> 
takes two parameters of type Reference - one to the chargeItem and the other to the account.  The type of the 
parameters is <code>Reference(Charge)</code> and <code>Reference(Account)</code>, respectively.  The expectation is that the server performing the 
operation will resolve those references as part of the operation execution.
In a parameters resource, the chargeItem parameter would be represented like this: 
</p>
<pre class="xml">
  &lt;parameter&gt;
    &lt;name value=&quot;chargeItem&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;valueReference&gt;
      &lt;reference value="ChargeItem/123"/&gt;
    &lt;/valueReference&gt;
  &lt;/parameter&gt; 
</pre>
<p>
or, in JSON:
</p>
<pre>
 "parameter": [
    {
      "name": "chargeItem",
      "valueReference" : {
        "reference" : "ChargeItem/123"
      }
    }
  ]
</pre>

<p>
Some operations can take either form; in that case, two distinct parameters
must be defined: one for a resource as a direct parameter, and one for a reference.
</p>

<a name="system"></a>
<h3>Determining System Compatibility</h3>

<p>
A client can determine the compatibility of the server by processing its capability
statement and ensuring that the server implements the specific operation definitions and parameters required by the client. The client can then report a useful error to the user rather than allowing mystifying operational errors to occur.
</p>
<p>
However, there are fundamental limitations to this approach because 
there are many aspects of these operations that are not (or cannot be) defined 
in a formal fashion using OperationDefinition, for example, co-occurrence constraints among parameters.
</p>
<p>
In the same sense, a 3rd party tool can examine a server's CapabilityStatement and a client's definition of an acceptable server to determine whether
those two system are interoperable or not.
</p>

<a name="forms"></a>
<h3>Dynamically Generating Forms</h3>

<p>
Finally, it is possible to generate user interface forms automatically from 
the OperationDefinition. The documentation in the <code>OperationDefinition.description</code> 
and <code>OperationDefinition.parameter.documentation</code> should be sufficient to allow
moderately technical users to guess at the correct content of the form.
For this reason, highly technical documentation should go in <code>OperationDefinition.comment</code>.
</p>
<p>
It is anticipated that this would be used to automate development processes, rather than to generate end-user forms: such users will usually need more support than can be offered in a generated form.
</p>

<a name="defined"></a>
<h3>Operations defined as part of this Specification</h3>

<%operationslist%>


</div>
