<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="scope"></a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p style="border:2px; border-style:solid; border-color:#999999; padding: 1em; border-radius: 4px 4px 4px 4px;"><b><i>For an overview of this resource and others in the Medication Definition domain, also see the <a href="medication-definition-module.html">module page</a></i></b></p>
		<p>
			ManufacturedItemDefinition is to be used when you need to describe an actual physical medication item such as a tablet or capsule. 
			This is typically for regulatory or manufacturing use cases, rather than day to day prescribing or dispensing.
		</p>
		<p>
			This resource represents (for example) a single physical tablet. It can also represent physical liquids, powders, capsules etc. 
			When prescribing, it is not usually necessary to represent the physical properties of the tablet that the patient will eventually receive and consume.
			Prescriptions make statements about types of products or substances, in general terms or more specific, which may be fulfilled by tablets (in some cases) 
			but usually without directly talking about the details of those tablets. 
			It is not usual to prescribe a red tablet with an "X" on it, so it is clear that this resource is not needed for the prescribing workflow itself.
			However it may be useful during a patient consultation (or perhaps in response to an adverse event), 
			to look up which tablet is the red triangle with an "X" imprint. These definitional facts can be captured with this resource. 
			They would likely never be on a prescription, but this resource supports the prescribing process as well as other downstream events.
			The weights, sizes, chemical properties and so on are naturally important to manufacturers, distributors, and regulators - who need every property detailing.
		</p>
		<p>
			A defining aspect of this resource is that the item described is in the state as it comes from being manufactured, 
			and has had no other preparatory steps - such as crushing or mixing. 
			It is in the state ready for packaging and distribution to consumers, 
			and not necessarily in the state ready for administration (for which see AdministrableProductDefinition).
			This is the state where medication items are commonly encountered, within packaging, before actually being used. 
			It is a medication item "as manufactured", recognizing that other non-medication items are also manufactured, 
			and that even the administrable form of a drug, and the packaging that an item is placed into, have been manufactured at some stage.
		</p>
		<p>
			The manufactured item describes the physical characteristics of the item, as opposed to its pharmaceutical aspects 
			(which may only apply after mixing with other items - to become an AdministrableProductDefinition), 
			or its packaging, or legal aspects (which apply only to the whole group of packing and manufactured items). 
			There are typically multiple instances of the item in the packaging (a PackagedProductDefinition resource) 
			and this is indicated by the quantity within the containing package (e.g. 12 tablets), referencing a single copy of the manufactured item.
		</p>
		<p>
			This is the only resource that treats the "tablet" (or whatever it may be) as a physical object.
			It is still definitional however - it describes all instances of this tablet.
			The resource aims to capture the definition of a single medication item type, such as a tablet of aspirin with a certain form, shape, manufacturer. 
			It is not intended to describe and be instantiated for each medication item, i.e. it is not an actual real instance of a tablet, 
			but rather represents (e.g.) all tablets of the same medication item type, that are described by the ManufacturedItemDefinition.
		</p>
		<p>
			To define several package variations, e.g. pack of 10 tablets and of 50 tablets, you would need only one ManufacturedItemDefinition, 
			referenced from both (and associated with a numeric quantity of 10 or 50 in the respective PackagedProductDefintions).
			To prescribe or dispense 100 tablets, you would not generally need this resource at all, 
			because usually the code of the medication product as a whole is sufficient, plus a quantity, e.g. 100 of "ABC123" (meaning e.g. aspirin 75 mg).
		</p>
		<p>
			This resource excludes devices and other items found in medication packaging such as scissors, 
			applicators and so on (which would use DeviceDefinition), and components of packaging that are not considered devices, 
			such bottle stoppers (use PackagedProductDefintion.package.package).
		</p>
	</div>
</div>
