<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
    These protocols (colorectal cancer and prostate-radical prostatectomy) are likely to be change to suit implementation when that occurs in H2 2016.  
    These protocols are being developed for trial implementation at selected sites are are not yet suitable for wider consumption.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
TODO
</p>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
    The Royal College of Pathologists of Australasia (RCPA) has a number of projects running as part of the Pathology Information, Terminology and Units Standardisation (PITUS-15-16) Project.
    One of these projects (working group 5) is concerned with report modelling and in particular the development of structured cancer protocols.
    Two structured cancer protocols (https://www.rcpa.edu.au/Library/Practising-Pathology/Structured-Pathology-Reporting-of-Cancer/Cancer-Protocols) 
    ie colorectal cancer and prostate cancer (radical prostatectomy), were chosen to pilot the development of FHIR artefacts. 
    It is envisaged these FHIR artefacts will be used in some example colorectal and prostate cancer (radical prostatectomy) pathology reports from public and private pathology providers. 
    These trial reports will be sent to and consumed by selected cancer registries. 
    It is envisaged this pilot project will determine a way forward for greater adoption of the use of structured cancer reporting and in particular the use of FHIR to facilitate this change.
    These preliminary cnacer protocols (colorectal and prostate-radical prostatectomy) require further development of the terminology valuesets ie the next release (Sep 2016) of 
    SNOMED CT-AU is expected to have more of the required result values.
</p>
</div>

</div>
