<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource covers the administration of all medications.  Please refer to the <a href="immunization.html">Immunization</a> resource/Profile for the treatment of vaccines.
It will principally be used within care settings (including inpatient) to record medication administrations, including self-administrations of oral medications, injections, intravenous infusions, etc.  It can also be used in outpatient settings to record allergy shots and other non-immunization administrations.  In some
cases, it might be used for home-health reporting, such as recording self-administered or even device-administered insulin. 
</p>
    <p>Note:  devices coated with a medication (e.g. heparin) are not typically recorded as a medication administration.  However, administration of a medication via an implanted medication pump (e.g., insulin) would be recorded as a MedicationAdministration.</p>
    <p>MedicationAdministration is an event resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html#event"> Workflow Event </a>
    </p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
<b>The Medication domain includes a number of related resources</b>
</p>
<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="2" frame="box">
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationrequest.html">MedicationRequest</a></td>
        <td>An order for both supply of the medication and the instructions for administration of the medicine to a patient.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationdispense.html">MedicationDispense</a></td>
        <td>Provision of a supply of a medication with the intention that it is subsequently consumed by a patient (usually in response to a prescription).  </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationadministration.html">MedicationAdministration</a></td>
        <td>When a patient actually consumes a medicine, or it is otherwise administered to them.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td><a href="medicationusage.html">MedicationUsage</a></td>
        <td>This is a record of a medication being taken by a patient or that a medication has been given to a patient, where the record is the result of a report from the patient or another clinician. 
          A medication statement is not a part of the prescribe->dispense->administer sequence but is a report that such a sequence (or at least a part of it) did take place, resulting in a belief that the patient has received a particular medication.
        </td>
    </tr>
</table>
<p>
<b>MedicationAdministration</b> is intended for tracking the administration of medications.  Administration of vaccines is intended to be handled using the <a href="immunization.html">Immunization</a> resource.    Some systems treat immunizations in the same way as any other medication administration.  Such systems SHOULD use an immunization resource to represent these.  However, if systems need to use a <b>MedicationAdministration</b> resource to capture vaccinations for workflow or other reasons, a Medication Administration resource may be used but systems SHOULD also create and expose an equivalent <a href="immunization.html">Immunization</a> instance.
</p>
</div>

</div>
