<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->
<a name="examplecodes"></a>
<h3>Example Codes</h3>
<p>Genomic Study resource uses many example codes for terminology binding. Reviewers and implementers are strongly encouraged to provide their comments and feedback about the example codes for terminology binding purposes.</p>
<p>Below the attributes of provided example bindings are listed. Links are included to indicate where the example codes from were pulled from.</p>
<h4>GenomicStudy.type</h4>
<p>The type example codes were based on discussions by Clinical Genomics Workgroup.
</p>
<h4>GenomicStudy.analysis.methodType</h4>
<p>The method type example codes were pulled from <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gtr/">National Library of Medicine-Genetic Testing Registry (NCBI-GTR)</a> values of describing different testing methods on various levels: <a href="https://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/GTR/standard_terms/Major_method_category.txt">major method category</a>, <a href="https://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/GTR/standard_terms/Method_category.txt">method category</a>, and <a href="https://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/GTR/standard_terms/Primary_test_methodology.txt">primary methodology</a>.
</p>
<h4>GenomicStudy.analysis.input.type and GenomicStudy.analysis.output.type</h4>
<p>The input and output type example codes were pulled from <a href="https://software.broadinstitute.org/software/igv/FileFormats">Integrative Genomics Viewer Documentation</a> by Broad Institute.
</p>
<h4>GenomicStudy.analysis.changeType</h4>
<p>The change type example codes were based on discussions by Clinical Genomics Workgroup.
</p>
<a name="notes"></a>
<h3>Implementation Notes</h3>
<p>
</p>

<a name="use-case"></a>
<h3>Use Case</h3>
<p>GenomicStudy.subject and GenomicStudy.analysis.subject can reference a lot of resource types besides Patient such as Group, BiologicallyDerivedProduct, or Substance. In addition, it can provide more details about involved genomic files as inputs or outputs. These various options allow the GenomicStudy resource to cover many use cases besides direct patient care, e.g., research studies that involve multiple patients or environmental samples. Through the following subsections, some of these use cases are described.
</p>
<h4>Trio studies</h4>
<p>Trio studies involve a proband and two more subjects such as proband’s mother and father for a de novo mutation detection study. GenomicStudy would list the proband as GenomicStudy.subject because it is the main subject of the study. While each of the study participants, i.e., proband, mother, and father, may have their own individual GenomicStudy.analysis.
</p>
<p>GenomicStudy.analysis.input lists various files that may be used for each individual analysis, their types, and their generation context. GenomicStudy.analysis.input.file elements may link these files to DocumentReference resources that provides more details about each individual files. One of the main details is the subject of a file. If a file is linked to a specific patient, the corresponding DocumentReference.subject may reference this Patient Resource. If the file contains data from multiple persons, the corresponding DocumentReference.subject may reference a Group resource that lists these persons, and their relationship to each other if available.
</p>

<h4>Somatic mutation detection studies</h4>
<p>Somatic mutation studies may use multiple samples from the patient to support mutation detection, e.g., tumor-normal sample pair. GenomicStudy.analysis may describe conducted analyses per each sample, where GenomicStudy.analysis.specimen elements may provide more details about each individual element. In addition GenomicStudy.analysis.input can list relevant input files, where the DocumentReference provide by GenomicStudy.analysis.input.file can list the specific specimen this input file is related to using DocumentReference.subject as a Specimen resource instance.
</p>

<a name="ehr-usecase"></a>
<h4>EHR access to genomic studies</h4>
<p>
</p>
</div>
