<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
GenomicStudy resource aims at delineating relevant information of a genomic study. A genomic study might comprise one or more analyses, each serve a specific purpose.  These analyses may vary in method (e.g., karyotyping, CNV, or SNV detection), performer, or devices used.  The assays in a genomic study may vary in region studied, specimen, or even subject.
</p>
<p>
GenomicStudy describes relevant information including the reasons, purpose, and performers of the study. It also provides technical endpoints to access these data. It could be a logical aggregator for complex genomic analyses.
</p>
<p>
A genomic study might be based on one or more service requests or care plans. The reasons for performing a genomic study might be driven by specific <a href="condition.html">Conditions</a> or <a href="observation.html">Observations</a>. Although the genomic study subject is the focus of the study, the assay-level subject could be used to specify other relevant subjects. For example, trio testing may involve three subjects: the proband, and both parents. The proband would be the subject listed directly under the genomic study, while each of the analyses could represent proband, mother, and father genomic assays.
</p>
<p>
In clinical use, the study interpreters use all the results of these various analyses to provide diagnostic and therapeutic insights for the patient. Where performers are listed according to their participation in each genomic analysis and included assays. Each analysis may base on a set of defined protocols that may differ from the performed protocols.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
A main function of GenomicStudy is to provide additional metadata for one or more clinical genomic analysis pipelines where <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> instances are used to track inputs and outputs of those pipelines. Device is used to represent both hardware and software used in the sequencing and in the analyses.
</p>
<p>
It is intended that this resource be referenced by <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> and <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReference</a> similarly to how ImagingStudy is currently referenced on those resources. Of note, the results of the study would be captured in Observations and referenced on a DiagnosticReport.
</p>
<p>
Important contextual references include Patient, Specimen, Encounter, ServiceRequest, Practitioner, and Organization.
</p>
<p>
<a href="observation.html">Observation</a> or <a href="condition.html">Condition</a> instances may also be referenced from genomic study to designate a given reason for performing the study
</p>
<p>
GenomicStudy can support the event-definition workflow pattern by referencing PlanDefinition(s) via the instantiatesCanonical relationship when implementers wish to describe more specifics of the pipelines and devices used in the analysis.
</p>
</div>
</div>
