<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
GenomicStudy resource aims at delineating relevant information of a genomic study. A genomic study might comprise one or more analyses, each serve a specific purpose.  These analyses may vary in method (e.g., karyotyping, CNV, or SNV detection), performer, or devices used.  The assays in a genomic study may vary in region studied, specimen, or even subject.
</p>
<p>
GenomicStudy describes relevant information including the reasons, purpose, and performers of the study. It also provides technical endpoints to access these data. It could be a logical aggregator for complex genomic analyses.
</p>
<p>
A genomic study might be based on one or more service requests or care plans. The reasons for performing a genomic study might be driven by specific <a href="condition.html">Conditions</a> or <a href="observation.html">Observations</a>. Although the genomic study subject is the focus of the study, the assay-level subject could be used to specify other relevant subjects. For example, trio testing may involve three subjects: the proband, and both parents. The proband would be the subject listed directly under the genomic study, while each of the analyses could represent proband, mother, and father genomic assays.
</p>
<p>
In clinical use, the study interpreters use all the results of these various analyses to provide diagnostic and therapeutic insights for the patient. Where performers are listed according to their participation in each genomic analysis and included assays. Each analysis may base on a set of defined protocols that may differ from the performed protocols.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p> 
GenomicStudy is used for genomic relevant information where result files are represented as <a href="documentreference.html">DocumentReferences</a> that include relevant metadata in addition to links to actual files or as attachments.
</p>
<p>
This resource could be referenced by Genomic Diagnostic Report or genomic observations, e.g., Variant, or Genotype.
</p>
</div>
</div>
