<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

[%stu-note dstu%]
This resource is still undergoing development and review by the appropriate Workgroups. At this time, is considered only as a draft resource not suitable for production implementation.
[%end-note%]

<p>
Different resources have different ways to handle “physical instances”
</p>
<ul>
	<li>Lack of clear support and guidance for instance has caused traceability to be a problem in implementations: Standards-guided implementations do not consider “instances” or do so inconsistently.</li>
	<li>In border cases (medication containing devices), this can cause issues.
</li>
	<li>Inconsistency can also require extensions and further divergence. E.g. for adopting the EU Serialization directive, need to add “serial number” to the medication. What and where is that extension?
</li>
</ul>

 <p>
 If the resources that represent physical entities were split into a "kind" resource and an "instance" resource, this resource would represent the instance that would be referenced by the "kind" resource. For example,  Device would be split into Device ( representing the kind or type of Device ) + ItemInstance ( representing the instance of  a Device ).

</p>
<p>Resources impacted:</p>
<ul>
	<li>Substance</li>
	<li>Medication</li>
	<li>Device</li>
</ul>



</div>

<!-- (recommended):
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Explains how this resource relates to others. Particularly important is to differentiate between appropriate usages for related resources when an implementer might be confused about what to reference when.
</p>
</div>
-->

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->

</div>
