<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

	<div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
			Schedule resources provide a container for time-slots that can be booked using an appointment,
			It provides the window of time (period) that slots are defined for and what type of appointments can be booked.<br/>
			The schedule does not provide any information about actual appointments. This seperation also greatly assists where
			access to the appointments would not be permitted for security or privacy reasons, and still being able
			to determine if an appointment might be available.
		</p>
    <p>
      Note: A schedule is not used for the delivery of medication, that is the <a href="datatypes.html#Timing">Timing</a> datatype.
    </p>

		<h3>
			Context
		</h3>
    <p>
      A schedule controls the dates and times available for the performance of a service
      and/or the use of a resource.  One schedule applies to one service or resource, since
      each service or resource can be reserved independently of the others.<br/>
      (If two or more services, people, locations, or things cannot be reserved independently
      of one another, they are considered to be one activity or resource.)
    </p>
    <p>
      A schedule consists of slots of time during which the controlled service or resource is potentially available
			for provision or use.  Slots are categorized as open, booked, or blocked.  An open slot
			on a schedule indicates that the service or resource is available for provision or use
			during that period of time.  A booked slot indicates that the service or resource is not
			available during the time period, because an appointment has been scheduled.  A blocked
			slot indicates that a service or resource is unavailable for reasons other than a scheduled
			appointment.
		</p>
		<p>
			The real-world, non-automated analog of the schedule described above is a standard
			appointment book.  These books are generally organized with rows of time slots, during
			which a service or resource is available.
		</p>
		<p>
			A slot is one unit on a schedule.  A slot represents the smallest unit of time or quantity
			that a service or resource may be booked.  Depending on the nature of the service or
			resource, there may be more than one defined slot at a given instant of time.
			For example, if a service is an open group therapy session with twelve available seats,
			then there are twelve slots for the given block of time.
		</p>

		<h3>Actor - What the schedule applies to</h3>
		<p>
			The schedule belongs to a single owner, the actor. This is normally a HealthcareService, Practitioner, Location
			or Device. When booking an appoitment, multiple schedules may need to be checked depending on the configuration
			of the system.
		</p>
		<p>
			If an appointment has 2 practitioners, a specific medical device and a room then there could be a schedule for
			each of these resources that may need to be consulted to ensure that no collisions occur.<br/>
			If the schedule needed to be consulted, then there would be one created covering the planning horizon for the
			time of the appointment.
		</p>

		<h3>Checking availability - Searching</h3>
		<p>
			When checking availability for an appointment, the creator of the appointment should check
			that the see what schedules are applicable, then check for available slots within these schedules.
		</p>
		<p>
			The searching could be done via the properties of the referenced actors, such as the ServiceCategory
			on the HealthcareService, or the Address on a Location.
		</p>
		<p>
			The type property can be used to filter the types of appointments that can be booked within the appointment.
			These can be filtered down further by specifying types on the slots too.<br/>
			The terminology bound to this property will be the same as that used on appointment and slot too.
		</p>
		<p>
			If all slots are busy, the caller could find some slots that they believe are close enough, and request
			for the appointment in these slot(s)<br/>
			(the appointment may be given a higher precedence and allocated in an overbooked status if business rules permit)
		</p>
	</div>
</div>
