<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<a name="bnc"> </a>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>
SpecimenDefinition will define a kind of specimen, which can be associated with in vitro diagnostic procedures described in a catalog of orderable services. SpecimenDefinition describes the kind of specimen to be collected from the subject of these procedures as well as the requirements applying to the collection activity, the preparation of the subject for this collection. This resource also describes the associated type(s) of specimen conditioned for testing, which are the output of the specimen collection activity. A specimen conditioned for testing is described with the type(s) of container and possible additive to be used, the minimal and normal volumes of collection, the conditions of storage, transportation and handling for the specimen once collected and conditioned. This resource is a necessary building block of a sharable catalog of orderable in vitro diagnostic services. The subjects of these orderable services may be human patients, non-human living subjects or non-living materials such as water, surfaces, medical devices, etc.. All sub-specialties of clinical and anatomic pathology laboratories are concerned, as well as all care services prone to order in vitro diagnostic services to those laboratories. A catalog of orderable services generally belongs to a specific laboratory or facility. Nonetheless, the data items used to build this catalog are of universal meaning and interest.
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
		</p>
	</div>
	<div>
		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
		<p>
This resource relates to these other resources:		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>The SpecimenDefinition resource is referenced by the Catalog resource, which represents a whole catalog, to enable the creation and maintenance of kinds of specimens within a catalog of orderable diagnostic services.
</li>
			<li>The SpecimenDefinition resource references the SubstanceDefinition resource, in order to describe the type of substance (body fluid, other material) concerned by a kind of specimen. It also references the SubstanceDefinition resource to describe additives to be used in the production of specimens of some kind.
</li>
		</ul>
	</div>
	<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->
</div>
