<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    
    <div>
        <a name="bnc"/>
        <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
        <strong>Note that this content is preliminary and has not yet undergone proper review by the
            appropriate Workgroups. </strong>
        <p> The OccupationalData (i.e., Occupational Data for Health, ODH) FHIR resource covers information about a
            patient's work or a patient's family member's work. ODH is designed for the social
            history section of a medical record, to facilitate clinical care in most, if not all disciplines
            and delivery environments. ODH also can be used to support public health reporting,
            population health activities, clinical decision support, and similar value-based care.
            ODH is not designed to support billing activities. The scope of the work information
            includes: </p>
        <ul>
            <li>Subject (patient or related person)</li>
            <li>Employment Status</li>
            <li>Retirement Date(s)</li>
            <li>Combat Zone Period</li>
            <li>Usual Work, which includes:<ul>
                    <li>Usual Occupation</li>
                    <li>Usual Industry</li>
                    <li>Start Date</li>
                    <li>Duration</li>
                </ul></li>
            <li>Past or Present Job, which includes:<ul>
                    <li>Past or Present Occupation</li>
                    <li>Past or Present Industry</li>
                    <li>Work Classification</li>
                    <li>Work Schedule, with:<ul>
                            <li>Weekly Work Days</li>
                            <li>Daily Work Hours</li>
                        </ul></li>
                    <li>Job Duty</li>
                    <li>Occupational Hazards</li>
                    <li>Employer Details (e.g., name, address)</li>
                </ul></li>
        </ul>
        <p> This resource is expected to be implemented by clinical systems of all settings. Since a
            likely mechanism for collecting work information would be by patient data entry, the
            resource may be implemented by Personal Health Record systems. Systems supporting
            quality metrics and population health may also implement this resource. </p>
        <!--<p> Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. </p>-->
        <p>Example Scenarios</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Diabetes management affected by rotating shift</li>
            <li>Population prevention and testing activities due to potential for increased
                substance exposure or take-home exposure (e.g., lead) associated with occupation
                (e.g., house painter)</li>
            <li>Stress factors associated with retirement status</li>
            <li>Long shifts with safety sensitive work</li>
            <li>Recognition of asthma related to the workplace environment</li>
            <li>Recognition of cancer related to exposure to an occupational hazard during a
                previous job</li>
        </ul>
    </div>

    <!-- (recommended): -->
    <div>
        <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
        <p> This resource is expected to be referenced within FHIR profiles to incorporate patient's
            work information. Such profiles may include those related to: </p>
        <ul>
            <li>Quality measures</li>
            <li>Public health reporting (e.g., vital records, cancer, case reporting)</li>
            <li>Encounter summaries</li>
        </ul>
        <p> This resource refers to the following other resources: </p>
        <ul>
            <li>The Observation Resource for the actual observations</li>
            <li>The RelatedPerson Resource for work or occupations related to the patient's
                family</li>
            <li>The Organization Resource for Employer name and address information</li>
            <li>The Author extension for documentation of the person that recorded the patient's
                work information </li>
        </ul>
    </div>
    <!-- -->

    <!-- (optional): -->
    <div>
        <h2>Background and Context</h2>
        <p> The majority of adults in the U.S. spend more than half their waking hours at work.
            Therefore health and work are inextricably inter-related. For example, the management of
            chronic conditions requires taking the patient's work environment into consideration.
            Furthermore, the recognition of new conditions related to previously unknown workplace
            hazards has often come from astute clinicians, which requires knowledge of the patient's
            work setting. ONC has indicated recognition of the value of work information for health
            care.</p>
    </div>
    <!-- -->

</div>
