<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<p>CarePlan is one of the <a href="workflow.html#request">request</a> resources in the FHIR <a href="workflow.html">workflow</a> specification.</p>

<p> 
Care Plans are used in many areas of healthcare with a variety of scopes.
They can be as simple as a general practitioner keeping track of when their 
patient is next due for a tetanus immunization through to a detailed plan for
an oncology patient covering diet, chemotherapy, radiation, lab work and
counseling with detailed timing relationships, pre-conditions and goals. They may
be used in veterinary care or clinical research to describe the care of a herd or
other collection of animals.  In public health, they may describe education or
immunization campaigns.
</p>
<p>
This resource takes an intermediate approach to complexity.  It captures basic details about
who is involved and what actions are intended without dealing in discrete data
about dependencies and timing relationships.  These can be supported where
necessary using the extension mechanism.
</p>
<p>
The scope of care plans may vary widely.  Examples include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Multi-disciplinary cross-organizational care plans; e.g. An oncology plan including the 
oncologist, home nursing staff, pharmacy and others
</li>
<li>
Plans to manage specific disease/condition(s) (e.g. nutritional plan for a patient post bowel 
resection, neurological plan post head injury, pre-natal plan, post-partum plan, grief management 
plan, etc..)
</li>
<li>
Decision support generated plans following specific practice guidelines (e.g. stroke care plan, 
diabetes plan, falls prevention, etc..)
</li>
<li>
Self-maintained patient or care-giver authored plans identifying their goals and an integrated understanding of actions to be taken.  This does not include the legal Advance Directives, which should be represented with either the Consent resource with Consent.category = Advance Directive or with a specific request resource with intent = directive.  Informal advance directives could be represented as a Goal, such as "I want to die at home."
</li>
</ul>
<p>
This resource can be used to represent both proposed plans (for example, recommendations from
a decision support engine or returned as part of a consult report) as well as active plans.  The
nature of the plan is communicated by the status.  Some systems may need to filter CarePlans to ensure
that only appropriate plans are exposed via a given user interface.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
CarePlan activities can be defined using references
to the various "request" resources.  These references could be to resources with a status of
"planned" or to an active order.  It is possible for planned activities to exist (e.g. appointments)
without needing a CarePlan at all.  CarePlans are used when there's a need to group activities,
goals and/or participants together to provide some degree of context.
</p>
<p>
CarePlans can be tied to specific <a href="condition.html">Conditions</a>, however they can also be 
condition-independent and instead focused on a particular type of care (e.g. psychological, nutritional)
or the care delivered by a particular practitioner or group of practitioners.
</p>
<p>
An <a href="immunizationrecommendation.html">ImmunizationRecommendation</a> can be interpreted as a narrow
type of CarePlan dealing only with immunization events.  Where such information could appear in either
resource, the immunization-specific resource is preferred.
</p>
<p>
CarePlans represent a specific plan instance for a particular patient or group.  It is not intended to be used to define generic plans or protocols that are independent of a
specific individual or group.  CarePlan represents a specific intent, not a general definition.  Protocols and order sets are supported through <a href="plandefinition.html">PlanDefinition</a>.
</p>
</div>

</div>
