<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The PaymentReconciliation resource provides the bulk payment details 
associated with a payment by the payor for receivable amounts, such as for goods and services rendered by a provider to patients 
covered by insurance plans offered by that payor. These are the payment reconciliation details which may
align to the individual payment amounts indicated on discrete <a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponses</a> or <a href="invoice.html">Invoices</a> for example.
</p>
<p>
Bulk payments need to provide a means to associate the amounts paid against specific Claims, Invoices, 
and other financial exchanges and adjustments, to the bulk payment itself in order to reconcile
 accounts receivable.
</p>
<p>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
</p>


		<p>The PaymentReconciliation resource is a "event" resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html#event">Workflow Event.</a></p>

<h3>Additional Information</h3>
<p>
Additional information regarding electronic payment notice content and usage may be found at:
</p>		
<ul>
<li><a href="financial-module.html#resource-status">Financial Resource Status Lifecycle</a>: how .status is used in the financial resources.</li>
</ul>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
	The PaymentReconciliation resource serves to correlate a payment amount to the adjudicated claim amounts appearing on one or more <a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponses</a>. PaymentReconciliation provides the bulk payment details 
associated with a payment by the payor for goods and services rendered by a provider to patients 
covered by insurance plans offered by that payor.
</p>

<p>
	The <a href="paymentnotice.html">PaymentNotice</a> resource is used to indicate that a payment has, or is about to occur. The resource is used commonly when tracking of payment occurences is required for regulatory or business purposes. 
</p>

<p>
The <a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponse</a> resource is an insurer's adjudication and/or authorization of a set of healthcare-related goods and services for a patient against the patient's insurance coverages and does not indicate that payment has occured.
</p>

<p>
	For reporting out to patients or transferring data to patient centered applications, such as patient health Record (PHR) application, the <a href="explanationofbenefit.html">ExplanationOfBenefit</a> 
	should be used instead.
</p>

		<p>
			<b>The eClaim domain includes a number of related resources</b>
		</p>
		<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="2" frame="box">
			<tr>
				<td>PaymentReconciliation</td>
				<td>Provides the bulk payment details 
associated with a payment by the payor for goods and services rendered by a provider to patients 
covered by insurance plans offered by that payor.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponse</a></td>
				<td>A payor's adjudication and/or authorization response to the suite of services provided in a Claim. Typically the ClaimResponse references the Claim but does not duplicate
		the clinical or financial information provided in the claim.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><a href="explanationofbenefit.html">ExplanationOfBenefit</a></td>
				<td>This resource combines the information from the Claim and the ClaimResponse, stripping out any provider or payor proprietary information, into a unified information model 
		suitable for use for: patient reporting; transferring information to a Patient Health Record system; and, supporting complete claim and adjudication information exchange
 with regulatory and analytics organizations and other parts of the provider's organization.
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><a href="paymentnotice.html">PaymentNotice</a></td>
				<td>An indication that a payment has occured, is about to occur, or has been cancelled.</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->


</div>
