<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Representing Medication in the majority of healthcare settings is a matter of identifying an item from a list and then conveying a reference 
for the item selected either into a patient related resource or to other applications.  Additional information about the medication is frequently 
provided for human verification but a full representation of the details of composition and efficacy of the medicine is conveyed by referring
to drug dictionaries by means of the codes they define. There are some occasions where it is necessary to identify slightly more detail, such
as when dispensing a package containing a particular medicine requires identification both of the medicine and the package at once.  
There are also some occasions (e.g. custom formulations) where the composition of a medicine must be represented.  
In these cases the ingredients of the medicine have to be specified together with the amount contained, though the medication resource 
does not provide full details.
</p>
<p>
The medication resource allows for medications to be characterised as either a product or a package; this classification is important 
because it affects the interpretation of a prescribed amount. For instance, is the prescribed amount 20 tablets, or 20 packages of
50 tablets each? However the <i>kind</i> element is not required because not all contexts of use are involved with prescription (medication
statements, for instance). Typically, however, profiles describing the use of the medication resource in a prescribing environment 
will make the <i>kind</i> element required. 
</p>
<p>
Depending on whether the medication is a product or a package, further details about the composition can be provided. A product
has a form (tablet, suspension, etc.) and a list of ingredients with quantities. The ingredients may be other medications or 
substances. A package has a container (vacuum packed box, jar, etc.) and a list of the products or other packages that are in the package.
</p>
</div>    
    
</div>
