<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The PaymentNotice resource indicates the resource for which the payment has been indicated and 
reports the current status information of that payment. The payment notice may be used by providers and payers 
to advise the provider or regulatory bodies of the state of a payment (check in the mail/EFT sent, 
payment cashed, payment canceled)for example to provide payment status information or to document the forwarding or receipt of payment to support regulatory
requirements. Employers or Insurance Exchanges may also use this to advise payers of premium payment.
</p>
<p>
Payers and/or providers may have the need to advise providers and/or regulators of the status of claim settlement and payment completion. 
This same resource may be used by employers and insurance exchanges to advise payers that premium payments have been 
issued and settled.
</p>
<p>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
</p>

		<p>The PaymentNotice resource is a "event" resource from a FHIR workflow perspective - see <a href="workflow.html#event">Workflow Event.</a></p>

<h3>Additional Information</h3>
<p>
Additional information regarding electronic payment notice content and usage may be found at:
</p>		
<ul>
<li><a href="financial-module.html#resource-status">Financial Resource Status Lifecycle</a>: how .status is used in the financial resources.</li>
<li><a href="financial-module.html#batch">Batches</a>: how eClaims may handle batches of eligibility, claims, payments and responses.</li>
</ul>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
	The PaymentNotice resource is used to indicate that a payment has been initiated. The resource is used commonly when tracking of payment occurences is required for regulatory or business purposes, such as ensuring that payment of claim adjudications occurs within a specific timeframe. The PaymentNotice is not used to report adjudicated amounts (see <a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponse</a>) or to reconcile adjudicated amounts against actual payment (see <a href="paymentreconciliation.html">PaymentReconciliation</a>) 
</p>

<p>
The <a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponse</a> resource is an insurer's adjudication and/or authorization of a set of healthcare-related goods and services for a patient against the patient's insurance coverages and does not indicate that payment has occured.
</p>

<p>
	The <a href="paymentreconciliation.html">PaymentReconciliation</a> resource serves to correlate payment amounts to the adjudicated claim amounts appearing on one or more <a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponses</a>.
</p>

		<p>
			<b>The eClaim domain includes a number of related resources</b>
		</p>
		<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="2" frame="box">
			<tr>
				<td>PaymentNotice</td>
				<td>An indication that a payment has been initiated or has been cancelled.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><a href="claimresponse.html">ClaimResponse</a></td>
				<td>A payor's adjudication and/or authorization response to the suite of services provided in a Claim. Typically the ClaimResponse references the Claim but does not duplicate
		the clinical or financial information provided in the claim.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td><a href="paymentreconciliation.html">PaymentReconciliation</a></td>
				<td>Provides the bulk payment details 
associated with a payment by the payor for goods and services rendered by a provider to patients 
covered by insurance plans offered by that payor.</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
</div>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->


</div>
