<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <a name="usage"></a>
  <h2>Usage</h2>
  <p>
    The RequestGroup resource is used when there are temporal, co-occurrence or other dependencies between
    one or more steps of an overall workflow.  For example, "do procedure A or procedure B, but not both" or
    "do procedure A after procedure B" or "Act on this ServiceRequest, then use the value of that observation in
    the calculation of the dose of this subsequent MedicationRequest".  RequestGroups that define actions
    (i.e. that are more than just narrative representations) will always reference other Request resources with
    an <code>intent</code> of "option".
  </p>
  <p>
    Each "option" request can only be interpreted in the context of a RequestGroup that references it.  This is
    because the RequestGroup defines the context in which the option request may/should/must occur, including
    any triggers, timing constraints, choices, sequencing requirements, etc.  Typically such "option" requests
    will be <a href="references.html#contained">contained</a> resources due to this dependency.  However, in some
    cases "option" requests may be stand-alone if they are immutable or tightly tied to a 
    <a href="activitydefinition.html">ActivityDefinition</a> such that the option resources can safely be referenced
    without a risk of their content/intent changing
  </p>
  <p>
    Elements in the "option" requests may include extensions for timing or other elements that allow calculation
    based on information found in the RequestGroup or other referenced "option" resources, as well as to expose
    elements within the "option" resource for referencing in other "option" resources.  These extensions are:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>TODO</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    The RequestGroup and all of its referenced "option" Requests are treated as a single integrated Request whose
    status is the status of the RequestGroup.  If there is a need to manage statuses of the different parts, separately,
    refer to the guidance <a href="request.html#requestgroup">here</a>.
  </p>
</div>
