<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"> </a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
Used to record detailed information pertinent to a clinician's assessment and assertion of a particular aspect of a person's state of health. 
Examples of condition include problems, diagnoses, concerns, issues. There are many uses of condition which include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>recording a problem, diagnosis, health concern or health issue during an encounter</li>
<li>the use of such information to populate a problem list of a summary statement such as a discharge summary </li>
</ul>
<p>
This resource is used to record detailed information about a clinician's assessment and assertion of a particular aspect of a patient's state of health. 
It is intended for use to record information about a disease/illness identified from application of clinical reasoning over the pathologic and 
pathophysiologic findings (diagnosis), or identification of health issues/situations that require ongoing monitoring and/or management (health issue/concern), 
or identification of health issues/situations considered harmful, potentially harmful and required to be investigated and managed (problems).
</p>
<p>
The condition resource may also be used to record certain health state of a patient which does not normally present negative outcome (until complications 
are predicted or detected), e.g. pregnancy. Examples of complications of pregnancy include: hyperemesis gravidarum, preeclampsia, eclampsia - which are 
captured as problems/diagnoses.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"> </a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
    The condition resource may be referenced by other resources as "reasons" for an action (e.g. <a href="medicationorder.html">MedicationOrder</a>,
<a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a>, <a href="diagnosticrequest.html">DiagnosticRequest</a>, etc.)
</p>
<p>
This resource is not to be used to record information about subjective and objective information that might lead to the recording of a Condition.
Such signs and symptoms that are typically captured using the <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resource; 
although in some cases a persistent symptom, e.g. fever, headache may be captured as a condition before a definitive diagnosis can be discerned by a clinician.
</p>
<p>
The condition resource also specifically excludes <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a> as those are handled with their own resource.
</p>

<a name="dstu"> </a>
<blockquote class="dstu-note">
<p>
<b>STU Note:</b> The <code>Condition.category</code> element is a <code>CodeableConcept</code> data type with a <a href="terminologies.html#preferred">preferred</a> (not <a href="terminologies.html#required">required</a>) binding to four category codes:  
<code>complaint | symptom | finding | diagnosis</code> from the FHIR-defined condition-category code system and value set.  In <a href="http://gforge.hl7.org/gf/project/fhir/tracker/?action=TrackerItemEdit&amp;tracker_item_id=10091">GFORGE # 10091</a>, 
the conformance requirements for code vs. CodeableConcept (4a) note that a CodeableConcept should use a standard terminology such as SNOMED CT.  The Patient Care WG has recommended that <code>Condition.category</code> be changed to a <code>code</code> data type with a <a href="terminologies.html#required">required</a> binding to the condition-category value set (containing the four codes: <code>complaint | symptom | finding | diagnosis</code> as noted above).
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://gforge.hl7.org/gf/project/fhir/tracker/">Feedback</a> is sought particularly on these questions:
</p>
<ol>
 <li>Is <code>CodeableConcept</code> needed for Condition.category?  If so, what are the concepts that could be used from SNOMED CT for this constrained value set?  How would this impact searching by category?</li> 
 <li>If Condition.category is changed to a <code>code</code> data type, is the use of the current four codes adequate for condition classification, or are additional codes needed?  If so, what would these be?  Note the recommendation to make this a <b>required</b>, not a preferred binding.  Please comment on the impact of high level categories vs. more granular categories.</li>   
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>
<b>PLANNED CHANGE:</b>
</p>
<p>
<b>Communication</b> is one of the <a href="workflow.html#event">Event</a> resources in the FHIR <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a> specification.  As such, it
is expected to be adjusted to align with the <a href="event.html">Event</a> workflow pattern which will involve adding a number of additional data elements and potentially
renaming a few elements.  Any concerns about performing such alignment are welcome as ballot comments and/or tracker items.
</p>
</div>

</div>
