<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>Procedure is one of the <a href="workflow.html#event">event</a> resources in the FHIR <a href="workflow.html">workflow</a> specification.</p>

<p>
This resource is used to record the details of current and historical procedures performed on, with, or for a patient, practitioner, device, organization, or location. Examples include surgical procedures, diagnostic procedures, endoscopic procedures, biopsies, counseling, physiotherapy, personal support services, adult day care services, non-emergency transportation, home modification, exercise, verification of enrollment qualifications for a social program etc. Procedures may be performed by a healthcare professional, a service provider, a friend or relative or in some cases by the patient themselves.
</p>
<p>
Procedures can be performed on other non-patient subjects.  For example, a procedure can represent an inspection to verify temperature or humidity for storage at a given location.  Additionally, a procedure can represent the verification of the practitioner's qualifications for accreditation.
</p>
<p>
This resource provides summary information about the occurrence of the procedure and is not intended to
provide real-time snapshots of a procedure as it unfolds, though for long-running procedures such as psychotherapy,
it could represent summary level information about overall progress.  The creation of a resource to support detailed
real-time procedure information awaits the identification of a specific implementation use-case to share such information.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The Procedure resource should not be used to capture an event if a more specific resource already exists - e.g. 
<a href="immunization.html">immunizations</a>, <a href="medicationadministration.html">drug administrations</a>,
<a href="communication.html">communications</a>, and <a href="nutritionintake.html">nutrition intake</a>. The boundary between determining whether an action is a Procedure 
(training or counseling) as opposed to a Communication is based on whether
there's a specific intent to change the mind-set of the patient.  Mere disclosure of information would be considered
a Communication.  A process that involves verification of the patient's comprehension or to change the patient's
mental state would be a Procedure.
</p>
<p>
Note that many diagnostic processes are procedures that generate <a href="observation.html">Observations</a> and 
<a href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReports</a>. In many cases, 
such an observation does not require an explicit representation of the procedure used to create the 
observation, but where there are details of interest about how the diagnostic procedure was performed, 
the Procedure resource is used to describe the activity.
</p>
<p> Some diagnostic procedures might not have a Procedure record. The Procedure record is only necessary when 
there is a need to capture information about the physical intervention that was performed to capture the diagnostic 
information (e.g. anesthetic, incision, scope size, etc.)</p>
<p>
A <a href="task.html">Task</a> is a workflow step such as cancelling an order, fulfilling an order, signing an order, merging a set of records, admitting a patient. 
Procedures are actions that are intended to result in a physical or mental change to or for the subject (e.g. surgery, physiotherapy, training, counseling). 
A <a href="task.html">Task</a> resource often exists in parallel with clinical resources. For example, a <a href="task.html">Task</a> might request fulfillment of a <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a> ordering a Procedure.
</p>

</div>

</div>
