<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<div>
		<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
		<p>         This Patient Profile is part of the The USLabOrder and USLabReport Implementation Guides. Its scope is US Realm ambulatory care and is based upon upon existing regulatory requirements for Laboratories and Electronic Health Record Systems (EHR-S) for ordering clinical laboratory results. The content has been modeled after the joint HL7 and The Standards and Interoperability (S and I) Framework Laboratory Orders and Results Interface Initiatives and the HL7 Lab Order Conceptual Specification and V3 Lab Normative Standard. However, much of the content is likely to be useable outside the ambulatory space and in other jurisdictions. </p>
		
		<p>A single Patient profile is defined which is referenced as the subject of the USLabOrder DiagnosticOrder and DiagnosticReport profile.  It may referenced by copy to and blind copy to as well.  Although  not specified in this implementation, it may be used in in other resources as well.</p>
		
		<p>         For the purposes of this profile, all elements listed in the differential profile view are <i>Supported</i> which means that the Laboratory Order/Results Sender  SHALL be capable of supplying these elements and or extensions to the Laboratory Order/Results Receiver if the data is available.          For the Laboratory Order/Results Receiver <i>Supported</i> means they SHALL save/print/archive/etc. the supplied the elements and or extensions sent by the Laboratory Order/Results Sender.  Both the Laboratory Receiver and Laboratory Sender MAY use the information to control their display of the information.      </p>
		
		
		
		<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
		<p>         Explains how this resource relates to others. Particularly important is to differentiate between appropriate usages for related resources when an implementer might be confused about what to reference when.      </p>
	</div>   -->   <!-- (optional):      <div>      <h2>Background and Context</h2>      <p>      Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used      </p>      </div>      -->
</div>
