<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This Resource covers data about patients and animals involved in a wide range of health-related activities, including:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Curative activities</li>
<li>Psychiatric care</li>
<li>Social services</li>
<li>Pregnancy care</li>
<li>Nursing and assisted living</li>
<li>Dietary services</li>
<li>Tracking of personal health and exercise data</li>
<li>Tracking financial services (e.g., insurance subscriber/policy holder)</li>
<li>Public health</li>
<li>Population health</li>
</ul>
<p>
The data in the Resource covers the "who" information about the patient: its attributes are focused on the demographic
information necessary to support the administrative, financial and logistic procedures. A Patient record is generally 
created and maintained by each organization providing care for a patient. A patient or animal receiving care at multiple
organizations may therefore have its information present in multiple Patient Resources.
</p>
<p>
Not all concepts are included within the base resource (such as race, ethnicity, organ donor status, nationality, etc.), 
but may be found in <a href="patient-profiles.html">profiles</a> defined for specific jurisdictions (e.g., US Meaningful Use Program) 
or <a href="patient-core.html">standard extensions</a>. Such fields vary widely between jurisdictions and often have different 
names and valuesets for the similar concepts, but they are not similar enough to be able to map and exchange.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
    <p>
        The Patient resource is the primary resource used to represent the recipient of care, services or processes.
        Patient is the appropriate resource even when a domain may use a different term for that person, such as client, subscriber, member, guarantor, etc.  
    </p>
    <p>
        There are several resources that can be used to represent an individual:
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
            Person can be used to link all resources that represent the same individual, including Patient.
            See the <a href="patient.html#linking">Patient vs. Person vs. Patient.Link vs. Linkage</a> section.
        </li>
        <li>
            Patient.contact and RelatedPerson may both be used to represent patient contacts.
            See the <a href="patient.html#contact">Patient.contact vs. RelatedPerson</a> section.
        </li>
        <li>
            For employee health, a single individual may be represented as both a Patient and a Practitioner.
            The Patient representation would be used when the individual is the subject of care or services, and the Practitioner would be used when the individual is providing care or services.
            The Person resource may be used to indicate that the Patient and Practitioner represent the same individual,
            as described in the <a href="patient.html#linking">Patient vs. Person vs. Patient.Link vs. Linkage</a> section.
        </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
        The Patient resource can be used to represent non-human recipients of care, such as animals.  See the <a href="patient.html#veterinary">Veterinary Care</a> section.
        In the case of a collective group of animals, such as a herd, if the individual animal is tracked, then Patient resources would be used to represent each animal.
        If the individual animals are not tracked, Group would be used to represent the collective.
    </p>
    <p>
        Patient resources may be used in multiple contexts.
        For example, in the financial context, the Patient may fill the role of <a href="account-definitions.html#Account.guarantor">guarantors</a>,
        <a href="coverage-definitions.html#Coverage.subscriber">subscribers</a>,
        <a href="coverage-definitions.html#Coverage.beneficiary">beneficiaries</a>, or other financial actors.
        In this case, different Patient resource instances may be used if the patient had different demographics that are relevant for each context.
    </p>
</div>
    
</div>
