<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
Notes:
</p>
<ul>
<li>multipleBirth can be either expressed as a boolean (just indicating whether the patient is part of a multiple birth) or as an integer, indicating the actual birth order.</li>
<li>Patient records may only be in one of two statuses: in use (active=true) and not in use (active=false). 
A normal record is active, i.e. it is in use. Active is set to 'false' when a record is created as a duplicate or in error. 
A record does not need to be linked to be inactivated.
</li>
<li>The <i>link</i> element is used to assert that two or more Patient resources are both about the same actual person. 
See below for further discussion</li>
<li>There should be only one preferred language (Language.preference = true) per mode of expression.</li>
<li>The Contact for a Patient has an element <i>organization</i>, this is for use with guardians or business related contacts where just the organization is relevant.</li>
</ul>

<a name="links"> </a>
<h2>Managing Patient Registration (Linking Patients)</h2>
<p>
Managing Patient registration is a well known difficult problem. Around 2% of registrations are in error, 
mostly duplicate records. Sometimes the duplicate record is caught fairly quickly and retired before much 
data is accumulated. In other cases, substantial amounts of data may accumulate. For these and other 
reasons, the identifiers associated with a patient may change over time.
</p>
<p>
A Patient record's Resource Id can never change. For this reason the identifiers with 
which humans are concerned (often called MRN - Medical Record Number, or UR - Unit Record) should not 
be used for the resource' id. Instead they should be represented in the <i>Patient.identifier</i> 
list where they can be managed. This is also useful for the case of institutions that have acquired 
multiple numbers because of mergers of patient record systems over time.
</p>
<p>
This specification does not specify merge functionality: if multiple patient records are found to be 
duplicates, they can be linked together - an assertion that two (or more) Patient resources are both 
about the same actual person. When patient resources are linked, one may be chosen as the "master" - 
the correct record. In this case, the active status of all the other resources is set to false, 
and all the content is moved to the active record by updating it directly. 
</p>
<p>
The <i>link</i> element is used to assert that patient resources refer to the same person.  
If any patient resources is linked to another, then that other resource SHALL also link back to 
the source resource in order to maintain record consistency. <font color="Maroon"><b>Systems should not update patient links across two or more patient resources
using separate transactions (i.e. update operations), where later operations may fail and leave the 
patient resources in disagreement with each other</b></font>. Instead, systems should either:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Use a <a href="http.html#transaction">transaction</a> and update all the resources in a single transaction</li>
 <li>Use a <a href="message.html#events">patient link/unlink</a> message</li>
</ul>

</div>
