<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
Notes:
</p>
<ul>
<li>multipleBirth can be either expressed as a boolean (just indicating whether the patient is part of a multiple birth) or as an integer, indicating the actual birth order.</li>
<li>Patient records may only be in one of two statuses: in use (active=true) and not in use (active=false). 
A normal record is active, i.e. it is in use. Active is set to 'false' when a record is created as a duplicate or in error. 
A record does not need to be linked to be inactivated.
</li>
<li>The <i>link</i> element is used to assert that two or more Patient resources are both about the same actual person. 
See below for further discussion</li>
<li>There should be only one preferred language (Language.preference = true) per mode of expression.</li>
<li>The Contact for a Patient has an element <i>organization</i>, this is for use with guardians or business related contacts where just the organization is relevant.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Patient id's and Patient resource id's</h2>
<p>A Patient record's Resource Id can never change. For this reason the identifiers with 
which humans are concerned (often called MRN - Medical Record Number, or UR - Unit Record) should not 
be used for the resource's id, since MRN's may change, i.e. as a result of having duplicate records of
the same person. Instead they should be represented in the <i>Patient.identifier</i> 
list where they can be managed. This is also useful for the case of institutions that have acquired 
multiple numbers because of mergers of patient record systems over time.
</p>


<a name="links"> </a>
<h2>Linking Patients</h2>
<p>The <i>link</i> element is used to assert that patient resources refer to the same person. This element is used
to support three distinct scenario's where multiple records of the same person exist:</p>

<h3>Duplicate Patient records</h3>
<p>Managing Patient registration is a well known difficult problem. Around 2% of registrations are in error, 
mostly duplicate records. Sometimes the duplicate record is caught fairly quickly and retired before much 
data is accumulated. In other cases, substantial amounts of data may accumulate. By using a link of type 'replace',
the record containing such a link is marked as a duplicate and the link points forward to a record that should
be used instead. Note that the record pointed to may in its turn have been identified as created in error and forward
to yet another Patient resource. Records that replace another record, do not point back to the replaced record.
</p>

<h3>Patient record in a Patient index</h3>
<p>A Patient record may be present in a system that acts as a Patient Index: it maintains a (summary of) patient data and
a list of one or more servers that it are known to hold a more comprehensive and/or authorative record of the same patient.
The link type 'refer' is used denote such a link. Note that linked records may contain contradictory information. The
record referred to does not point back to the referring record.</p>

<h3>Distributed Patient record</h3>
<p>In a distributed architecture, multiple systems keep separate patient records concerning the same person. These
records are not considered duplicates, but contain a distributed, potentially overlapping view of the patient's data.
Each such record may have its own focus or maintaining organization and there need not be a sense of one record
being more complete or more authorative than another. In such cases, links of type 'seealso' can be used to point to
other patient records. It is not a requirement that such links are bilateral. 
</p>

<h2>Merging records</h2>
<p>
This specification does not specify merge functionality: if multiple patient records are found to be 
duplicates, they can be linked together, as described above. These links merely express the relationship
between records, and in the case of a replacement link, indicate a "master" record.  This specification
does not mandate that FHIR servers migrate information between such records on finding such a link. Note:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Health information administrators may call the process "merging", but it is often implemented as "linking" at the record level</li>
 <li>Servers are allowed to implement merging/record migration even though it is not mandated. </li>
</ul>
</div>
