<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The DeviceComponent resource is used to describe the characteristics, operational status and capabilities of a medical-related component of a medical device. It can be a physical component that is integrated inside the device, a removable physical component, or a non-physical component that allows physiological measurement data and its derived data to be grouped in a hierarchical information organization. 
</p>
<p>
Note:
</p>
<p>
For the initial scope, this DeviceComponent resource is only applicable to describe a single node (such as MDS, VMD, or Channel) represents in the containment tree that is produced by the context scanner in any medical device that implements or derives from the ISO/IEEE 11073 standard.</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The DeviceComponent allows us to change the configuration of the device without having to change the device resource instance. The life-cycle of the configuration may be completely different than the one of the device itself.
</p>
<p>
There are several related resources
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="device.html">Device</a>  - Used by the MedicalDeviceSystem profile</li>
 <li><a href="patient.html">Patient</a>  - Used by the MedicalDeviceSystem profile</li>
 <li><a href="location.html">Location</a>  - Used by the MedicalDeviceSystem profile</li>
 <li><a href="devicecomponent.html">DeviceComponent</a></li>
</ul>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<h3>Structure of a DeviceComponent Resource</h3>

<p>
A Context Scanner object of a medical device that implements or derives from ISO/IEEE 11073
standard is responsible for observing device configuration changes. After instantiation, the
Context Scanner object is responsible for announcing the object instances in the device's MDIB, 
a hierarchical containment (MDS->VMD->Channel->Metric). The DeviceComponent resource can be used  
to describe  the characteristics, operational status and capabilities of a medical-related 
component of a medical device. It can be a physical component that is integrated inside 
the device, a removable physical component, or a non-physical component that allows 
physiological measurement data and its derived data to be grouped in a hierarchical 
information organization. Devices are conceptualised using the following main structure:
</p>
<ol>
 <li><b>MedicalDeviceSystem</b> - An actual device that external systems communicate with. In 11073, this is known as a MDS.</li>
 <li><b>VirtualMedicalDevice</b> - A medical-related subsystem of a medical device. It can either be a physical hardware piece or a pure software plugin component of a medical device. In 11073, this is known as a VMD.</li>
 <li><b>Channel</b> - A non-physical component that allows physiological measurement data and its derived data to be grouped in a hierarchical information organization.</li> 
</ol>

<p>
Very simple devices may have only a single virtual device with a single channel and one metric, while complex devices may have multiple items at every level. 
</p>
</div>
 
</div>
