<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<h3>Converting Device Logs to Device Observations</h3>
<p>
A device log has little context, and does not have the full context to support integrating 
the data into the patient record. The usual process for feeding the data from the device 
log resource into the patient record is to convert it to a <a href="deviceobservation.html">Device Observation</a>.
</p>
<p>
To convert the data from a Device Log to a Device Observation:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Locate the matching Device Capabilities resource (may be referred to explicitly in the log, but is also sent explicitly by the machine each time a system connects to it)</li>
 <li>Use the key values on the device log to identify the relevant metric or facet for each item</li>
 <li>Use the information for the metric or facet to build a set of <a href="observation.html">observation</a> resources (see below)</li>
 <li>Create a device observation that provides the device context for the observations</li>
 <li>Fill out the missing information (device identity, subject, etc.). This information may be 
   explicit in the device capabilities and device log resources, but the simpler the device, the more likely it must come from local context/configuration</li>
 <li>Submit the device observation to the patient record</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Converting a Data Item to an Observation</b></p>
<p>
Between the Device Item and the matching Device Capabilities information, the following information is provided:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>metric or facet code - the code for the observation</li>
 <li>data item value</li>
 <li>data type </li>
 <li>additional information to complete the data type</li>
 <li>a set of flags</li>
</ul>
<p>
The following table describes how to convert from value to the correct data type:
</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr>
  <th>Data Type</th>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>Template</th>
 </tr> 
 <tr>
  <td><a href="datatypes.html#Quantity">Quantity</a></td>
  <td>The common case. The device capabilities provides a units, and optionally a UCUM code</td>
  <td>
   <pre>
    &lt;valueQuantity&gt;
      &lt;value value="[data item value]" /&gt;
      [ (if appropriate from flags) &lt;comparator value="??" /&gt; ]
      &lt;units value="[units]" /&gt;
	    [ (if UCUM code provided)
        &lt;system value="http://unitsofmeasure.org" /&gt;
        &lt;code value="[UCUM]" /&gt;
      ]
    &lt;/valueQuantity&gt;
   </pre>
  </td>
 </tr> 
 <tr>
  <td><a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a></td>
  <td>When the output is a choice of one of a set of discrete values.<br/>The system should be a reference to some locatable definition of the values so that display names can be resolved</td>
  <td>
   <pre>
    &lt;valueCoding&gt;
      &lt;system value="[system]" /&gt;
      &lt;code value="[data item value]" /&gt;
    &lt;/valueCoding&gt;
   </pre>
  </td>
 </tr> 
 <tr>
  <td><a href="datatypes.html#string">string</a></td>
  <td>The output should be treated as a simple string</td>
  <td>
   <pre>
    &lt;valueString value="[data item value]"/&gt;
   </pre>
  </td>
 </tr> 
</table>
<p>The following table summarizes the interpretation of the possible flags</p>
<table class="grid">
 <tr>
  <th>Flag</th>
  <th>Interpretation</th>
 </tr> 
 <tr>
  <td>ok, ongoing, early, questionable, calibrating, error, unknown</td>
  <td>The flags have the same meaning on the observation.reliability element</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>test, demo, alarm, alarm-off</td>
  <td>These flags have no representation in the observation resource</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>under, over</td>
  <td>These flags map to the Quantity.comparator element</td>
 </tr>
</table>

<p>
Generally, as a rule of thumb, metrics and facets are components of the observation. 
</p>


</div>
