<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
There are 4 device related resources
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="device.htm">Device</a>  - an administrative resource that tracks individual devices and their location. Primarily used for attribution of actions to devices</li>
 <li><a href="devicecapabilities.htm">Device Capabilities</a> - Defines what observations a device will provide when another system connects to it</li>
 <li>Device Log (this resource) - A raw report from a device at a point in time. Must be paired with the correct Device Capabilities resource in order to be processed</li>
 <li><a href="deviceobservation.htm">Device Observation</a> - A report of observations from a device</li>
</ul>
<p>
The device capabilities and log resources are used when communicating with a device, either directly or indirectly. 
When a channel is opened with the device, or its proxy, it first sends the Capabilities resource, and then a 
series of log resources. The FHIR JSON format is used in this case. (TODO: What's the communication protocol?)
The application that receives the log resources may choose to merge the log with the capabilities 
statement to create a device observation, which is suitable for wider use within a EHR/Clinical record context.
The application that receives the log resources may choose to merge the log with the capabilities 
statement to create a device observation, which is suitable for wider use within a EHR/Clinical record context. 
The Device Capabilities and Device Log resources may be used in a RESTful context, but in many contexts this 
will not be very useful - the data should be converted to a Device Observation for normal RESTful use in a 
patient care context.
</p>

<h3>Structure of the Device Log</h3>

<p>
A medical device emits a series of these device log resources on a regular basis.
A device log is simply a list of items with a key, a value, and a set of flags.  
The only way to understand the contents of the resource is to match the device log
to the device capabilities that provides the context for interpreting the data
in the device log. The device log can identify the appropriate <a href="devicecapabilities.htm">Device Capabilities</a> resource
explicitly, but generally this is omitted, and the applicable resource is the 
one that is sent prior to any device log resources being sent. The system receiving
the data must keep track of the appropriate <a href="devicecapabilities.htm">Device Capabilities</a> resource.
</p>

<p>
Some devices may be configured to know the identity of the subject of the observations,
so the device log also includes the subject. However many simple devices do not know 
the identity of the subject well, or even at all, and the subject information must be 
provided or completed by the recipient of the device logs based on local context.
</p>
<p>
The device log is a low level resource suitable for direct communication with devices.
The data from the device is usually converted to a <a href="deviceobservation.htm">Device Observation</a> for 
general use in a patient care context. This process is described further below. 
</p>

</div>
