<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p> 
The EncounterHistory is used to be able to record an ongoing history of significant events/changes that occur
during a patient encounter.
This information is not always up to date/accurate while entering encounter information and
is often back-dated as more detailed information becomes available, or corrections need to be made during
the completion of the encounter while it is being processed in coding or billing.
</p>
[%stu-note dstu%]
In FHIR R4 and earlier this data was in the Encounter statusHistory and classHistory backbone elements, 
however with longer duration encounters (where a patient encounter might be considered active for years) 
this would become increasingly inefficient, so was re-factored into this resource.<br/>
The design notes for this change are on <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/PA/Encounter+History+and+Movements">confluence</a>.
[%end-note%]
</div>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p> 
The Encounter resource stores the complete set of current/most recent data about an Encounter.
The EncounterHistory contains a snapshot of some key aspects (properties) of the encounter to track
changes to the encounter over time - specifically those that contribute to significant changes/events/milestones
during the encounter - such as moving between departments or locations.
</p>
<p>
Note that this historical information is different than what is tracked in the versions of the Encounter resource.
Past movements of a patient are often updated after the fact to correct what actually happened.<br/>
FHIR History (_history) doesn't cater for this need as the information isn't always accurate and can be corrected/back populated too.
Another challenge with _history is that it also includes corrections to errors in data entry which could not be
differentiated from actual movements/changes.
</p>
<p>
No clinical resources are expected to ever refer to a specific EncounterHistory event, they are only
attributed to the Encounter as a whole. If a resource is desiring to connect to a portion of an encounter
(and wanting to use EncounterHistory) this is an indication that you should be using a child Encounter through
the partOf property.
</p>
</div>

</div>
