<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
A declarative <a href="security.html#binding">attribute-based access control</a> policy statement.

Permission is used to express who has specific rights to specific data under specific conditions. Permission can express rules including
</p>
<ul>
<li>security labels/codes (<a href="security-labels.html#6.1.1.4.0.2">policies, refrains, and obligations</a>),</li>
<li>user identity,</li>
<li>application being used,</li>
<li>location of the requester,</li>
<li>organization requesting access,</li>
<li>purposeOfUse of the request and for which the data will be used,</li>
<li>data sensitivity, timeframe, authorship, and</li>
<li>the current status of privacy Consent.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The Permission can express permit or deny rules; and with permit rules there may be residual refrains, obligations, or filtering. 
The Permission resource may be used to record the access control constraints under which data can be collected, used, or shared.
</p>
</div>
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
The Permission resource is intended to be used to encode access control policies in a FHIR interoperable language. Where the access control policies protect access to FHIR defined interactions, resources, and operations; from actions done by organizations, practitioners, patients, and etc.
</p>
<p>
The Permission resource is intended to be used where <a href="consent.html">Consent</a> resource does not apply or where exposure of the full <a href="consent.html">Consent</a> details are not needed or desired.
The Permission resource may be used to express transactional access control rules that may be derived from a <a href="consent.html">Consent</a>.
</p>
<p>
Examples are:
</p>
<ul>
<li>use-cases that are not involving a patient subject.</li>
<li>an organizational directory: who can create, update, delete, and read</li>
<li>an organization wide access control policy expressing user groups and what they generally have available to them</li>
<li>residual policy that must be applied by a recipient of a response Bundle</li>
<li>base policy that Consent builds upon (i.e., `Consent.policyBasis.reference`)</li>
<li>consent provisions (i.e., `Consent.provision`) encoding in a different rule language (i.e., `Permission.rule`) using `Consent.provisionReference`.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The Permission resource should not be used in a conflicting way with <a href="security-labels.html">security labels in the .meta.security element</a>.
</p>

<!-- (optional):
<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Provides additional detail on exactly how the resource is to be used
</p>
</div>
-->
</div>
</div>
