<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>

<a name="scope"></a>
<blockquote class="stu-note">
	<p><b>Note to Implementers:</b> For an overview of this resource and others in the Device domain, also see the <a href="device-module.html">module page</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="stu-note">
	<p><b>Note to Implementers:</b> The owner has been removed from Device and is now included in DeviceAssociation as .relationship of the subject.  Please comment on the revision if there are issues with removing the identification of individuals in the Device resource.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="stu-note">
 <p><strong>Note to Implementers:</strong> Extensions have been created and are now available to represent previously removed <code>Device</code> elements and new concepts. These include:</p>

  <ul>
    <li><code>device-mode</code>, <code>device-cycle</code>, <code>device-duration</code>, <code>device-gateway</code>, and <code>device-endpoint</code></li>
    <li><code>device-alertDetection</code> – describes the alert detection activation states for the overall device</li>
    <li><code>device-conformsTo-source</code> – represents the source of the device specification</li>
  </ul>

 <p>Links to these extensions can be found in the <a href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/fhir-extensions/extensions-Device.html">FHIR Extension Pack</a>. Feedback from implementers is welcomed to inform further refinement and usage guidance.</p>
	</blockquote>
</div>  
<div>  
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>This is a base resource that tracks individual instances of a device and their location. It is referenced by other resources for recording which device performed an action such as a procedure or an observation, which device was implanted in or explanted from a patient, dispensing a device to a patient for their use, managing inventory, or when requesting a specific device for a patient's use. Medical devices include durable (reusable) medical equipment, implantable devices, as well as disposable equipment used for diagnostic, treatment, and research for healthcare and public health. Medical devices may also include some types of software.</p>
<p>Non-medical devices may include items such as a machine, cellphone, computer, software application or algorithm, etc. In short, a Device can range from a tongue depressor to an MRI. The fields in the Device resource must be flexible enough to cover this range.</p>
<p>The resource may be used to document the Unique Device Identifier (UDI) and information about a device where appropriate or necessary according to local jurisdictions over time. Additional information about UDI is provided in the <a class="external-link" href="device.html#udi" rel="nofollow">Unique Device Identifier (UDI)</a> section.</p>
<p>Devices may be categorized and may be associated with one or more categories. Device category examples include, but are not limited to: active, communicating, durable medical equipment, home use, implantable, InVitro diagnostics, personal health, point-of-care, single use, re-usable, and software. See <a class="external-link" href="devicedefinition.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceDefinition</a> for detailed descriptions of device categories.</p>

<h3 id="DeviceScopeBoundaryRelationships-Device-DeviceDefinition">Device and DeviceDefinition</h3>
<p>When referring to a specific instance, even without specific instance details, Device is to be used, not a DeviceDefinition. The context of a data exchange indicates whether the data is representing a physical instance or a &quot;kind&quot;, not the presence of instance data such as lot and serial numbers. </p>
<p>Some examples:</p>
<ol>
<li>
In a Procedure, reporting the use of a pump for which we have no instance data - the pump is a physical instance. Whether the lot number (for example) is known or not, depends on the circumstance - in another Procedure or in an update of the Procedure, the lot number could be added. Hence the use of Device.  
</li>
<li>
When a device gets replaced by another device of the same type. In this case, a procedure indicates that one instance of the device is removed/explanted/discarded, and another instance is used. These are physical instances for which instance data might exist and be known, or not.
</li>
</ol>
</div>


<div>  
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

[%stu-note dstu%]
The module pages under development by Orders and Observations will further describe the variations of device use cases across the device resources, e.g., Device, DeviceDefinition, DeviceAssociation, DeviceDispense, DeviceMetric, DeviceRequest, and Device Usage.
</p>
[%end-note-np%]

<p>There are several resources that can be used to represent device related events, requests or definitions.  The following Resources should be used in the following manner: </p>
<ul>
<li>Device (this resource)</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="devicedefinition.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceDefinition</a>&nbsp;- Describes a "kind" of device - not a specific instance of the device. A kind of device is frequently defined and documented by the manufacturer, reseller, or regulatory. Documentation would include any information that applies to all instances of a device, and may be published through a catalog. For example, the characteristics of a test analyzer, x-ray machine, or wheelchair.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="devicemetric.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceMetric</a>&nbsp;- Describes a measurement, calculation or setting capability of a device instance. A Device may include multiple device metrics, each yielding a different observation. The DeviceMetric models the properties of the Observations generated by and/or about the device such as whether or not the Observation is a setting.  A DeviceMetric describes aspects of the device that may change over time. In contrast, the <code>Device.property</code> is used to capture inherent, essentially fixed, characteristics of the device, such as a "large" blood pressure cuff, the bore size of an MRI, the color of a lead. (Such static characteristics may also be recorded in DeviceDefinition.). </li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="deviceassociation.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceAssociation</a>&nbsp;- Records the association of a device with a subject and/or operator (e.g. a Patient by ownership, or a Practitioner by usage during a procedure). DeviceAssociation should be used for ownenship/custiodianship.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="devicealert.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceAlert</a>&nbsp;- Represents a single alert or alarm condition detected and signaled by a patient-connected health / medical device to create clinician’s awareness of a patient safety risk that needs to be addressed.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="devicerequest.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceRequest</a> - The workflow step to request/order the use of a device in a specific context.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/oo-incubator/StructureDefinition-DeviceDispense.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceDispense</a> - The workflow step to manage the distribution of the device.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/oo-incubator/StructureDefinition-SupplyRequest.html" rel="nofollow">SupplyRequest</a> - The workflow step to request/order supplies that would be needed beyond the devices in the DeviceRequest. </li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/oo-incubator/StructureDefinition-SupplyDelivery.html" rel="nofollow">SupplyDelivery</a> - The workflow step to manage the distribution of supplies that are ordered beyone the devices in the DeviceDispense.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/oo-incubator/StructureDefinition-DeviceUsage.html" rel="nofollow">DeviceUsage</a> - To record the use of a device that is not covered by a procedure - i.e., patient reported use of a device.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="nutritionorder.html" rel="nofollow">NutritionOrder</a>&nbsp;- An order for nutrition can request to a specific device to administer enteral feeding.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="observation.html" rel="nofollow">Observation</a>&nbsp;- A measurement can be generated by many types of devices. It may be linked to and supplemented by data about the current structure and status of the device itself in one or more Device or DeviceMetric resources.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="procedure.html" rel="nofollow">Procedure</a>&nbsp;- A procedure can be performed using a variety of devices, or a device can be implanted or otherwise associated with a patient. A procedure may also record the inclusion of an additive.</li>
<li><a class="external-link" href="medicationadministration.html" rel="nofollow">MedicationAdministration</a>&nbsp;- A medication administration can be performed using a variety of devices.</li>
</ul>
<p>In FHIR, the Device represents either the device in total, or a component of an encapsulating device when there is a need for individual tracking of a component. A Device as a component then points to the parent device it is part of. The top-level Device captures the actual data about the instance of the device and the instances of all its children that either provides identifying characteristics of the Device (including applicable UDI &ndash; unique device identification) and data that can vary dynamically by device, e.g., specific settings at a particular point in time.</p>
<p>Devices differ from medications because they are not "used up" - they remain active in or for a patient for a longer duration. They also may be re-used, particularly non-implanted devices and those used for diagnostics and procedures. Frequently, when a device is packaged with a medication, the ordering, dispense, and administration processes typically focus on the medication aspects and reference the device.</p>
<p>In the case of an infusion pump, while some actions are focused on the device (e.g., ordering to a room or maintaining the pump), the focus is as well on the medication while the device is used for administration. However, that separation is not always as clear and may be impacted by specific implementations. Regardless, the&nbsp;<a class="external-link" href="medication.html" rel="nofollow">Medication</a>&nbsp;resource should not be used to represent (implanted) devices, rather reference the relationship where an actual device needs to be tracked in addition to the medication. In some sense the Medication is analogous to the Observation generated by a Blood Pressure personal health device. The Observation resource contains the blood pressure values, units and the time stamp while the Device resource contains the manufacturer name, model number, serial number, firmware and hardware versions, exchange protocol information, any clock capabilities, etc.</p>


</div>

</div>
