<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h3>Notes</h3>
<ul>
 <li>There are many sources of possible codes for device type. The example suggests to use device codes from RTM, 
 which has many codes suitable to devices that make <a href="deviceobservationreport.html">Device Observation Reports</a>. 
 Another source which will be appropriate for many devices is the FDA GUDID (see below) or equivalent. 
 Alternatively, many jurisdictions have their own supply chain arrangements which define many useful codes.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Device Identifiers</h3>

<p>
Nearly all devices are assigned one or more identifiers, which are usually printed or affixed to the device using either barcodes or RFIDs. 
The identifiers can come from the manufacturer (often called the "serial number", various institution and registries. Any of 
these identifiers assigned to the device can and should be recorded in the device resource. The different identifiers are 
differentiated by their use, label, and system values.
</p>
<p>
The most important of the identifiers is the 
<a href="http://www.fda.gov/MedicalDevices/DeviceRegulationandGuidance/UniqueDeviceIdentification/default.htm">Unique Device Identifier</a>
(UDI), which most medical devices are required to carry and which can be used to access the 
<a href="http://www.fda.gov/MedicalDevices/DeviceRegulationandGuidance/UniqueDeviceIdentification/GlobalUDIDatabaseGUDID/ucm20038750.htm">Global 
Unique Device Identification Database</a> (GUDID). The UDI has its own element (<i>udi</i>). The UDI may identify an instance of a device uniquely, or it may just identify the type of the device. 
A portion of the UDI - the DI part - can be extracted from the UDI when required, and used 
to look up information about the device through the GUDID.
Where the device has an assigned UDI, the other details carried in the resource (e.g. lot, expiry date etc) SHALL be 
consistent with the information encoded  in the UDI or registered in the GUDID.
</p>
<p>
Note that a GTIN (sometimes also called an EAN number) is a code for the kind of device, not an identifier for the device.
The GTIN may be part of the UDI, but it may also be known separately, in which case GTINs should be carried in the type element:
</p>
<div class="example">
<p>GTIN example</p>
<pre>
  &lt;type&gt;
    &lt;coding&gt;
      &lt;system value=&quot;urn:oid:1.3.160‎&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;value value=&quot;00614141999996&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/coding&gt;
    &lt;!-- other codes for type --&gt;
  &lt;/type&gt;
</pre>

</div>





</div>
