<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>

<a name="scope"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This is a base resource that tracks individual instances of a device and their location. It is referenced by other resources for recording which device performed an action such as a procedure or an observation, which device was implanted in or explanted from a patient, dispensing a device to a patient for their use, managing inventory, or when requesting a specific device for a patient’s use. The resource may be used to document the Unique Device Identifier (UDI) and information about a device where appropriate or necessary.  Additional information about UDI is provided in the <a href="#udi">Unique Device Identifier (UDI)</a> section.
</p>
<p>
Medical devices include durable (reusable) medical equipment, implantable devices, as well as disposable equipment used for diagnostic, treatment, and research for healthcare and public health. Non-medical devices may include items such as a machine, cellphone, computer, application, etc.
</p>

<p>Devices can also be subdivded as follows:</p>
<p><b>Implantable device</b></p>
<ul>
  <li>
     a device that is intended to be placed in a surgically or naturally formed cavity of the human body…for a continuous period of 30 days or more <a href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/home-health-and-consumer-devices/home-use-devices">US Food and Drug Administration Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Home Use Devices.</a> Accessed 13 March 2020.
  </li>
  <li>
     any active medical device which is intended to be totally or partially introduced, surgically or medically, into the human body or by medical intervention into a natural orifice, and which is intended to remain after the procedure <a href="https://www.bsigroup.com/en-US/medical-devices/Technologies/Active-Implantable-Medical-Devices/">BSI Group. Active implantable medical devices.</a> Accessed 13 March 2020.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>
 <p><b>Patient-use device</b></p>
<ul>
<li>Patient-use, or home use devices, intended for users in any environment outside of a professional healthcare facility. This includes devices intended for use in both professional healthcare facilities and homes <a href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/home-health-and-consumer-devices/home-use-devices">US Food and Drug Administration Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Home Use Devices.</a> Accessed 13 March 2020.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a name="bnr"></a>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
These are the device related resources
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Device (this resource)</li>
 <li><a href="devicedefinition.html">DeviceDefinition</a> - Describes a "kind" of device - not a physical instance. A kind of device is frequently defined and documented by the manufacturer, reseller, or regulatory. Documentation would include general information any information that applies to any instance of a device, and may be published through a catalog. For example, the characteristics of a test analyzer, x-ray machine, or wheelchair.</li>
 <li><a href="devicemetric.html">DeviceMetric</a> - Describes a measurement, calculation or setting capability of a device.  A Device may include multiple device metrics, each yielding a different observation.</li>
</ul>
<p>
In FHIR, the Device represents either the device in total, or a component of a larger device when there is a need for individual tracking of a component.  A Device as a component then points to the parent device it is part of.  The Device captures the actual data about the instance of the device that either provides identifying characteristics of the Device (including applicable UDI – unique device identification) and data that can vary by device, e.g., specific settings at a particular point in time.  The DeviceDefinition represents the data that is applicable to all devices that reference that DeviceDefinition.
</p>
<p>The  DeviceMetric  model the dynamic aspects of the Device, including operation status of those aspects and is consequently much more volatile. </p>
<p>
Devices differ from medications because they are not "used up" - they remain active in or for a patient for a longer duration.  They also may be re-used, particularly non-implanted devices and those used for diagnostics and procedures. Frequently, when a device is packaged with a medication, the ordering, dispense, and administration processes typically focus on the medication aspects and reference the device, rather than that the Device is the focus of the ordering, dispense, and administration process.  In the case of an infusion pump, while some actions are focused on the device (e.g., ordering to a room or maintaining the pump), the focus is as well on the medication while the device is used for administration.  However, that separation is not always as clear and may be impacted by specific implementations.  Regardless, the <a href="medication.html">Medication</a> resource should not be used to represent (implanted) devices, rather reference the relationship where an actual device needs to be tracked in addition to the medication. 

</p>

</div>

</div>
