<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
This resource carries a set of data from a device that is observing a subject. Most commonly, the subject is a patient,
and the device is something like a vital signs monitor, or a glucose measurement device, but other kinds of subjects
and devices are expected as well. 
</p>
<p>
This resource does not cater for:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Supporting real-time analytics and in particular, alarms that might be raised as a result of such analysis</li>
 <li>Sending commands to a device</li>
</ul>
<p>
This capability is expected to be subject of additional resources that are yet to be developed, and implmenter input on this is welcome.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
There are 2 device related resources
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="device.html">Device</a>  - An administrative resource that tracks individual devices of all kinds and their location. Primarily used for attribution of actions to devices</li>
 <li>DeviceObservationReport (this resource) - A record of a set of observations produced by a device</li>
</ul>

<p>
Note that this resource is entirely concerned with devices that report data. Interacting with and
controlling devices such as infusion pumps etc. is not in scope for this resource (no solution for this yet). 
This resource is based on ISO 11073.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<h3>Structure of a Device Data Resource</h3>

<p>
A medical device is conceived of as a measuring device that is capable of reporting 
a series of groups of measurements on a regular basis. The device capabilities resource 
describes the kind of data that a medical device reports. Devices are conceptualised 
using the following main structure:
</p>
<ol>
 <li><b>Device</b> - The actual device that external systems communicate with. In 11073, this is known as a "Medical Device System" (MDS)</li>
 <li><b>Virtual Medical Device</b> - A medical-related subsystem of a medical device. The virtual device that may be part of the containing device, or a separate device that may be communicating with it</li>
 <li><b>Channel</b> - Groups together physiological measurement data and derived data</li>
 <li><b>Metrics</b> - A piece of measured or derived data that will be reported by the machine, reported as an observation</li>
 <li><b>Facets</b> - Additional data that qualifies the metric, or contributes to its assessment, reported in observation.compartment</li>
</ol>

<p>
Very simple devices may have only a single virtual device with a single channel and one metric, while complex devices may have multiple items at every level. 
</p>
</div>
 
</div>
