<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The core extensions provide HL7 provided extensions to the <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resource.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<h3>Questionnaire documentation</h3>
<p>
The <a name="category"><b>category</b></a> extension allows a questionnaire to be grouped under various headings for discovery and/or
for navigation of a list of categories.
</p>
<p>
The <a name="label"><b>label</b></a> extension allows the heading number for a group or question to be conveyed from the group title or
question text.  This permits justification and more advanced formatting.
</p>

<h3>Repetitions</h3>
<p>
There are two extensions that provide precise control over the number of repetitions of a group or the number of answers to a question:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a name="minOccurs"><b>minOccurs</b></a> establishes a minimum number of group repetitions or minimum number of question answers for "required" groups/questions where the minimum number is greater than 1</li>
  <li><a name="maxOccurs"><b>minOccurs</b></a> establishes a maximum number of group repetitions or maximum number of question answers for "repeating" groups/questions where the maximum number is not unlimited</li>
</ul>

<h3>Visibility</h3>
<p>
There are two extensions that provide control over whether groups or questions are allowed to be answered and/or displayed to the user:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a name="enableWhen"><b>enableWhen</b></a> indicates that a question or group should only be answerable (and generally visible) when a particular question has a specified answer (or at least has an answer)</li>
  <li><a name="hidden"><b>hidden</b></a> indicates that a question or group should not be displayed to the user at all because the answer is intended for internal use only</li>
</ul>

<h3>Defaults</h3>
<p>
Some questionnaires may choose to declare defaults (though this can obviously influence data collection and is generally avoided
for questionnaires used for research purposes).  Two extensions are provided to support this:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a name="defaultValue"><b>defaultValue</b></a> - This allows a default answer to be provided for a question.  The default value is typically displayed
when the questionnaire is initially rendered, giving the user a chance to change it.
</li>
<li>
<a name="defaultAsFixed"><b>defaultAsFixed</b></a> - This prevents a user from changing the value of the default value.  It may be used in circumstances where
a part of the questionnaire is set by context or where it's useful to expose certain data as though it were a question but
preventing it from being changed.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>References</h3>
<a name="deReference"><b>deReference</b></a> allows a question to be linked to the corresponding <a href="dataelement.html">DataElement</a>
resource that defines the meaning and allowed answer types for the question.  Note that the question text and any constraints
must still be explicitly declared.
</div>

</div>
