<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul>
<li>Questionnaires may be used to represent predefined forms, named using Questionnaire.name.</li>
<li>A Questionnaire's contents are placed inside its single nested Group, which may contain Questions or subgroups with Questions.</li>
<li>Groups and Questions may have linkIds allowing groups and question answers captured in a <a href="questionnaireanswers.html">QuestionnaireAnswers</a>
to be associated with their corresponding group or question.</li>
<li>Questionnaire allows for flexible naming and structuring of its contents to reflect the flexible and varying nature of forms and questionnaires. 
It explicitly does not try to standardize or streamline exchange of its contents outside its context of use, although exchanging partners may further
constrain its structure and flexibility using profiles to define standardized, reusable forms.</li>
<li>Because of the lack of explicit support for Questionnaires in HL7v3, HL7 CDA Documents frequently used named sections with
Observations to model Questionnaires. Such use cases should now utilize the Questionnaire Resource instead.</li>
<li>The order of questions within groups, groups within groups and groups within questions is relevant and must be retained for display and capture.</li>
</ul>

<a name="qversusr" />
<h3>Using Questionnaires versus using Resources</h3>
<p>
There is considerable overlap between the information covered by <b>Questionnaires</b> and other Resources (especially <a href="familyhistory.html">FamilyHistory</a>,
<a href="medicationstatement.html">MedicationStatement</a>, <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a>, etc.): 
<b>Questionnaire's</b> flexible structure can easily be misused to capture any data, even data that should be captured as separate Resources. The choice between using <b>Questionnaires</b> or separate 
Resources may be dictated by the procedure of collection and recording. E.g. if the data is captured as a physician-agreed (electronic) form, it might be impossible or undesirable to 
distill separate resources from it and capturing the data in a <b>Questionnaire</b> would be most appropriate.
</p> 

<p>
However, data captured only in <b>Questionnaires</b> can be difficult to query after-the-fact. Queries against other Resources will not return data captured only in <b>Questionnaires</b>, 
and querying against <b>Questionnaires</b> directly may not find all desired data, depending on how the questions may have been phrased or encoded over time or by different clinicians. 
Moreover, interoperability of such <b>Questionnaires</b> is limited as interpretation of its contents is only known to the circle of parties that were involved in its definition: encoding data from 
such <b>Questionnaires</b> using other, more specific, Resources increases the ability and consistency with which it can be understood and queried.
</p> 

<h3>Structure of the Questionnaire</h3>
<p>
A Questionnaire is built out of three components:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The main component is Questionnaire, which holds information <em>about</em> the Questionnaire, 
  like the identifier, publisher, date authored, etc. The Questionnaire contains one "main" Group, which contains all the content of the questionnaire.</li>
  <li>This Group can contain <em>either</em> nested Groups (to represent sections and subsections on a questionnaire form) or Questions.
  This way, any form containing sections or subsections can be represented, down to the actual questions.</li>
  <li>The Questions themselves may be simple questions with a prompt text and one expected answer, but they may also contain nested groups, 
each containing sets of nested questions. This way, one can model "panels" of questions which would only be relevant (and thus would only be displayed)
depending on the answers of a parent question. E.g. a question "Did the patient receive treatment in the past six months?" would contain a nested
group of questions asking for further details about the treatment. See an <a href="questionnaire-example-bluebook.xml.html">example</a> from 
the <a href="http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/Kids/Publications/my-personal-health-record.pdf">Australian NSW blue book</a></li>
<li>Specific controls on dynamic display of groups, questions, etc. based on the answers to other questions is outside the scope of the base resource and
are expected to be introduced as extensions.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Question Definitions</h3>
<p>
Questionnaires can be crafted using any questions the author can conceive phrased in whatever manner is appropriate or convenient.  However, standardization of
questions and the constraints enforced on the accompanying answers increases the ability to compare data gathered across questionnaires.  There are two
mechanisms defined in the specification for linking a Question (or Group) to a standardized definition:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>The <code>code</code> element on both Group and Question allows an individual question, a group of questions or even the questionnaire as a whole to be associated
  with a pre-defined terminology of questions and question groups such as LOINC or SNOMED</li>
  <li>The <a href="questionnaire-extensions.html#deReference">deReference</a> extension allows a question or group to be associated with the
  <a href="dataelement.html">DataElement</a> (DE) resource that formally defines the data element.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Linking to formal definitions of a question allows data captured by distinct questionnaires to be compared.  If systems have the necessary mappings to the
formal definition, linkages to formal definitions may also be used to automatically pre-populate or extract data from a corresponding 
<a href="questionnaireanswers.html">QuestionnaireAnswers</a> resource.
</p>
</div>
