<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
A <b>Questionnaire</b> is an organized collection of questions intended to solicit infomation from patients, providers or other individuals involved
in the healthcare domain.  They may be simple flat lists of questions or can be hierarchically organized in 
groups and sub-groups, each containing questions.  The <b>Questionnaire</b> defines the questions to be asked, how they are ordered and grouped and what
the constraints are on the allowed answers.  The results of a <b>Questionnaire</b> can be communicated using the <a href="questionnaireanswers.html">QuestionnaireAnswer</a> resource.
</p>
<p>
Questionnaires cover the need to communicate data originating from forms used in medical history examinations, research questionnaires and sometimes full
clinical speciality records. In many systems this data is collected using user-defined screens and forms. Questionnaires record specifics about data capture -
exactly what questions were asked, in what order, what choices for answers were, etc. Each of these questions are part of the Questionnaire, 
and as such the Questionnaire is a separately identifiable Resource, whereas the individual questions are not.
</p>
<p>Examples of Questionnaires include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Past medical history (PMH)</li>
<li>Family diseases</li>
<li>Social history</li>
<li>Research questionnaires/Clincial resarch forms (CRFs)</li>
<li>Quality and evaluation forms</li>
</ul>
<p>
This resource is limited in scope to support the characteristics of simple questionnaires.  However, common extensions have been defined to allow more
sophisticated behavior.  This includes:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="questionnaire-extensions.html">Questionnaire core extensions</a> which defines the additional descriptive characteristics for questionnaires and their groups and questions</li>
  <li><a href="element-extensions.html">Element extensions</a> which can describe additional constraints on allowed answers for questionnaires such as string length and date and numeric ranges</li>
</ul>
<p>
Additional profiles such as the <a href="questionnaire-sdc.html">Structured Data Capture Questionnaire profile</a> may provide additional capabilities for defining
more sophisticated questionnaires and forms.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
<b>Questionnaires</b> differ from <a href="list.html">Lists</a> because <a href="list.html">Lists</a> group existing resources, while <b>Questionnaires</b> group
arbitrary questions.  In theory, a <b>Questionnaire</b> could be expressed as a <a href="list.html">List</a> or <a href="composition.html">Composition</a> containing
<a href="dataelement.html">DataElement</a> resources.  However, the former would disregard the "wholeness" associated with a questionnaire where questions 
must generally be maintained as a single structure.  The latter would focus on rendering of the data elements rather than organizing the capture of information.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Groups and questions that make up a Questionnaire can be explicitly coded to refer to externally defined numbering or identification of questions and sections on
formally defined questionnaires. This allows extraction of the data on a form and post-processing of the data contained in a Questionnaire. Such coding is not required however 
and Questionnaires may be quite loosely defined. The section <a href="#qversusr">Questionnaire versus Resources</a> below discusses the issues of collecting data in such
loosely defined Questionnaires versus collecting data as well-defined separate Resources.
</p>
</div>

</div>





