<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="language"/>
<h3>Language and translations</h3>
<p>
In some environments, it may be necessary for a questionnaire to support multiple languages.  The rendering tool would select the appropriate
language based on a configuration setting, or perhaps would display all available languages and the user would read the one they are familiar with.
Systems MAY choose to provide support for identifying language and translations.  If they do, they MAY do so using the generic language and
translation extensions FHIR defines based on the ISO21090 data type specification:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090.html#language">http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090#language</a> allows the language of a particular (or any other data type) to be identified</li>
  <li><a href="http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090.html#string-translation">http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090#string-translation</a> allows additional repetitions in alternate languages to be communicated.  
  (The language for each translation would be communicated using the above #language extension)</li>
</ul>
<p>
These extensions can be used on absolutely any string element on <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>, <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a>, one of 
the data types or any other resource.  The base string should be the primary language of the questionnaire.  It is what will be rendered by systems that do
not support the translation extension or by systems whose language preference is other than one of the languages provided.
</p>
<p>
The ISO 19763 specification permits declaring language on questionnaire titles, descriptions, display names for codes and many other strings.  It also supports
capturing multiple variants of these strings with distinct languages.  These capabilities can be mirrored using the above extensions.
</p>
<p>
An alternative is to define an extension to the <b>Questionnaire</b> providing a pointer to an externally maintained set of extensions.  This approach allows
the translations to be maintained independently of the resource which has both positive and negative impacts, particularly with respect to resource signature.
</p>
<p>
<b>Open Issue:</b> Should this profile define such an extension and/or a resource for managing such translations?
</p>

<a name="ihe-interop"/>
<h3>Interoperability with the IHE SDC specification</h3>
<p>
This FHIR profile is partially based on the IHE <a href="http://ihe.net/uploadedFiles/Documents/QRPH/IHE_QRPH_Suppl_SDC_Rev1.0_PC_2014-06-06.pdf">Structured Data Capture</a> 
Technical Framework Supplement.  While largely aligned, there are differences between them, driven in part by their different technologies.
(FHIR tends to nail things down and only include those data elements that are essential to the use-case, while the IHE specification is somewhat looser in the content it 
supports.  As the content of both specifications stabilizes, the project team intends to develop a set of XSLT transforms to support translation between the two syntaxes.  
These transforms should provide seamless conversion in the majority of circumstances and will be designed to raise warning messages where some content could not be safely 
converted.
</p>
<p>
Another source of difference is in the data types.  The IHE specification supports arbitrary data types, though it enumerates a specific list of allowed types for text_field.
Of these, most map cleanly to FHIR, though there are some exceptions:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Date and time: In FHIR there's no ability to transmit different date formats - formatting control is handled by an extension, but all dates and
times are conveyed according to the w3c schema standard over the wire.  As well, partial-precision times are not supported in FHIR and must be zero-filled down to the second</li>
  <li>Durations in FHIR are limited to a single value and unit.  E.g. "3.5 days" or "84 hours".  There is no ability to convey "3d12h" as a single question answer</li>
  <li>The Attachment data type in FHIR supports conveying attachments both embedded within the answer or as references (possibly to a <a href="http.html#binary">Binary</a>
  resource in a bundle or to some external location.</li>
  <li>FHIR introduces a 'boolean' data type. (The IHE specification presumes this would be captured using a code.)</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <b>Open Issue:</b> Should FHIR also support an open-ended set of data types?  Why?
</p>
</div>