<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The Questionnaire may be a single list of questions, or can be hierarchically organized in 
groups and sub-groups, each containing questions. Questions may contain and single answer, which can take the form of simple text, 
numbers, dates or a set of coded choices.
</p>
<p>
Questionnaires cover the need to communicate data originating from forms used in medical history examinations, research questionnaires and sometimes full
clinical speciality records. In many systems this data is collected using user-defined screens and forms. Questionnaires record specifics about data capture -
exactly what questions were asked, in what order, what choices for answers were, etc. Each of these questions are part of the Questionnaire, 
and as such the Questionnaire is a separately identifiable Resource, whereas the individual questions are not.
</p>
<p>Examples of Questionnaires include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Past medical history (PMH)</li>
<li>Family diseases</li>
<li>Social history</li>
<li>Research questionnaires</li>
<li>Quality and evaluation forms</li>
</ul>
<p>Support for validation is outside the scope of this Resource, although basic structural features can be defined using the 
<a href="questionnaire-extensions.html">Questionnaire core extensions</a>.</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Questionnaires differ from Lists because Lists regroup or summarize existing information, while Questionnaires contain original, 
clinician collected data. Questionnaires are similar to Documents. However, the purpose of a Questionnaire is the capture of raw data as opposed to the composition 
and assertion of information intended for long term persistence and use in a Document.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<p>
Groups and questions that make up a Questionnaire can be explicitly named to refer to externally defined numbering or identification of questions and sections on
formally defined questionnaires. This allows extraction of the data on a form and post-processing of the data contained in a Questionnaire. Such naming is not required however 
and Questionnaires may be quite loosely defined. The section <a href="#qversusr">Questionnaire versus Resources</a> below discusses the issues of collecting data in such
loosely defined Questionnaires versus collecting data as well-defined separate Resources.
</p>
</div>

</div>





