<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<p>
A Questionnaire is a structured set of answers to a predefined list of questions. The Questionnaire can be a flat list, or can be composed
of (possibly named) sections and subsections, each containing answers. There may be multiple answers to the same question and even whole
sections may be repeated. Anwers specify the question they answer and take the form of codes, values, dates or text. Answers may explicitly
reference Observations, Procedures or other resources they are based on.</p>

<p>Questionnaires cover the need to communicate data originating from forms used in medical history examinations, research questionnaires and sometimes full
clinical speciality records. In many systems this data is collected using user-defined screens and forms. Although there is possible overlap between the 
information covered by Questionnaires and other Resources (mainly Observation, Procedure and MedicationAdministration), the process of collection and 
recording differ: Questionnaires record history while Resources are part of the registration of an ongoing clinical process. Because of this overlap,
Questionnaire allows information both to be based on on-screen forms and/or actual Observations and other Resources using Answer.evidence.</p>

<p>Questionnaires differ from Lists because Lists regroup or summarize existing information, while Questionnaires contain original, 
clinician collected data. Questionnaires differ from Documents, in that Questionnaires are independent, versionable Resources, from which
a Document may be composed.</p>

<p>A Questionnaire contains names for sections and answers, which may refer externally defined names of questions and sections on
predefined questionnaires. This way, it is not necessary to include the actual text of the questions asked or the textual captions of the
sections on a questionnaire. However, if no such definition exist, or there is a need to explicitly include the text of the questions answered, 
this text may be provided in the Answer.name and Section.name's CodeableConcept datatype. In addition, multiple-choice
questions can be answered using the Choice datatype, which allows the sender to state the text of the possible choices.</p>

<p>Examples of Questionnaires are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Past medical history (PMH)</li>
<li>Family diseases</li>
<li>Social history</li>
<li>Research questionnaires</li>
<li>Quality and evaluation forms</li>
</ul>

</div>


