<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/xhtml1-strict.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
<p>
The core extensions provide HL7 provided extensions to the <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> resource.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<h3>Questionnaire structure and validation</h3>
<p>
There are two extensions to help with defining the structure of a Questionnaire, especially useful when sending an "empty form" Questionnaire, e.g. a Questionnaire where only the questions are provided.
such Questionnaires contain the text and descriptions of sections and questions within the sections, and these two extensions provide extra information to a client displaying such
an empty Questionnaire and make it possible to do basic validation of the input. It is expected that more extensive validation for Questionnaires is added by creating new extensions.
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<b>mayRepeat</b> - This extension may be used on a Questionnaire.group to signal that this group can occur more than once in the instance. Such repeating groups contain Questions that
may repeat, often shown in a tabular form where each question is a column heading and each repeat a row in a table.
</li>
<li>
<b>answerFormat</b> - This extension may be used on Questionnaire.question and indicates the kind of answer expected. The format is either a basic input form (corresponding to the
FHIR types like string and integer) or an indication that the answer is a coded choice coming from a list of options. In the latter case, the answer may be single- or multiple-choice and
supplying free text ("Other, please specify...") may also be indicated. This format helps the client to display the correct kind of input method for such a question.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<b>omitReason</b> - A code to explicitly indicate why a question on a form was not answered (comparable to some of the ISO 21090 concepts in nullFlavor), i.e. "patient did not
want to answer", "no matching choice available" etcetera.
</li>
</ul>
</div>

</div>
