<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="notes"></a>
<h2>
Notes:
</h2>
<ul>
<li>Questionnaires may be used to represent predefined forms or panels, referenced using items of type "group"</li>
<li>Questions may be nested.  The Questionnaire resource supports nested items beneath both items of type "group" (which doesn't capture an answer of its own) as well as beneath questions</li>
<li>Groups and Questions may have linkIds allowing groups and question answers captured in a <a href="questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a>
to be associated with their corresponding group or question.</li>
<li>Questionnaire allows for flexible naming and structuring of its contents to reflect the flexible and varying nature of forms and questionnaires.
It explicitly does not try to standardize or streamline exchange of its contents outside its context of use, although exchanging partners may further
constrain its structure and flexibility using profiles to define standardized, reusable forms.</li>
<li>Because of the lack of explicit support for Questionnaires in <a href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186">HL7 v3</a>, <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> Documents frequently used named sections with
Observations to model Questionnaires. Such use cases should now use the Questionnaire Resource instead.</li>
<li>The order of questions within groups, groups within groups and groups within questions is relevant and must be retained for display and capture.</li>
<li>Display items allow the inclusion of instructions, background information and similar content within a questionnaire.</li>
<li>In cases where it is necessary or appropriate to capture the reason why a response is missing (that is, why a particular question was not answered), there should be an explicit child item defined for the relevant question(s) in the Questionnaire; e.g. add a child question of "Reason not specified:" with an enableWhen operator "not exists" to the parent question.</li>
</ul>

<a name="sdc"> </a>
<h3>Structured Data Capture</h3>
<p>
The base questionnaire resource is aimed at the capabilities of "most" healthcare systems that deal with forms and questionnaires.  While the resource structure
supports a reasonable degree of complexity, it doesn't provide the degree of control over rendering, question flow and data management needed by some portions 
of the healthcare space.  Many of these more sophisticated requirements are addressed by a supplemental implementation guide called 
<a href="http://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/sdc/">Structured Data Capture (SDC)</a>.  This implementation guide covers the following capabilities, plus several others:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Rendering grids of questions, multi-column drop-downs, multi-language questionnaires, and other 'advanced' formatting capabilities</li>
  <li>Advanced dynamic questionnaires including calculated scores, enabling of questions and groups based on complex logic, drop-downs driven by answers to other questions</li>
  <li>Support for populating questionnaires from existing clinical data based on the current patient, encounter, etc., including the ability to render the form as HTML or to redirect to a website to complete unanswered items</li>
  <li>Support for extracting information from a completed QuestionnaireResponse to generate other FHIR resources such as Observations, MedicationUsages, etc.</li>
  <li>Support for completing 'adaptive' questionnaires (see below)</li>
</ul>

<a name="adaptive"> </a>
<h3>Adaptive Questionnaires</h3>
<p>
Some questionnaires might not provide a full listing of questions, instead relying on a service to interactively sending partially completed forms to a server which generates the next set of questions.  
As such, some questionnaires might be 'active' but have either no questions or an insufficient set of questions for their purpose.  Further guidance on the use of such forms, can be found in the <a href="#sdc">SDC</a> implementation guide.
</p>

<a name="qversusr"></a>
<h3>Using Questionnaires versus using Resources</h3>
<p>
There is considerable overlap between the information covered by <b>Questionnaires</b> and other Resources (especially <a href="familymemberhistory.html">FamilyMemberHistory</a>,
<a href="medicationusage.html">MedicationUsage</a>, <a href="observation.html">Observation</a>, <a href="procedure.html">Procedure</a>, etc.).
<b>Questionnaire's</b> flexible structure can easily be misused to capture any data, even data that should be captured as separate Resources. The choice between using <b>Questionnaires</b> or separate
Resources may be dictated by the procedure of collection and recording; e.g. if the data is captured as a physician-agreed (electronic) form, it might be impossible or undesirable to
distill separate resources from it and capturing the data in a <b>Questionnaire</b> would be most appropriate.
</p>

<p>
However, data captured only in <b>Questionnaires</b> can be difficult to query after-the-fact. Queries against other Resources will not return data captured only in <b>Questionnaires</b>
and querying against <b>Questionnaires</b> directly might not find all desired data, depending on how the questions may have been phrased or encoded over time or by different clinicians.
Moreover, interoperability of such <b>Questionnaires</b> is limited, as interpretation of its contents is only known to the circle of parties that were involved in its definition: encoding data from
such <b>Questionnaires</b> using more specific resources increases the availability of the information they contain.
</p>

<p>
It is entirely possible for data to exist in both QuestionnaireResponse and in other resources.  For example, data may be captured in
<a href="questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> as part of an intake questionnaire.  That data may then be propagated into the
<a href="patient.html">Patient</a> resource (demographics), <a href="familymemberhistory.html">FamilyMemberHistory</a>, <a href="allergyintolerance.html">AllergyIntolerance</a>,
<a href="medicationusage.html">MedicationUsage</a> and <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> resources to allow the data to be queried and analyzed.  The original
<a href="questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> instance can be retained for traceability purposes.  If desired, a <a href="provenance.html">Provenance</a> resource
can be used to identify the Questionnaire as the data source for the other resources.  For example, if a questionnaire question asks "what is your weight", an <a href="observation.html">Observation</a> with the appropriate <code>Observation.code</code> and the specified answer as the
<code>Observation.valueQuantity</code> can be created.
</p>

<a name="profiling"> </a>
<h3>Profiling Questionnaires</h3>
<p>
<a href="profiling.html">Profiling</a> can be used to define the constraints of a set of Questionnaires - for example that a particular system only supports Questionnaires where answers have certain data types, only recognizes certain extensions, mandates the presence of certain metadata, etc.  However, profiling should NOT be used to define the content of a specific Questionnaire instance.  To define a Questionnaire instance, simply create an instance of Questionnaire as you would any other resource.
</p>

<a name="structure"> </a>
<h3>Structure of the Questionnaire</h3>
<p>
A Questionnaire is built out of two components, Questionnaire and item:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The main component is Questionnaire, which holds information <em>about</em> the Questionnaire,
  like the identifier, publisher, date authored, title, etc. The Questionnaire contains zero or more items which define the content of the questionnaire  (zero items allows for the possibility of narrative-only questionnaires, though these provide little computable information).</li>
  <li>Items have one of three sub-types, distinguished by the <code>type</code> element:
    <ul>
      <li><b>display</b> items convey text to be rendered on the form that won't capture data and which won't contain nested items.  This might include copyright or authorship information,
        instructions or other background information.</li>
      <li><b>group</b> items organize content of the questionnaire into sections, sub-sections, etc.  Groups don't have answers associated with them directly, but generally contain child
        'question' items which do.  </li>
      <li><b>question</b> items ask a specific question to which an answer may be given.  There isn't a single
        <code>type</code> for question items. Instead, the type conveys the data type of the answer for the question.  If an item isn't a 'display' or a 'group', 
        then it's a question which allows a particular type of answer to be gathered. Questions may also have nested content - groups and/or
        other questions. This way, one can model "panels" of questions which would only be relevant (and thus would only be displayed)
        depending on the answers of a parent question; e.g. a question "Did the patient receive treatment in the past six months?" would contain a nested
        group of questions asking for further details about the treatment. See an <a href="questionnaire-example-bluebook.xml.html">example</a> from
        the <a href="http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/Kids/Publications/my-personal-health-record.pdf">Australian New South Wales blue book</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
Specific controls on dynamic display of groups, questions, etc. based on the answers to other questions is outside the scope of the base resource and
are handled using extensions.
</p>
<p>
Group text is intended to provide a "label" for a collection of nested items.  The text will often be rendered in a "heading" style.  As such, it should be kept relatively short.  
Detailed instructions should be conveyed by a nested "display" item.  It's not necessary to create groups in order to relate an instruction to a collection of questions - you can simply intermix
display items and questions or groups, with the expectation that users will see the display text before encountering the following questions. 
</p>

<a name="group"> </a>
<h3>Group properties</h3>
<p>
Some properties defined at the 'group' level will impact the behavior of everything within the group.  For example, if a 'group' item is marked as readOnly=true, then all items within that
group are automatically treated as readOnly - even if they explicitly declare readOnly=false.  The same holds for enableWhen.  If a group is 'disabled' based on its enableWhen settings, then
all child items are automatically disabled - regardless of whether they have enableWhen declared or how those enableWhen conditions might resolve.  Some extensions (e.g. the SDC 'hidden'
extension) behave in the same manner.  Systems MAY choose to raise errors or warnings if questionnaires have conflicting settings.  E.g. if a group is marked as readOnly=true and a descendant
item explicitly declares readOnly=false.  This wouldn't be because the behavior is unclear, but more to draw the author's attention to the fact that their desired behavior for the child will
not be realized due to the setting of the ancestor group.
</p>
<p>
Behavior of parent 'question' items (i.e. questions with child groups or questions) can also influence descendant elements, but not as strongly.  If a question is readOnly, that doesn't mean that
child items are also readOnly.  However, if a question is disabled, all descendant items are also disabled.  Similarly, a 'hidden' question, would hide child elements as well.
</p>


<a name="identifiers"> </a>
<h3>Identifiers within Questionnaire</h3>
<p>There are three different "identifying" elements within Questionnaire: <code>identifier</code>, <code>id</code> and <code>linkId</code>.  Each serves very distinct
purposes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The <b>identifier</b> element is used to reference the overall questionnaire in business terms.  It is the number printed across the top of the form or listed beside the form
  when making a choice between alternate forms.</li>
  <li>The <b>id</b> attribute supported on each element is used for references within a resource, for example linking narrative to discrete elements.  Ids are not generally displayed to end users</li>
  <li>The <b>linkId</b> element on questions and groups establishes a link between elements in a <a href="questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> and their
  definition inside a Questionnaire.  This is the <i>only</i> way to link between the groups and questions in a Questionnaire and QuestionnaireResponse.  These are also not displayed to end users</li>
</ul>

<a name="definition"> </a>
<h3>Question Definitions</h3>
<p>
Questionnaires can be crafted using any questions the author can conceive and can be phrased in whatever manner is appropriate or convenient.  However, standardization of
questions and the constraints enforced on the accompanying answers increases the ability to compare data gathered across questionnaires. 
Items can be directly linked to an <a href="elementdefinition.html">ElementDefinition</a> using <code>Questionnaire.item.definition</code>
which provides details for the item. If a definition is provided, then the following element values can be derived from the definition:
</p>
<ul>
<li>code (from ElementDefinition.code)</li>
<li>text (from ElementDefinition.label)</li>
<li>required (inferred from ElementDefinition.min)</li>
<li>repeats (inferred from ElementDefinition.max)</li>
<li>maxLength (from ElementDefinition.maxLength)</li>
<li>answerValueSet (from ElementDefinition.binding.valueSet)</li>
<li>initial.value[x] or fixed[x] (from ElementDefinition.defaultValue[x] - depending on whether readOnly is set)</li>
</ul>
<p>
QuestionnaireResponse.item.type corresponds to ElementDefinition.type, however item.type is madatory in Questionniare, so it
can't be 'populated' because it must exist for the item to exist at all.  However, the values specified for item.type and ElementDefinition.type  do need to correspond.  Complex types such as Address or anything based
on BackboneElement would correspond to 'group', while simple types would normally map directly.
</p>
<p>
In addition, extensions and elements that have corresponding extensions should also propagate.  Specifically:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Any extensions that have a context of both ElementDefinition and Questionnaire.item (e.g. <a href="extension-maxsize.html">maxSize</a>) should propagate</li>
  <li>Any extensions defined for Questionnaire.item that directly correspond to elements on ElementDefinition should also propagate.  E.g.:
    <ul>
      <li>ElementDefinition.minValue[x] -> <a href="extension-minvalue.html">minValue</a></li>
      <li>ElementDefinition.maxValue[x] -> <a href="extension-maxvalue.html">maxValue</a></li>
      <li>There are Questionnaire extensions defined in the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc">SDC IG</a> that correspond to min, max, type.targetProfile and constraint</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Any information provided in these elements overrides the information from the definition, and some are always required to be populated so that invariants can be enforced, etc. 
The url refers to an ElementDefinition in  <a href="structuredefinition.html">StructureDefinition</a>, and always starts with the canonical URL for the target resource.
When referring to a StructureDefinition, a fragment identifier is used to specify the element definition by its
id (Element.id). E.g. http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/Observation#Observation.value[x]. In the absence
of a fragment identifier, the first/root element definition in the target is the matching element definition. Examples:
</p> 
<table class="grid">
 <tr><td>Value of definition</td><td>Explanation</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/Observation#Observation.effectiveDateTime</code></td><td>A reference to the standard Observation element <code>effectiveDateTime</code></td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>http://example.org/definitions/xxx</code></td><td>A reference to the <a href="structuredefinition.html#logical">logical model</a> "xxx" that represents a data element</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>http://example.org/StructureDefinition/Oedema#Observation.category:XXX</code></td><td>A reference to slice <code>XXX</code> on the Observation <code>category</code> element on an Oedema Scale profile</td></tr>
 <tr><td><code>http://example.org/StructureDefinition/Oedema|2.0#Observation.category:XXX</code></td><td>A reference to slice <code>XXX</code> on the Observation <code>category</code> element on an Oedema Scale profile, specifying version 2.0</td></tr>
</table>
<p>
The definitions may also be used to automatically pre-populate answers, or extract data from a corresponding pre-existing <a href="questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> resource.
</p>
<p>
Note that LOINC codes <a href="https://terminology.hl7.org/LOINC.html">implicitly</a> define logical models whose elements can be considered question definitions.
</p>
<p>
NOTE: Even if a standard question definition is provided<!--s are referenced using <code>concept</code> or the <code>deReference</code> extension-->, information such as the question text,
data type and value set SHOULD still be declared for the question.  Systems processing the questionnaire might not have access to or support the ability to look
up the question definitions from external sources.  If the information is not included in-line within the questionnaire, other systems might not be able to render
or use the Questionnaire.  The <a href="extension-questionnaire-definitionbased.html">questionnaire-definitionBased</a> extension can be used to flag that a questionnaire requires the
ability to resolve and use item.definition information to fully understand the Questionnaire.  Systems that validate, render or otherwise process the questionnaire SHOULD check for this
extension.
</p>
<p>
If an external definition <!--reference (<code>concept</code> or <code>deReference</code> extension)--> is included along with question information such as question text, data type or
value set, it is expected that the content for the question and the referenced definition would be in alignment.  However, FHIR does not dictate what degree of
alignment is required; e.g. Does the question text need to match exactly?  Is it legitimate for a question to constrain the allowed value set of possible answers?
These rules will need to be established within implementation environments.
</p>

<a name="question-types"> </a>
<h3>Question types</h3>
<p>
The codes for the data type for each question are slightly different than the data types allowed in the <a href="questionnaireresponse.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> resource.
Where the names are the same (ignoring case), the "answer" must use the specified type.  Where the names are different, the mappings are as follows:
</p>
<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <th>Questionnaire AnswerFormat code</th>
      <th>QuestionnaireResponse data type</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>text</td>
      <td><a href="datatypes.html#string">string</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>url</td>
      <td><a href="datatypes.html#uri">uri</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>coding</td>
      <td><a href="datatypes.html#Coding">Coding</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<a name="choices"></a>
<h3>Permitted values for questions</h3>
<p>
Many questionnaires place constraints on the allowed list of values for a given question.  FHIR supports this notion through the <code>item.answerValueSet</code> or the
<code>item.answerOption</code> element.
</p>
<p>
The "answerOption" mechanism is simplest - all possible answers are listed in-line with the question using the <code>item.answerOption</code> element.  Maintenance of the set of permitted question answers involves maintenance of
the questionnaire itself.
</p>
<p>
The "answerValueSet" mechanism is more sophisticated.  Rather than listing the possible answers directly, the <code>item.answerValueSet</code> element refers to a <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a> resource.  This approach adds complexity for
questionnaires having a simple list of strings as choices for a question, but provides several benefits, including:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Questionnaires that reference codes from externally defined code systems have a means of doing so</li>
  <li>Answer sets can be shared across questions (and there are many questionnaires where this capability is useful)</li>
  <li>The full capability of value sets can be brought into play, including the ability to use ConceptMap to link and translate from questionnaire-specific codes to
  other codes, the use of multiple display names (e.g. different languages), the ability to use coded ordinals, and the ability to allow choices from larger value sets
  (e.g. "all SNOMED CT procedure codes")</li>
</ul>
<p>
In many cases, the set of code choices will be specific to a given questionnaire and should be maintained as part of the questionnaire.  In this case, the referenced
ValueSet can be included as a <a href="references.html#contained">contained</a> resource.  All contained ValueSets are listed together and then are referenced by the
individual questions as necessary.  Alternatively, the <code>item.answerValueSet</code> element can reference the value set in a version-specific manner.  This ensures that the Questionnaire
will not adopt a new version of the referenced value set without revising the Questionnaire to point to that new version - putting the author of the Questionnaire
in control of any changes.
</p>

<a name="valuesets"> </a>
<h3>Useful Value Sets</h3>
<p>
Many questions have a common set of possible codes for their answer. These value sets may be useful to help,
and when referenced by full URL, do not need to be provided as part of the questionnaire:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="valueset-example-yesnodontknow.html">Yes | No | Don't Know</a>: http://hl7.org/fhir/ValueSet/yesnodontknow</li>
</ul>

<a name="booleans"> </a>
<h3>Handling Boolean Answers</h3>
<p>
In a questionnaire response, a question of type 'boolean' can have 3 possible states - unanswered, answered true, and answered false.  Users will generally need to be able to toggle through all three states.  If a default
value is specified and the element is mandatory, a simple control with only true and false options will suffice.  However, if a three-state selection is required,
the typical controls used in HTML and other rendering technologies for booleans might not be appropriate.  E.g. a checkbox that can only convey 'true' or 'false' will not be able to differentiate 'unanswered' and thus is generally not
appropriate.  If a tri-state control is available, that would work well.  Alternatively, a set of radio buttons allow choices of true, false or "no answer" could also work.
</p>
<p>
As well, when enableWhen expressions are used that reference boolean elements, designers should consider whether "non-answered" is a possible value for boolean questions and design their enableWhen logic accordingly.
</p>

<a name="polymorphic"> </a>
<h3>Questions with multiple answer types</h3>
<p>
In some questionnaires, it may be possible to respond to a question with multiple types of answers.  For example, capturing a coded answer plus free text,
capturing a coded value plus a numeric priority, etc.  In FHIR, this is handled through nested questions.  Each question has a single data type.  However,
each question can have nested child questions.  These nested child questions can have text (e.g. "Please specify") or can have no text at all if the appropriate
guidance is provided by the parent question or group.
</p>

<a name="math"> </a>
<h3>Questionnaires with Math</h3>
<p>
Many questionnaires involve computations on questionnaire answers, e.g. tabulating scores.

To help with associating numeric values to coded answers, the <a href="extension-ordinalvalue.html">ordinalValue</a> 
extension can be used to define the numeric weighting of a code defined in a value set or in the questionnaire itself.
</p>

<p>In addition, there are extensions for defining the dynamic value of an element using expressions. For more information, see the 
<a href="clinicalreasoning-topics-using-expressions.html">Using Expressions</a> and <a href="clinicalreasoning-knowledge-artifact-representation.html#documentation-template">Documentation Template</a> 
topics in the Clinical Reasoning module.</p>

<a name="workflow"> </a>
<h3>Questionnaire workflow</h3>
<p>
Once a Questionnaire is defined, there's often a need to 'assign' a Questionnaire to a particular individual to request them to complete it.  This is not done using the Questionnaire resource
directly.  Instead, the Questionnaire is referenced as an 'input' or argument using one of FHIR's <a href="workflow-communications.html">workflow patterns</a>.  The most common mechanism is by
defining a stand-alone Task that references the Questionnaire and seeks completion.  The SDC implementation guide defines profiles and guidance for using this mechanism.
</p>

<a name="advanced"> </a>
<h3>More advanced questionnaires</h3>
<p>
The capabilities of the Questionnaire resource are fairly simple and try to adhere to what most systems that deal with questionnaires would be capable of.
However, there are lots of systems that require more sophisticated capabilities, such as:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Greater control over rendering, including tables, read-only values, hidden answers, multi-column drop-downs</li>
  <li>Greater control over question flow, including formula-based rules for conditional display of elements</li>
  <li>Ability to pre-populate forms with data found in the client system</li>
  <li>Ability to define how to convert a completed QuestionnaireResponse for a Questionnaire into a collection of Observations and/or other resources</li>
</ul>
<p>
Extensions have been defined for all of these purposes and many more.  (Questionnaire has the most 'core' extensions of any resource to-date.)  A list of these
extensions can be found <a href="questionnaire-profiles.html#extensions">here</a>.  However, some of the extensions are complex and work together in particular
ways.  To support more advanced questionnaire implementation, the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc">Structured Data Capture (SDC)</a> implementation guide has been 
created to provide non-country-specific guidance on the use of most of these extensions and sets expectations for systems wishing to support more complex forms.
</p>
</div>
