<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h3>Language and translations</h3>
<p>
In some environments, it may be necessary for a questionnaire to support multiple languages.  The rendering tool would select the appropriate
language based on a configuration setting, or perhaps would display all available languages and the user would read the one they are familiar with.
Systems MAY choose to provide support for identifying language and translations.  If they do, they SHALL do so using the generic language and
translation extensions FHIR defines based on the ISO21090 data type specification:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090.html#language">http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090#language</a> allows the language of a particular (or any other data type) to be identified</li>
  <li><a href="http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090.html#string-translation">http://hl7.org/Profile/iso21090#string-translation</a> allows additional repetitions in alternate languages to be communicated.  
  (The language for each translation would be communicated using the above #language extension)</li>
</ul>
<p>
These extensions can be used on absolutely any string element on <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a>, <a href="valueset.html">ValueSet</a>, one of 
the data types or any other resource.  The base string should be the primary language of the questionnaire.  It is what will be rendered by systems that do
not support the translation extension or by systems whose language preference is other than one of the languages provided.
</p>
<p>
The ISO 19763 specification permits declaring language on questionnaire titles, descriptions, display names for codesand many other strings.  It also supports
capturing multiple variants of these strings with distinct languages.  These capabilities can be mirrored using the above extensions.
</p>

<h3>Extensions</h3>
<p>
This profile defines a number of extensions that are expected to be specific to use within the U.S. Structured Data Capture (SDC) initiative
(though they are welcome to be used whereever they might be useful).  The specific extensions defined include:
</p>
<ul>
<!--  <li><a name="additionalTitle"/><a name="additionalTitle.value"/><a name="additionalTitle.context"/><b>additionalTitle</b>:
    Conveys alternate titles for the questionnaire along with the context/purpose for that alternate title</li>
  <li><a name="additionalQuestionnaireDescription"/><a name="additionalQuestionnaireDescription.value"/>
    <a name="additionalQuestionnaireDescription.context"/><b>additionalQuestionnaireDescription</b>: Conveys alternate
    descriptions of the questionnaire intended for use by different consumers along with who the description is for</li>
  <li><a name="securityPrivacy"/><b>securityPrivacy</b>: Information on how completed versions of the questionnaire should
    be treated from a security/privacy perspective</li>-->
  <li><a name="endpoint"/><b>endpoint</b>: The base URI of the server to which 
    <a href="questionnaireanswers.html">QuestionnaireAnswers</a> associated with a
    <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> should be sent</li>
  <li><a name="specialGroup"/><b>specialGroup</b>: Allows flagging a particular group as a header or footer for rendering
    purposes</li>
  <li><a name="additionalGroupText"/><a name="additionalGroupText.value"/><a name="additionalGroupText.context"/>
    <b>additionalGroupText</b>: Additional text to be rendered or made available along with a 
    <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> group</li>
  <li><a name="additionalQuestionText"/><a name="additionalQuestionText.value"/><a name="additionalQuestionText.context"/>
    <b>additionalQuestionText</b>: Additional text to be rendered or made available along with a
    <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaire</a> question</li>
</ul>

</div>





