<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h3>Notes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Conceptually, a bundle is a list of resources with some context (named links, and status on the entries)</li>
<li>Since a Bundle is itself a <a href="resource.html">Resource</a> it has the same common metadata as all resources, including profile assertions, tags, and security labels</li>
</ul>

<h3>Resolving references in Bundles</h3>

<p>
Bundle has a 'base' element, which is used to resolve relative references present in the bundled resources. 
In the case that the bundle includes resources with different bases, each entry can also assert it's 
applicable base if this is different to the overall base. A base SHOULD always be specified, either
in the bundle itself, or on each entry.
</p>
<p>
Applications reading a bundle should always <a href="references.html#bundle-refs">look for a resource</a> 
by its identity in the bundle first before trying to access it by its URL.
</p>

<p>
The <code>id</code> property of a resource is a relative URI. In the case of the RESTful API, the 
id is relative to the system base URL such that the absolute URI of the resource is:
</p>
<pre>
[base]/[Type]/[id]
</pre>
<p>
When resolving references with in a bundle, the resolution is against the absolute URI. 
For instance, if a resource with a stated base of http://example.org/fhir has a reference
with a value of Patient/2341, then it will resolve to a Patient resource with an id of 
2341 and a base of http://example.org/fhir, which is an absolute URI of 
http://example.org/fhir/Patient/2341.
</p>
<p>
There is one special case: for a base URI of urn:uuid: or urn:oid:, the absolute 
URI does not include the type of the resource:
</p>
<pre>
[base][id]
</pre>
<p>
OIDs and UUIDs are intended for use where the resource the entry is for has no established identity 
on an existing RESTful interface.
</p>




</div>