<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<a name="notes"> </a>
<h3>Notes about Bundle</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Conceptually, a bundle is a list of resources with some context (named links, and status on the entries)</li>
  <li>Since a Bundle is itself a <a href="resource.html">Resource</a> it has the same common metadata as all resources, including profile assertions, tags, and security labels</li>
  <li>Although there are no extensions on the Bundle itself, <code>link</code>, <code>entry</code>, and <code>search</code>/<code>request</code>/<code>response</code> can all have extensions. See <a href="patient.html#match">Patient</a> and <a href="location.html#positional">Location</a> for examples on search</li>
  <li>Both Bundle.link and Bundle.entry.link are defined to support providing additional context when Bundles are used (e.g. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HATEOAS">HATEOAS</a>). 
    Bundle.entry.link corresponds to links found in the HTTP header if the resource in the entry was <a href="http.html#read">read</a> directly.
    This specification defines some specific uses of Bundle.link for <a href="search.html#conformance">searching</a> and <a href="http.html#paging">paging</a>, but no specific uses for Bundle.entry.link, and no defined function in a transaction - meaning is implementation specific</li>
  <li>Bundles have both .id and .identifier - see <a href="resource.html#id">Resource Identities</a> for further information</li>  
</ul>

<a name="using"></a>

<h3>Using Bundles</h3>

<p>
The content and rules for using a Bundle depend on the <a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.type">type</a> of the bundle. 
Note that all bundle types use resource identity resolution as described below.
</p>

<a name="document"></a>
<h4>Document</h4>

<p>
A document Bundle (type = "document") consists of a series of 
entries, the first of which is a <a href="composition.html">Composition</a>. 
Each entry element SHALL contain a resource. See <a href="documents.html">Documents</a>
for further information.
</p>

<p><a href="document-example-dischargesummary.html">Example</a></p>

<a name="message"></a>
<h4>Message</h4>

<p>
A message Bundle (type = "message") consists of a series of 
entries, the first of which is a <a href="messageheader.html">MessageHeader</a>. 
Each entry element SHALL contain a resource. See <a href="messaging.html">Messaging</a>
for further information.
</p>

<p>Example <a href="message-request-link.html">Request</a> and <a href="message-response-link.html">Response</a></p>

<a name="searchset"></a>
<h4>Search Results</h4>

<p>
A set of search results (type = "searchset") consists of a series of 
0 or more entries. Each entry element SHALL contain a resource. See <a href="http.html#search">Search</a>
for further information.
</p>
<p>
In addition, <a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.total">Bundle.total</a> may be 
used to return the total number of resources that match the search, and that may be 
returned by following the "next" <a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.link">link</a>.
</p>
<p>
For each entry, a search set can also contain two specific pieces of search related
information:
</p>
<ul>
 <li><a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.entry.search.mode">search.mode</a>: An indication of whether the resource is in the search set because it matched the search criteria or whether it is included because another resource refers to it (e.g. by the <a href="search.html#include">_include</a> parameter)</li>
 <li><a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.entry.search.score">search.score</a>: The server's search ranking score for the entry. Servers are not required to return a ranking score, but if they do, 1 is most relevant, and 0 is least relevant. Note: often, search results are sorted by score, but the client may specify a different sort order (see <a href="search.html#score">Search Relevance</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="bundle-example.html">Example</a></p>

<a name="history"></a>
<h4>History</h4>

<p>
A change history (type = "history") consists of a series of 
0 or more entries. Each entry element SHALL contain a request element that describes the change
that was made and, if the method is a POST or PUT, a resource that represents the state of the 
resource at the conclusion of the operation. A response element SHALL also be present so that consumers
can access the <code>location</code> header. See <a href="http.html#history">History</a> for further information.
</p>
<p>
In addition, <a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.total">Bundle.total</a> may be 
used to return the total number of resources that are included in the change history, 
including those that may be returned by following the "next" <a href="bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.link">link</a>.
</p>

<a name="transaction"></a>
<h4>Transaction / Batch</h4>

<p>
A transaction (type = "transaction") or batch (type = "batch") consists of a series of 0 or more entries. 
Each entry element SHALL contain a request element has the details of an HTTP operation that informs the system 
processing the transaction what to do with the entry. If the entry method is a 'PUT' or 
'POST', then the entry SHALL contain a resource that becomes the body of the HTTP operation. 
See <a href="http.html#transaction">Transactions</a> for further information. 
</p>

<p><a href="bundle-transaction.html">Example</a></p>

<a name="transaction-response"></a>
<h4>Transaction/Batch Response</h4>

<p>
A transaction response (type = "transaction-response") or batch response (type="batch-response") 
consists of a series of 0 or more entries: 1 for each entry in the transaction or batch it is in response to. 
Each entry element SHALL contain a <code>response</code> element which indicates 
the outcome of the HTTP operation that the server performed for the entry. 
</p>

<p><a href="bundle-response.html">Example</a></p>

<a name="collection"></a>
<h4>Collection</h4>

<p>
A collection (type = "collection") consists of a series of 
0 or more entries. No particular use with respect to the FHIR specification is associated with this Bundle.
Each entry element SHALL contain a resource.
</p>

<p><a href="diagnosticreport-examples.html">Example</a></p>

<a name="subscription-notification"></a>
<h4>Subscription Notification</h4>
[%StandardsStatus trial-use BundleType n/a%]
<p>
A subscription notification (type = "subscription-notification") consists of a series of 
1 or more entries, the first of which is a <a href="subscriptionstatus.html">SubscriptionStatus</a>. There 
may be additional contents, as specified by the subscription responsible for generating the notification. See 
<a href="subscription.html">Subscription</a> for further information.
</p>

<p><a href="subscriptionstatus-examples.html">Examples</a></p>


<a name="bundle-unique"></a>
<h2>Resource URL &amp; Uniqueness rules in a bundle</h2>

<p>
Except for transactions and batches, each entry in a <code>Bundle</code> must have a <code>fullUrl</code> 
which is the identity of the resource in the entry. Note that this is not a versioned reference to the resource, but its 
identity. Where a resource is not assigned a persistent identity that can be used
in the Bundle, a UUID should be used (urn:uuid:...).
</p>
<p>
For transactions and batches, entries MAY not have fullURLs when the entry.request.method = POST, 
and the resource has no identity. Note that even in this case, there may still be a fullURL in a 
transaction on a POST so that relationships between resources can be represented (see <a href="http.html#transaction">Transactions</a>).
</p>
<p>
A given version of a resource SHALL only appear once in each Bundle. There might, however, 
be multiple versions of a single resource present in a single bundle. This would be expected
in Bundles of type <code>history</code>, and also might be necessitated by closely tracking
Provenance. 
</p>
<p>
Note that the meaning of an unversioned reference to a resource that appears multiple times 
is potentially ambiguous, though processors may have additional informaton to help resolve 
this (e.g. change order in a history bundle).
</p>
<p>
When processing batches and transactions, it is at server discretion how to behave if multiple
versions of a single resource are present.
</p>


<a name="resolving"></a>
<a name="references"></a>
<h3>Resolving references in Bundles</h3>

<p>
The <code>Bundle</code> resource is a packaging construct that has one of more entries that 
are other kinds of resources. Those resources themselves have references to other resources - e.g. 
an Observation that refers to a Patient. The referenced resources may also be found
in the Bundle. For example, the system that constructed the Bundle may have included both
the Observation and the Patient. The content of the references between resources doesn't 
change because of the bundle.
</p>
<p>
This section documents a method that resolves references correctly within a bundle. Note
that this method does not define any new semantics; resolution is based on the way
resource identity and resource references work.
</p>
<p>
Applications reading a Bundle should always <a href="references.html#bundle-refs">look for a resource</a> 
by its identity in the bundle first before trying to access it by its URL externally.
</p>
<p>
How to resolve a reference in a Bundle:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>If the reference is not an absolute reference, convert it to an absolute URL:
  <ul>
	 <li>if the reference has the format [type]/[id], and</li>
   <li>if the fullUrl for the bundle entry containing the resource is a RESTful one (see the <a href="references.html#regex">RESTful URL regex</a>) 
	  <ul>
     <li>extract the [root] from the fullUrl, and append the reference (type/id) to it</li>
     <li>then try to resolve within the bundle as for a RESTful URL reference. </li>
     <li>If no resolution is possible, then the reference has no defined meaning within this specification</li>
 	  </ul>
	 </li>
   <li>else no resolution is possible and the reference has no defined meaning within this specification</li>
	</ul>
 </li>
 <li>else 
  <ul>
   <li>Look for an entry with a fullUrl that matches the URI in the reference</li>
   <li>if no match is found, and the URI is a URL that can be resolved (e.g. if an http: URL), try accessing it directly)</li>
  </ul>
 </li>
</ul>

<p>
Note, in addition, that a reference may be by identifier, and if it is, and there is no URL, it may be 
resolved by scanning the ids in the bundle. Note also that transactions may contain <a href="http.html#trules">conditional references</a>  
that must be resolved by the server before processing the matches.
</p>
<p>
If the reference is version specific (either relative or absolute), then remove the version from the 
URL before matching fullUrl, and then match the version based on <code>Resource.meta.versionId</code>.
Note that the rules for resolving references in contained resources are the same as those for 
resolving resources in the resource that contains the contained resource.
</p>
<p>
If multiple matches are found, it is ambiguous which is correct. Applications MAY return an error or take some other action as they deem appropriate.
</p>

<p>
There is an <a href="bundle-references.html">example Bundle that demonstrates</a> these rules.
</p>



<a name="rest"></a>
<h3>Serving Bundles using the RESTful API</h3>

<p>
The Bundle resource type has an end-point like all most other resources. This 
end-point serves the <a href="http.html#interactions">usual interactions</a>.
Bundles are treated as static resources on the /Bundle end-point (i.e. when a
batch, transaction, or message is POSTed to /Bundle, it is stored as is, and 
the content is not processed as batch, transaction, or message - instead, they
are processed like normal resource, with indexing / auditing etc. Performing a 
GET /[base]/Bundle/[location] will return the same resource.
</p>
<p>
The Bundle end point does have two special search parameters - <code>composition</code> and <code>message</code>,
which allow for chained search into the first (special) entries in document and message resources.
</p>


<a name="signature"> </a>
<h3>Signatures</h3>

<p>
The Bundle resource includes a <i>signature</i> element (digital signature) which can be used for 
standards based integrity verification and non-repudiation purposes. The <a href="dataypes.html#Signature">Signature</a> datatype
provides details on use of the <i>signature</i> element. The Signature.type coded value of "Source" should be used
when the signature is for simply proving that the resource content is the same as it was when the resource
was updated or created.
</p>

</div>
