<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<div>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>

<p>
One common operation performed with resources is to gather a collection of resources into a single instance
with containing context. In FHIR this is referred to as "bundling" the resources together. These resource bundles are useful for a variety of different reasons, including:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Returning a set of resources that meet some criteria as part of a server operation (see <a href="http.html#search">RESTful Search</a>)</li>
  <li>Returning a set of versions of resources as part of the history operation on a server  (see <a href="http.html#history">History</a>)</li>
  <li>Sending a set of resources as part of a message exchange (see <a href="messaging.html">Messaging</a>)</li>
  <li>Grouping a self-contained set of resources to act as an exchangeable and persistable collection with clinical integrity - e.g. a clinical document (see <a href="documents.html">Documents</a>)</li>
  <li>Creating/updating/deleting a set of resources as a single atomic transaction on a server (see <a href="http.html#transaction">Transactions</a>)</li>
  <li>Storing a collection of resources</li>
</ul>

</div>

<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
There are two ways to collect resources together for transport and persistance purposes - <a href="references.html#contained">contained resources</a>, and
bundles. There is an important difference between the two: 
</p>
<ul>
 <li>Contained resources are "in" the container resource - they can only ever be interpreted and/or changed in the context of the container</li>
 <li>A bundle is a collection of resources that have an independent existence - the source of the resource can be determined by the base (see below) and the logical id</li>
</ul>

<p>
In addition to these two technical mechanism, there are three administrative and infrastructure resources which also support grouping of content:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
The <a href="list.html">List</a> resource - enumerates a flat collection of resources and provides features for managing the collection.  
While a particular List instance may represent a "snapshot", from a business process perspective the notion of "List" 
is dynamic – items are added and removed over time.  The list resource references other resources.  Lists may be 
curated and have specific business meaning.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="group.html">Group</a> resource - defines a group of specific people, animals, devices, etc. by enumerating them, 
or by describing qualities that group members have. The group resource refers to other resources, possibly implicitly.  
Groups are intended to be acted upon or observed as a whole.  E.g. performing therapy on a group, calculating risk for a group, 
etc.  This resource will commonly be used for public health (e.g. describing an at-risk population), clinical trials (e.g. 
defining a test subject pool) and similar purposes.
</li>
<li>
The <a href="composition.html">Composition</a> resource – defines a set of healthcare-related information that is assembled 
together into a single logical document that provides a single coherent statement of meaning, establishes its own context and 
that has clinical attestation with regard to who is making the statement. The composition resource provides the basic structure 
of a FHIR <a href="documents.html">document</a>.  The full content of the document is expressed using a bundle.  Compositions will 
often reference Lists as the focus of particular sections.
</li>
</ul>

</div>
</div>
