<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <a name="scope"></a>
    <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
    <p>
      A task resource describes an activity that can be performed and tracks the state of
      completion of that activity. It is a representation that an activity should be or has been
      initiated, and eventually, represents the successful or unsuccessful completion of that
      activity.
    </p>
    <p> Concretely the Task resource could be used in FHIR to serve different purposes like: </p>
<ul>
<li>operationalizing a Request (but could exists without a Request)</li>
<li>communicate between Filler and Placer</li>
<li>tracking of business status (i.e. collection of specimen, dispense of medication, procedure scheduled)</li>
<li>communicate the results of the execution (e.g. via .output)</li>
</ul>

    <p> Note that there are a variety of processes associated with making and processing orders.
      Some orders may be handled immediately by automated systems but most require real-world
      actions by one or more humans. Some orders can only be processed when other real-world actions
      happen, such as a patient presenting themselves so that the action to be performed
      can actually be performed. Often these real-world dependencies are only implicit in the order
      details. </p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <a name="bnc"></a>
    <h2>Background and Context</h2>
    <h3>Using Tasks in a RESTful context</h3>
    <p>In a RESTful context, a server functions as a repository of tasks. The server itself, or
      other agents are expected to monitor task activity and initiate appropriate actions to ensure
      task completion, updating the status of the task as it proceeds through its various stages of
      completion. These agents can be coordinated, following well choreographed business logic to
      ensure that tasks are completed. Task management may also be centrally controlled using some
      form of a workflow engine, in which case, the workflow engine itself may update and maintain the
      task resources in the server, and through its orchestration activities ensure that tasks are
      completed. The task resource enables either model of task management yet provides a
      consistent view of the status of tasks being executed in support of healthcare workflows. </p>
    <p>The assignment of tasks into categories by type of task, type of performer and task status
      enable the server to function as a queue of work items.  This queue can be polled or subscribed
      to by various agents, enabling automation of workflows in FHIR using existing search and subscription
      mechanisms.  Owners, requesters, other agents (e.g. workflow managers) can thus be ready to
      initiate the next steps in a complex workflow.</p>
    
      [%stu-note dstu%]
      Currently, task pre-requisites can be represented using Task's `description` element or the <a href="requestorchestration.html">RequestOrchestration</a> resource. We are seeking input from the implementer community in evaluating whether there is need for adding another mechanism to this resource for this purpose.
      </p>
      <p>
      Feedback <a href="https://chat.fhir.org/#narrow/stream/103-Orders-and.20Observation.20WG">here</a>.
      [%end-note%]

  </div>
  <div>
    <a name="bnr"></a>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>

    <p>Task spans both intent and event and tracks the execution through to
    completion. A Task is a workflow step such as cancelling an order,
    fulfilling an order, signing an order, merging a set of records, admitting a
    patient. In contrast, <a href="procedure.html">Procedures</a> are actions
    that are intended to result in a physical or mental change to or for the
    subject (for example, surgery, physiotherapy, training, counseling). A Task resource
    often exists in parallel with clinical resources. For example, a Task could
    request fulfillment of a <a href="servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a>
    ordering a Procedure that would result in a Procedure, <a
    href="observation.html">Observation</a>, <a
    href="diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a>, <a
    href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> or similar resource.  Another
    example would be a Task that requests fulfillment of a <a
    href="communicationrequest.html">CommunicationRequest</a> to be performed
    between various actors.</p>

    <p>As stated above, the task resource tracks the state of a task, enabling
    systems to ensure that tasks are completed. This information is kept
    separate from the operational details necessary to complete the task, as
    those details vary across and even within workflows. That detail is expected
    to be carried in the referenced `focus` of the task. </p>

     <p>Tasks may have named inputs and outputs. Inputs represent
     information that may or must be present in order for a task to
     complete. Outputs represent intermediate or final results produced by a
     task. For example, in a task supporting reading of radiology image, the
     inputs might include both the imaging study to be read, as well as
     relevant prior images. Outputs could represent radiology measurements
     as well as the Radiologist's diagnostic report. </p>

    <p>Inputs and outputs are tracked by the task because workflow
    management activity may automate the transfer of outputs from one task
    to inputs to a subsequent task. </p>

    <p>To facilitate the integration of off the shelf workflow applications
    with FHIR, the task resource may reference a definition.  This
    definition can represent a description of the workflow activity to be
    performed, using a standard workflow description language such as BPEL,
    BPMN, or XPDL, a workflow definition such as those defined in IHE
    profiles, or even simple written instructions explaining a process to be
    performed.</p>

  </div>
</div>
